PART 2 - APPLICATION AND INTERPRETATION OF THE RULES

Contents of this Part

Application of the Rules

2.1

(1) Subject to paragraph (2), these Rules apply to all proceedings in –

(a) county courts;

(b) the High Court; and

(c) the Civil Division of the Court of Appeal.

(2) These Rules do not apply to proceedings of the kinds specified in the first column of the following table (proceedings for which rules may be made under the enactments specified in the second column) except to the extent that they are applied to those proceedings by another enactment –

The glossary

2.2

(1) The glossary at the end of these Rules is a guide to the meaning of certain legal expressions used in the Rules, but is not to be taken as giving those expressions any meaning in the Rules which they do not have in the law generally.

(2) Subject to paragraph (3), words in these Rules which are included in the glossary are followed by‘(GL)’.

(3) The words ‘counterclaim’, ‘damages’, ‘practice form’ and ‘service’, which appear frequently in the Rules, are included in the glossary but are not followed by[‘(GL)’].

Interpretation

2.3

(1) In these Rules –

‘child’ has the meaning given by rule 21.1(2);

‘civil restraint order’ means an order restraining a party –

(a) from making any further applications in current proceedings (a limited civil restraint order);

(b) from issuing certain claims or making certain applications in specified courts (an extended civil restraint order); or

(c) from issuing any claim or making any application in specified courts (a general civil restraint order).

‘claim for personal injuries’ means proceedings in which there is a claim for damages in respect of personal injuries to the claimant or any other person or in respect of a person’s death, and ‘personal injuries’ includes any disease and any impairment of a person’s physical or mental condition;

‘claimant’ means a person who makes a claim;

‘CCR’ is to be interpreted in accordance with Part 50;

‘court officer’ means a member of the court staff;

‘defendant’ means a person against whom a claim is made;

‘defendant's home court’ means –

(a) if the claim is proceeding in a county court, the county court for the district in which the defendant resides or carries on business; and

(b) if the claim is proceeding in the High Court, the district registry for the district in which the defendant resides or carries on business or, where there is no such district registry, the Royal Courts of Justice;

(Rule 6.23 provides for a party to give an address for service)

‘designated money claim’ means any claim which –

(a) is started in a county court under Part 7;

(b) is only a claim for either or both a specified amount of money or an unspecified amount of money; and

(c) is not a claim for which special procedures are provided in these rules;

‘filing’, in relation to a document, means delivering it, by post or otherwise, to the court office;

‘judge’ means, unless the context otherwise requires, a judge, Master or district judge or a person authorised to act as such;

‘jurisdiction’ means, unless the context requires otherwise, England and Wales and any part of the territorial waters of the United Kingdom adjoining England and Wales;

‘legal representative’ means a –

(a) barrister;

(b) solicitor;

(c) solicitor’s employee;

(d) manager of a body recognised under section 9 of the Administration of Justice Act 1985^9; or

(e) person who, for the purposes of the Legal Services Act 2007^10, is an authorised person in relation to an activity which constitutes the conduct of litigation (within the meaning of that Act),

who has been instructed to act for a party in relation to proceedings;

‘litigation friend’ has the meaning given by Part 21;

‘preferred court’ means, if the claim is proceeding in a county court, the county court the claimant has specified in practice form N1 as the court to which the proceedings should be transferred if necessary;

‘protected party’ has the meaning given by rule 21.1(2);

‘RSC’ is to be interpreted in accordance with Part 50;

‘statement of case’ –

(a) means a claim form, particulars of claim where these are not included in a claim form, defence, Part 20 claim, or reply to defence; and

(b) includes any further information given in relation to them voluntarily or by court order under rule 18.1;

‘statement of value’ is to be interpreted in accordance with rule 16.3;

‘summary judgment’ is to be interpreted in accordance with Part 24.

(2) A reference to a ‘specialist list’ is a reference to a list(GL) that has been designated as such by a rule or practice direction.

(3) Where the context requires, a reference to ‘the court’ means a reference to a particular county court, a district registry, or the Royal Courts of Justice.

Power of judge, Master or district judge to perform functions of the court

2.4

Where these Rules provide for the court to perform any act then, except where an enactment, rule or practice direction provides otherwise, that act may be performed –

(a) in relation to proceedings in the High Court, by any judge, Master or district judge of that Court; and

(b) in relation to proceedings in a county court, by any judge or district judge.

Court staff

2.5

(1) Where these Rules require or permit the court to perform an act of a formal or administrative character, that act may be performed by a court officer.

(2) A requirement that a court officer carry out any act at the request of a party is subject to the payment of any fee required by a fees order for the carrying out of that act.

(Rule 3.2 allows a court officer to refer to a judge before taking any step)

Court documents to be sealed

2.6

(1) The court must seal(GL) the following documents on issue –

(a) the claim form; and

(b) any other document which a rule or practice direction requires it to seal.

(2) The court may place the seal(GL) on the document –

(a) by hand; or

(b) by printing a facsimile of the seal on the document whether electronically or otherwise.

(3) A document purporting to bear the court’s seal(GL) shall be admissible in evidence without further proof.

Court’s discretion as to where it deals with cases

2.7

The court may deal with a case at any place that it considers appropriate.

Time

2.8

(1) This rule shows how to calculate any period of time for doing any act which is specified –

(a) by these Rules;

(b) by a practice direction; or

(c) by a judgment or order of the court.

(2) A period of time expressed as a number of days shall be computed as clear days.

(3) In this rule ‘clear days’ means that in computing the number of days –

(a) the day on which the period begins; and

(b) if the end of the period is defined by reference to an event, the day on which that event occurs

are not included.

Examples

(i) Notice of an application must be served at least 3 days before the hearing.

An application is to be heard on Friday 20 October.

The last date for service is Monday 16 October.

(ii) The court is to fix a date for a hearing.

The hearing must be at least 28 days after the date of notice.

If the court gives notice of the date of the hearing on 1 October, the earliest date for the hearing is 30 October.

(iii) Particulars of claim must be served within 14 days of service of the claim form.

The claim form is served on 2 October.

The last day for service of the particulars of claim is 16 October.

(4) Where the specified period –

(a) is 5 days or less; and

(b) includes –

(i) a Saturday or Sunday; or

(ii) a Bank Holiday, Christmas Day or Good Friday,

that day does not count.

Example

Notice of an application must be served at least 3 days before the hearing.

An application is to be heard on Monday 20 October.

The last date for service is Tuesday 14 October.

(5) Subject to the provisions of Practice Direction 5C, when the period specified –

(a) by these Rules or a practice direction; or

(b) by any judgment or court order,

for doing any act at the court office ends on a day on which the office is closed, that act shall be in time if done on the next day on which the court office is open.

Dates for compliance to be calendar dates and to include time of day

2.9

(1) Where the court gives a judgment, order or direction which imposes a time limit for doing any act, the last date for compliance must, wherever practicable –

(a) be expressed as a calendar date; and

(b) include the time of day by which the act must be done.

(2) Where the date by which an act must be done is inserted in any document, the date must, wherever practicable, be expressed as a calendar date.

Meaning of ‘month’ in judgments, etc.

2.10

Where ‘month’ occurs in any judgment, order, direction or other document, it means a calendar month.

Time limits may be varied by parties

2.11

Unless these Rules or a practice direction provide otherwise or the court orders otherwise, the time specified by a rule or by the court for a person to do any act may be varied by the written agreement of the parties.

(Rules 3.8 (sanctions have effect unless defaulting party obtains relief), 28.4 (variation of case management timetable – fast track) and 29.5 (variation of case management timetable – multi-track), provide for time limits that cannot be varied by agreement between the parties)

Footnotes

1986 c.45. Back to text
1981 c.54. Back to text
1894 c.39. Back to text
2005 c. 9. Back to text
1984 c.42. Section 40 was amended by the Courts and Legal Services Act 1990 (c.41), Schedule 18, paragraph 50. Back to text
1976 c.36. Back to text
2002 c.38. Back to text
1983 c.2. Back to text
1985 c. 61. Back to text
2007 c. 29. Back to text

Back to top

PART 3 - THE COURT’S CASE MANAGEMENT POWERS

Contents of this Part

I CASE MANAGEMENT

The court’s general powers of management

3.1

(1) The list of powers in this rule is in addition to any powers given to the court by any other rule or practice direction or by any other enactment or any powers it may otherwise have.

(2) Except where these Rules provide otherwise, the court may –

(a) extend or shorten the time for compliance with any rule, practice direction or court order (even if an application for extension is made after the time for compliance has expired);

(b) adjourn or bring forward a hearing;

(c) require a party or a party’s legal representative to attend the court;

(d) hold a hearing and receive evidence by telephone or by using any other method of direct oral communication;

(e) direct that part of any proceedings (such as a counterclaim) be dealt with as separate proceedings;

(f) stay(GL) the whole or part of any proceedings or judgment either generally or until a specified date or event;

(g) consolidate proceedings;

(h) try two or more claims on the same occasion;

(i) direct a separate trial of any issue;

(j) decide the order in which issues are to be tried;

(k) exclude an issue from consideration;

(l) dismiss or give judgment on a claim after a decision on a preliminary issue;

(ll) order any party to file and exchange a costs budget;

(m) take any other step or make any other order for the purpose of managing the case and furthering the overriding objective.

(3) When the court makes an order, it may –

(a) make it subject to conditions, including a condition to pay a sum of money into court; and

(b) specify the consequence of failure to comply with the order or a condition.

(4) Where the court gives directions it will take into account whether or not a party has complied with the Practice Direction (Pre-Action Conduct) and any relevant pre-action protocol(GL).

(5) The court may order a party to pay a sum of money into court if that party has, without good reason, failed to comply with a rule, practice direction or a relevant pre-action protocol.

(6) When exercising its power under paragraph (5) the court must have regard to –

(a) the amount in dispute; and

(b) the costs which the parties have incurred or which they may incur.

(6A) Where a party pays money into court following an order under paragraph (3) or (5), the money shall be security for any sum payable by that party to any other party in the proceedings.

(7) A power of the court under these Rules to make an order includes a power to vary or revoke the order.

(8) The court may contact the parties from time to time in order to monitor compliance with directions. The parties must respond promptly to any such enquiries from the court.

Court officer’s power to refer to a judge

3.2 Where a step is to be taken by a court officer–

(a) the court officer may consult a judge before taking that step;

(b) the step may be taken by a judge instead of the court officer.

Court’s power to make order of its own initiative

3.3

(1) Except where a rule or some other enactment provides otherwise, the court may exercise its powers on an application or of its own initiative.

(Part 23 sets out the procedure for making an application)

(2) Where the court proposes to make an order of its own initiative –

(a) it may give any person likely to be affected by the order an opportunity to make representations; and

(b) where it does so it must specify the time by and the manner in which the representations must be made.

(3) Where the court proposes –

(a) to make an order of its own initiative; and

(b) to hold a hearing to decide whether to make the order,
it must give each party likely to be affected by the order at least 3 days’ notice of the hearing.

(4) The court may make an order of its own initiative, without hearing the parties or giving them an opportunity to make representations.

(5) Where the court has made an order under paragraph (4) –

(a) a party affected by the order may apply to have it set aside(GL), varied or stayed(GL); and

(b) the order must contain a statement of the right to make such an application.

(6) An application under paragraph (5)(a) must be made –

(a) within such period as may be specified by the court; or

(b) if the court does not specify a period, not more than 7 days after the date on which the order was served on the party making the application.

(7) If the court of its own initiative strikes out a statement of case or dismisses an application,

(including an application for permission to appeal or for permission to apply for judicial review) and it considers that the claim or application is totally without merit –

(a) the court’s order must record that fact; and

(b) the court must at the same time consider whether it is appropriate to make a civil restraint order.

Power to strike out a statement of case

3.4

(1) In this rule and rule 3.5, reference to a statement of case includes reference to part of a statement of case.

(2) The court may strike out(GL) a statement of case if it appears to the court –

(a) that the statement of case discloses no reasonable grounds for bringing or defending the claim;

(b) that the statement of case is an abuse of the court’s process or is otherwise likely to obstruct the just disposal of the proceedings; or

(c) that there has been a failure to comply with a rule, practice direction or court order.

(3) When the court strikes out a statement of case it may make any consequential order it considers appropriate.

(4) Where –

(a) the court has struck out a claimant’s statement of case;

(b) the claimant has been ordered to pay costs to the defendant; and

(c) before the claimant pays those costs, he starts another claim against the same defendant, arising out of facts which are the same or substantially the same as those relating to the claim in which the statement of case was struck out,
the court may, on the application of the defendant, stay(GL) that other claim until the costs of the first claim have been paid.

(5) Paragraph (2) does not limit any other power of the court to strike out(GL) a statement of case.

(6) If the court strikes out a claimant’s statement of case and it considers that the claim is totally without merit –

(a) the court’s order must record that fact; and

(b) the court must at the same time consider whether it is appropriate to make a civil restraint order.

Judgment without trial after striking out

3.5

(1) This rule applies where –

(a) the court makes an order which includes a term that the statement of case of a party shall be struck out if the party does not comply with the order; and

(b) the party against whom the order was made does not comply with it.

(2) A party may obtain judgment with costs by filing a request for judgment if –

(a) the order referred to in paragraph (1)(a) relates to the whole of a statement of case; and

(b) where the party wishing to obtain judgment is the claimant, the claim is for –

(i) a specified amount of money;

(ii) an amount of money to be decided by the court;

(iii) delivery of goods where the claim form gives the defendant the alternative of paying their value; or

(iv) any combination of these remedies.

(3) Where judgment is obtained under this rule in a case to which paragraph (2)(b)(iii) applies, it will be judgment requiring the defendant to deliver goods, or (if he does not do so) pay the value of the goods as decided by the court (less any payments made).

(4) The request must state that the right to enter judgment has arisen because the court’s order has not been complied with.

(5) A party must make an application in accordance with Part 23 if he wishes to obtain judgment under this rule in a case to which paragraph (2) does not apply.

Automatic Transfer

3.5A If –

(a) a claimant files a request for judgment which includes an amount of money to be decided by the court in accordance with rule 3.5; and

(b) the claim is a designated money claim,
the court will transfer the claim to the preferred court upon receipt of the request for judgment.

Setting aside judgment entered after striking out

3.6

(1) A party against whom the court has entered judgment under rule 3.5 may apply to the court to set the judgment aside.

(2) An application under paragraph (1) must be made not more than 14 days after the judgment has been served on the party making the application.

(3) If the right to enter judgment had not arisen at the time when judgment was entered, the court must set aside(GL) the judgment.
(4) If the application to set aside(GL) is made for any other reason, rule 3.9 (relief from sanctions) shall apply.

Sanctions for non-payment of certain fees

3.7

(1) This rule applies where –

(a) a directions questionnaire or a pre-trial check list (listing questionnaire) is filed without payment of the fee specified by the relevant Fees Order;

(b) the court dispenses with the need for a directions questionnaire or a pre-trial check list or both;

(c) these Rules do not require a directions questionnaire or a pre-trial check list to be filed in relation to the claim in question;

(d) the court has made an order giving permission to proceed with a claim for judicial review; or

(e) the fee payable for a hearing specified by the relevant Fees Order is not paid.

(Rule 26.3 provides for the court to dispense with the need for a directions questionnaire and rules 28.5 and 29.6 provide for the court to dispense with the need for a pre-trial check list)

(Rule 54.12 provides for the service of the order giving permission to proceed with a claim for judicial review)

(2) The court will serve a notice on the claimant requiring payment of the fee specified in the relevant Fees Order if, at the time the fee is due, the claimant has not paid it or made an application for full or part remission.

(3) The notice will specify the date by which the claimant must pay the fee.

(4) If the claimant does not –

(a) pay the fee; or

(b) make an application for full or part remission of the fee,
by the date specified in the notice –

(i) the claim will automatically be struck out without further order of the court; and

(ii) the claimant will be liable for the costs which the defendant has incurred unless the court orders otherwise.

(Rule 44.9 provides for the basis of assessment where a right to costs arises under this rule and contains provisions about when a costs order is deemed to have been made and applying for an order under section 194(3) of the Legal Services Act 2007^1)

(5) Where an application for –

(a) full or part remission of a fee is refused, the court will serve notice on the claimant requiring payment of the full fee by the date specified in the notice; or

(b) part remission of a fee is granted, the court will serve notice on the claimant requiring payment of the balance of the fee by the date specified in the notice."; and

(6) If the claimant does not pay the fee by the date specified in the notice –

(a) the claim will automatically be struck out without further order of the court; and

(b) the claimant will be liable for the costs which the defendant has incurred unless the court orders otherwise.

(7) If –

(a) a claimant applies to have the claim reinstated; and

(b) the court grants relief,
the relief will be conditional on the claimant either paying the fee or filing evidence of full or part remission of the fee within the period specified in paragraph (8).

(8) The period referred to in paragraph (7) is –

(a) if the order granting relief is made at a hearing at which the claimant is present or represented, 2 days from the date of the order;

(b) in any other case, 7 days from the date of service of the order on the claimant.

3.7A

(1) This rule applies where–

(a) a defendant files a counterclaim without –

(i) payment of the fee specified by the relevant Fees Order; or

(ii) making an application for full or part remission of the fee; or

(b) the proceedings continue on the counterclaim alone and –

(i) a directions questionnaire or a pre-trial check list (listing questionnaire) is filed without payment of the fee specified by the relevant Fees Order;

(ii) the court dispenses with the need for a directions questionnaire or a pre-trial check list or both;

(iii) these Rules do not require a directions questionnaire or a pre-trial checklist to be filed in relation to the claim in question; or

(iv) the fee payable for a hearing specified by the relevant Fees Order is not paid.

(2) The court will serve a notice on the defendant requiring payment of the fee specified in the relevant Fees Order if, at the time the fee is due, the defendant has not paid it or made an application for full or part remission.

(3) The notice will specify the date by which the defendant must pay the fee.

(4) If the defendant does not –

(a) pay the fee; or

(b) make an application for full or part remission of the fee,
by the date specified in the notice, the counterclaim will automatically be struck out without further order of the court.

(5) Where an application for –

(a) full or part remission of a fee is refused, the court will serve notice on the defendant requiring payment of the full fee by the date specified in the notice; or

(b) part remission of a fee is granted, the court will serve notice on the defendant requiring payment of the balance of the fee by the date specified in the notice.

(6) If the defendant does not pay the fee by the date specified in the notice, the counterclaim will automatically be struck out without further order of the court.

(7) If –

(a) the defendant applies to have the counterclaim reinstated; and

(b) the court grants relief,
the relief will be conditional on the defendant either paying the fee or filing evidence of full or part remission of the fee within the period specified in paragraph (8).

(8) The period referred to in paragraph (7) is –

(a) if the order granting relief is made at a hearing at which the defendant is present or represented, 2 days from the date of the order;

(b) in any other case, 7 days from the date of service of the order on the defendant.

Sanctions for dishonouring cheque

3.7B

(1) This rule applies where any fee is paid by cheque and that cheque is subsequently dishonoured.

(2) The court will serve a notice on the paying party requiring payment of the fee which will specify the date by which the fee must be paid.

(3) If the fee is not paid by the date specified in the notice –

(a) where the fee is payable by the claimant, the claim will automatically be struck out without further order of the court;

(b) where the fee is payable by the defendant, the defence will automatically be struck out without further order of the court,

and the paying party shall be liable for the costs which any other party has incurred unless the court orders otherwise.

(Rule 44.9 provides for the basis of assessment where a right to costs arises under this rule)

(4) If –

(a) the paying party applies to have the claim or defence reinstated; and

(b) the court grants relief,

the relief shall be conditional on that party paying the fee within the period specified in paragraph (5).

(5) The period referred to in paragraph (4) is –

(a) if the order granting relief is made at a hearing at which the paying party is present or represented, 2 days from the date of the order;

(b) in any other case, 7 days from the date of service of the order on the paying party.

(6) For the purposes of this rule, 'claimant' includes a Part 20 claimant and 'claim form' includes a Part 20 claim.

Sanctions have effect unless defaulting party obtains relief

3.8

(1) Where a party has failed to comply with a rule, practice direction or court order, any sanction for failure to comply imposed by the rule, practice direction or court order has effect unless the party in default applies for and obtains relief from the sanction.

(Rule 3.9 sets out the circumstances which the court will consider on an application to grant relief from a sanction)

(2) Where the sanction is the payment of costs, the party in default may only obtain relief by appealing against the order for costs.

(3) Where a rule, practice direction or court order –

(a) requires a party to do something within a specified time, and

(b) specifies the consequence of failure to comply,

the time for doing the act in question may not be extended by agreement between the parties.

Relief from sanctions

3.9

(1) On an application for relief from any sanction imposed for a failure to comply with any rule, practice direction or court order, the court will consider all the circumstances of the case, so as to enable it to deal justly with the application, including the need –

(a) for litigation to be conducted efficiently and at proportionate cost; and

(b) to enforce compliance with rules, practice directions and orders.

(2) An application for relief must be supported by evidence.

General power of the court to rectify matters where there has been an error of procedure

3.10 Where there has been an error of procedure such as a failure to comply with a rule or practice direction –

(a) the error does not invalidate any step taken in the proceedings unless the court so orders; and

(b) the court may make an order to remedy the error.

Power of the court to make civil restraint orders

3.11 A practice direction may set out –

(a) the circumstances in which the court has the power to make a civil restraint order against a party to proceedings;

(b) the procedure where a party applies for a civil restraint order against another party; and

(c) the consequences of the court making a civil restraint order.

II COSTS MANAGEMENT

Application of this Section and the purpose of costs management

3.12

(1) This Section and Practice Direction 3E apply to all multi-track cases commenced on or after 1st April 2013, except –

(a) cases in the Admiralty and Commercial Courts;

(b) such cases in the Chancery Division as the Chancellor of the High Court may direct; and

(c) such cases in the Technology and Construction Court and the Mercantile Court as the President of the Queen’s Bench Division may direct,

unless the proceedings are the subject of fixed costs or scale costs or the court otherwise orders. This Section and Practice Direction 3E will apply to any other proceedings (including applications) where the court so orders.

(2) The purpose of costs management is that the court should manage both the steps to be taken and the costs to be incurred by the parties to any proceedings so as to further the overriding objective.

Filing and exchanging budgets

3.13 Unless the court otherwise orders, all parties except litigants in person must file and exchange budgets as required by the rules or as the court otherwise directs. Each party must do so by the date specified in the notice served under rule 26.3(1) or, if no such date is specified, seven days before the first case management conference.

Failure to file a budget

3.14 Unless the court otherwise orders, any party which fails to file a budget despite being required to do so will be treated as having filed a budget comprising only the applicable court fees.

Costs management orders

3.15

(1) In addition to exercising its other powers, the court may manage the costs to be incurred by any party in any proceedings.

(2) The court may at any time make a ‘costs management order’. By such order the court will –

(a) record the extent to which the budgets are agreed between the parties;

(b) in respect of budgets or parts of budgets which are not agreed, record the court’s approval after making appropriate revisions.

(3) If a costs management order has been made, the court will thereafter control the parties’ budgets in respect of recoverable costs.

Costs management conferences

3.16

(1) Any hearing which is convened solely for the purpose of costs management (for example, to approve a revised budget) is referred to as a ‘costs management conference’.

(2) Where practicable, costs management conferences should be conducted by telephone or in writing.

Court to have regard to budgets and to take account of costs

3.17

(1) When making any case management decision, the court will have regard to any available budgets of the parties and will take into account the costs involved in each procedural step.

(2) Paragraph (1) applies whether or not the court has made a costs management order.

Assessing costs on the standard basis where a costs management order has been made

3.18 In any case where a costs management order has been made, when assessing costs on the standard basis, the court will –

(a) have regard to the receiving party’s last approved or agreed budget for each phase of the proceedings; and

(b) not depart from such approved or agreed budget unless satisfied that there is good reason to do so.

(Attention is drawn to rule 44.3(2)(a) and rule 44.3(5), which concern proportionality of costs.)

III COSTS CAPPING

Costs capping orders – General

3.19

(1) A costs capping order is an order limiting the amount of future costs (including disbursements) which a party may recover pursuant to an order for costs subsequently made.

(2) In this rule, ‘future costs’ means costs incurred in respect of work done after the date of the costs capping order but excluding the amount of any additional liability.

(3) This rule does not apply to protective costs orders.

(4) A costs capping order may be in respect of –

(a) the whole litigation; or

(b) any issues which are ordered to be tried separately.

(5) The court may at any stage of proceedings make a costs capping order against all or any of the parties, if –

(a) it is in the interests of justice to do so;

(b) there is a substantial risk that without such an order costs will be disproportionately incurred; and

(c) it is not satisfied that the risk in subparagraph (b) can be adequately controlled by –

(i) case management directions or orders made under this Part; and

(ii) detailed assessment of costs.

(6) In considering whether to exercise its discretion under this rule, the court will consider all the circumstances of the case, including –

(a) whether there is a substantial imbalance between the financial position of the parties;

(b) whether the costs of determining the amount of the cap are likely to be proportionate to the overall costs of the litigation;

(c) the stage which the proceedings have reached; and

(d) the costs which have been incurred to date and the future costs.

(7) A costs capping order, once made, will limit the costs recoverable by the party subject to the order unless a party successfully applies to vary the order. No such variation will be made unless –

(a) there has been a material and substantial change of circumstances since the date when the order was made; or

(b) there is some other compelling reason why a variation should be made.

Application for a costs capping order

3.20

(1) An application for a costs capping order must be made on notice in accordance with Part 23.

(2) The application notice must –

(a) set out –

(i) whether the costs capping order is in respect of the whole of the litigation or a particular issue which is ordered to be tried separately; and

(ii) why a costs capping order should be made; and

(b) be accompanied by a budget setting out –

(i) the costs (and disbursements) incurred by the applicant to date; and

(ii) the costs (and disbursements) which the applicant is likely to incur in the future conduct of the proceedings.

(3) The court may give directions for the determination of the application and such directions may –

(a) direct any party to the proceedings –

(i) to file a schedule of costs in the form set out in paragraph 3 of Practice Direction 3F – Costs capping;

(ii) to file written submissions on all or any part of the issues arising;

(b) fix the date and time estimate of the hearing of the application;

(c) indicate whether the judge hearing the application will sit with an assessor at the hearing of the application; and

(d) include any further directions as the court sees fit.

Application to vary a costs capping order

3.21 An application to vary a costs capping order must be made by application notice pursuant to Part 23.

Footnotes

1. 2007 c.29. Back to text

PRACTICE DIRECTION 3D – MESOTHELIOMA CLAIMS

This Practice Direction supplements CPR, rule 3.1

Contents of this Practice Direction

Scope

1 This Practice Direction applies to claims for compensation for mesothelioma.

Definitions

2 In this Practice Direction –

‘show cause procedure’ means (without prejudice to the court’s general case management powers in Part 3 of the CPR) the procedure set out in paragraph 6;

‘outline submissions showing cause’ means an outline or skeleton argument of the defendant's case within the show cause procedure; and

‘standard interim payment’ means the standard payment in respect of interim damages, and (if appropriate) interim costs and disbursements as determined from time to time by the Head of Civil Justice. The amount of this payment is currently £50,000.

Starting proceedings

3.1 The claim form and every statement of case must be marked with the title ‘Living Mesothelioma Claim’ or ‘Fatal Mesothelioma Claim’ as appropriate.

3.2 In order for the court to adopt the show cause procedure in the first case management conference, the claimant must file and serve any witness statements about liability (as are available) –

(1) either –

(a) at the same time as filing and serving the claim form and (where appropriate) the particulars of claim; or

(b) as soon as possible after filing and serving the claim form and (where appropriate) the particulars of claim; and

(2) in any event not less than 7 days before the case management conference.

3.3 Any witness statement about liability must identify as far as is possible –

(1) the alleged victim's employment history and history of exposure to asbestos;

(2) the identity of any employer where exposure to asbestos of the alleged victim is alleged;

(3) details of any self employment in which the alleged victim may have been exposed; and

(4) details of all claims made and payments received under the Pneumoconiosis etc. (Workers' Compensation) Act 1979.

3.4 The claimant must also attach to the claim form –

(1) a work history from H M Revenue and Customs (where available); and

(2) any pre-action letter of claim.

Claimants with severely limited life expectancy

4.1 Where the claimant believes that the claim is particularly urgent then on issue of the claim form, the claimant –

(1) may request in writing that the court file is placed immediately before a judge nominated to manage such cases in order to fix a case management conference; and

(2) must explain in writing to the court why the claim is urgent.

4.2 Where the court decides that the claim is urgent (and notwithstanding that a claim has not yet been served or a defence has not yet been filed) it will –

(1) fix the date for the case management conference to take place within a short period of time; and

(2) give directions as to the date by which the claimant must serve the claim form if it has not been served already.

Fixing the case management conference for other claims

5.1 Where paragraph 4 does not apply and –

(1) a defence is filed by the defendant or one of the defendants (where there is more than one); or

(2) the claimant has obtained a default judgment,

the court file will be referred to a judge nominated to manage such cases and the judge will give directions for the date of the case management conference.

5.2 Claims marked ‘Living Mesothelioma Claim’ will be given priority when fixing a case management conference.

The show cause procedure

6.1 The show cause procedure is a requirement by the court, of its own initiative and usually on a ‘costs in the case’ basis, for the defendant to identify the evidence and legal arguments that give the defendant a real prospect of success on any or all issues of liability. The court will use this procedure for the resolution of mesothelioma claims.

6.2 At the first case management conference, unless there is good reason not to do so, the defendant should be prepared to show cause why –

(1) a judgment on liability should not be entered against the defendant; and

(2) a standard interim payment on account of damages and (if appropriate) costs and disbursements should not be made by the defendant by a specified date.

6.3 At the first case management conference if liability remains in issue the court will normally order that the defendant show cause within a further given period.

6.4 The order requiring the defendant to show cause within a further given period will direct –

(1) that the defendant file and serve on the claimant by a specified date outline submissions showing cause and –

(a) if the outline submissions are not filed and served by a specified date, judgment, for a sum to be determined by the court, will be entered against the defendant without the need for any further order and the defendant will be ordered to make a standard interim payment by a specified date; or

(b) if the outline submissions are filed and served by the specified date, the claim will be listed for a show cause hearing; or

(2) that the defendant show cause at a hearing on a date fixed by the court.

6.5 At the first case management conference the court will –

(1) fix the date or trial window for the determination of damages and give any other case management directions as appropriate where the defendant admits liability or judgment is entered;

(2) fix the date or trial window for the determination of damages and give any other case management directions as appropriate where an order to show cause under paragraph 6.3 has been made (if the defendant subsequently shows cause then the determination date or trial window may be utilised for the trial of any issue); or

(3) in cases in which there is to be a trial on liability, give directions including the date or window for the trial.

6.6 Where the defendant fails to show cause on some issues, the court will normally enter judgment on those issues.

6.7 Where the defendant fails to show cause on all issues, the court will enter judgment for a sum to be determined and will normally order that a standard interim payment be made.

6.8 Where the defendant succeeds in showing cause on some or all issues, the court will order a trial of those issues. The court may also require the issue of quantum or apportionment (as appropriate) to be dealt with at the trial provided that it does not delay the date for the fixing of the trial.

Setting the trial date

7.1 In Living Mesothelioma Claims the date of the determination of damages or the trial will generally not be more than 16 weeks following service of the claim form.

7.2 In Fatal Mesothelioma Claims the hearing date may be more than 16 weeks following service of the claim form.

Taking evidence by deposition

8 Any party who for good reason wishes evidence to be taken by deposition may apply to the court at any time for such an order. However, the court will normally expect that such a request is made at a case management conference. The order will include a direction for the recording of such evidence on DVD and for the provision of a transcript. The parties must also be prepared to arrange for the provision of equipment to view the DVD by the court.

(Part 34 contains provisions for evidence to be taken by deposition.)

Compliance with pre-action protocols

9 In Living Mesothelioma Claims the court may decide not to require strict adherence to Practice Direction (Pre-Action Conduct) and any relevant pre-action protocol.

PRACTICE DIRECTION 6A – SERVICE WITHIN THE UNITED KINGDOM

This Practice Direction supplements CPR Part 6

Contents of this Practice Direction

Scope of this Practice Direction

1.1  This Practice Direction supplements –

(1) Section II (service of the claim form in the jurisdiction) of Part 6;

(2) Section III (service of documents other than the claim form in the United Kingdom) of Part 6; and

(3) rule 6.40 in relation to the method of service on a party in Scotland or Northern Ireland.

(Practice Direction 6B contains provisions relevant to service on a party in Scotland or Northern Ireland, including provisions about service out of the jurisdiction where permission is and is not required and the period for responding to an application notice.)

When service may be by document exchange

2.1  Service by document exchange (DX) may take place only where –

(1) the address at which the party is to be served includes a numbered box at a DX, or

(2) the writing paper of the party who is to be served or of the solicitor acting for that party sets out a DX box number, and

(3) the party or the solicitor acting for that party has not indicated in writing that they are unwilling to accept service by DX.

How service is effected by post, an alternative service provider or DX

3.1  Service by post, DX or other service which provides for delivery on the next business day is effected by –

(1) placing the document in a post box;

(2) leaving the document with or delivering the document to the relevant service provider; or

(3) having the document collected by the relevant service provider.

Service by fax or other electronic means

4.1  Subject to the provisions of rule 6.23(5) and (6), where a document is to be served by fax or other electronic means –

(1) the party who is to be served or the solicitor acting for that party must previously have indicated in writing to the party serving –

(a) that the party to be served or the solicitor is willing to accept service by fax or other electronic means; and

(b) the fax number, e-mail address or other electronic identification to which it must be sent; and

(2) the following are to be taken as sufficient written indications for the purposes of paragraph 4.1(1) –

(a) a fax number set out on the writing paper of the solicitor acting for the party to be served;

(b) an e-mail address set out on the writing paper of the solicitor acting for the party to be served but only where it is stated that the e-mail address may be used for service; or

(c) a fax number, e-mail address or electronic identification set out on a statement of case or a response to a claim filed with the court.

4.2  Where a party intends to serve a document by electronic means (other than by fax) that party must first ask the party who is to be served whether there are any limitations to the recipient's agreement to accept service by such means (for example, the format in which documents are to be sent and the maximum size of attachments that may be received).

4.3  Where a document is served by electronic means, the party serving the document need not in addition send or deliver a hard copy.

Service on members of the Regular Forces and United States Air Force

5.1  The provisions that apply to service on members of the regular forces (within the meaning of the Armed Forces Act 2006) and members of the United States Air Force are annexed to this practice direction.

Personal service on a company or other corporation

6.1  Personal service on a registered company or corporation in accordance with rule 6.5(3) is effected by leaving a document with a person holding a senior position.

6.2  Each of the following persons is a person holding a senior position –

(1) in respect of a registered company or corporation, a director, the treasurer, the secretary of the company or corporation, the chief executive, a manager or other officer of the company or corporation; and

(2) in respect of a corporation which is not a registered company, in addition to any of the persons set out in sub-paragraph (1), the mayor, the chairman, the president, a town clerk or similar officer of the corporation.

Certificate of service where claimant serves the claim form

7.1  Where, pursuant to rule 6.17(2), the claimant files a certificate of service, the claimant is not required to and should not file –

(1) a further copy of the claim form with the certificate of service; and

(2) a further copy of –

(a) the particulars of claim (where not included in the claim form); or

(b) any document attached to the particulars of claim,

with the certificate of service where that document has already been filed with the court.

(Rule 7.4 requires the claimant to file a copy of the particulars of claim (where served separately from the claim form) within 7 days of service on the defendant.)

Service by the court

8.1  Where the court serves a document in accordance with rule 6.4 or 6.21(2), the method will normally be first class post.

Application for an order for service by an alternative method or at an alternative place

9.1  Where an application for an order under rule 6.15 is made before the document is served, the application must be supported by evidence stating –

(1) the reason why an order is sought;

(2) what alternative method or place is proposed, and

(3) why the applicant believes that the document is likely to reach the person to be served by the method or at the place proposed.

9.2  Where the application for an order is made after the applicant has taken steps to bring the document to the attention of the person to be served by an alternative method or at an alternative place, the application must be supported by evidence stating –

(1) the reason why the order is sought;

(2) what alternative method or alternative place was used;

(3) when the alternative method or place was used; and

(4) why the applicant believes that the document is likely to have reached the person to be served by the alternative method or at the alternative place.

9.3  Examples –

(1) an application to serve by posting or delivering to an address of a person who knows the other party must be supported by evidence that if posted or delivered to that address, the document is likely to be brought to the attention of the other party;

(2) an application to serve by sending a SMS text message or leaving a voicemail message at a particular telephone number saying where the document is must be accompanied by evidence that the person serving the document has taken, or will take, appropriate steps to ensure that the party being served is using that telephone number and is likely to receive the message; and

(3) an application to serve by e-mail to a company (where paragraph 4.1 does not apply) must be supported by evidence that the e-mail address to which the document will be sent is one which is likely to come to the attention of a person holding a senior position in that company.

Deemed service of a document other than a claim form

10.1  Rule 6.26 contains provisions about deemed service of a document other than a claim form. Examples of how deemed service is calculated are set out below.

10.2

Example 1

Where the document is posted (by first class post) on a Monday (a business day), the day of deemed service is the following Wednesday (a business day).

10.3

Example 2

Where the document is left in a numbered box at the DX on a Friday (a business day), the day of deemed service is the following Monday (a business day).

10.4

Example 3

Where the document is sent by fax on a Saturday and the transmission of that fax is completed by 4.30p.m. on that day, the day of deemed service is the following Monday (a business day).

10.5

Example 4

Where the document is served personally before 4.30p.m. on a Sunday, the day of deemed service is the next day (Monday, a business day).

10.6

Example 5

Where the document is delivered to a permitted address after 4.30p.m. on the Thursday (a business day) before Good Friday, the day of deemed service is the following Tuesday (a business day) as the Monday is a bank holiday.

10.7

Example 6

Where the document is posted (by first class post) on a bank holiday Monday, the day of deemed service is the following Wednesday (a business day).

Annex

Service on Members of the Regular Forces

1.

The following information is for litigants and legal representatives who wish to serve legal documents in civil proceedings in the courts of England and Wales on parties to the proceedings who are (or who, at the material time, were) members of the regular forces (as defined in the Armed Forces Act 2006).

2.

The proceedings may take place in the county court or the High Court, and the documents to be served may be claim forms, interim application notices and pre-action application notices. Proceedings for divorce or maintenance and proceedings in the Family Courts generally are subject to special rules as to service which are explained in a practice direction issued by the Senior District Judge of the Principal Registry on 26 June 1979.

3.

In this Annex, the person wishing to effect service is referred to as the ‘claimant’ and the member of the regular forces to be served is referred to as ‘the member’; the expression ‘overseas’ means outside the United Kingdom.

Enquiries as to address

4.

As a first step, the claimant’s legal representative will need to find out where the member is serving, if this is not already known. For this purpose the claimant’s legal representative should write to the appropriate officer of the Ministry of Defence as specified in paragraph 10 below.

5.

The letter of enquiry should in every case show that the writer is a legal representative and that the enquiry is made solely with a view to the service of legal documents in civil proceedings.

6.

In all cases the letter must give the full name, service number, rank or rate, and Ship, Arm or Trade, Regiment or Corps and Unit or as much of this information as is available. Failure to quote the service number and the rank or rate may result either in failure to identify the member or in considerable delay.

7.

The letter must contain an undertaking by the legal representative that, if the address is given, it will be used solely for the purpose of issuing and serving documents in the proceedings and that so far as is possible the legal representative will disclose the address only to the court and not to the claimant or to any other person or body. A legal representative in the service of a public authority or private company must undertake that the address will be used solely for the purpose of issuing and serving documents in the proceedings and that the address will not be disclosed so far as is possible to any other part of the legal representative's employing organisation or to any other person but only to the court. Normally on receipt of the required information and undertaking the appropriate office will give the service address.

8.

If the legal representative does not give the undertaking, the only information that will be given is whether the member is at that time serving in England or Wales, Scotland, Northern Ireland or overseas.

9.

It should be noted that a member’s address which ends with a British Forces Post Office address and reference (BFPO) will nearly always indicate that the member is serving overseas.

10.

The letter of enquiry should be addressed as follows –

(a) Royal Navy and Royal Marine Officers, Ratings and Other Ranks

Director Naval Personnel
Fleet Headquarters
MP 3.1
Leach Building
Whale Island
Portsmouth
Hampshire
PO2 8BY

Army Officers and other Ranks –

Army Personnel Centre
Disclosures 1
MP 520
Kentigern House
65 Brown Street
Glasgow
G2 8EX

Royal Air Force Officers and Other Ranks –

Manning 22E
RAF Disclosures
Room 221B
Trenchard Hall
RAF Cranwell
Sleaford
Lincolnshire
NG34 8HB

Assistance in serving documents on members

11.

Once the claimant’s legal representative has ascertained the member’s address, the legal representative may use that address as the address for service by post, in cases where this method of service is allowed by the Civil Procedure Rules. There are, however, some situations in which service of the proceedings, whether in the High Court or in the county court, must be effected personally; in these cases an appointment will have to be sought, through the Commanding Officer of the Unit, Establishment or Ship concerned, for the purpose of effecting service. The procedure for obtaining an appointment is described below, and it applies whether personal service is to be effected by the claimant’s legal representative or the legal representative’s agent or by a court bailiff, or, in the case of proceedings served overseas (with the leave of the court) through the British Consul or the foreign judicial authority.

12.

The procedure for obtaining an appointment to effect personal service is by application to the Commanding Officer of the Unit, Establishment or Ship in which the member is serving. The Commanding Officer may grant permission for the document server to enter the Unit, Establishment or Ship but if this is not appropriate the Commanding Officer may offer arrangements for the member to attend at a place in the vicinity of the Unit, Establishment or Ship in order that the member may be served. If suitable arrangements cannot be made the legal representative will have evidence that personal service is impracticable, which may be useful in an application for service by an alternative method or at an alternative place.

General

13.

Subject to the procedure outlined in paragraphs 11 and 12, there are no special arrangements to assist in the service of legal documents when a member is outside the United Kingdom. The appropriate office will, however, give an approximate date when the member is likely to return to the United Kingdom.

14.

It sometimes happens that a member has left the regular forces by the time an enquiry as to address is made. If the claimant's legal representative confirms that the proceedings result from an occurrence when the member was in the regular forces and the legal representative gives the undertaking referred to in paragraph 7, the last known private address after discharge will normally be provided. In no other case, however, will the Ministry of Defence disclose the private address of a member of the regular forces.

Service on Members of United States Air Force

15.

In addition to the information contained in the memorandum of 26 July 1979, and after some doubts having been expressed as to the correct procedure to be followed by persons having civil claims against members of the United States Air Force in England and Wales, the Lord Chancellor’s Office (as it was then) issued the following notes for guidance with the approval of the appropriate United States authorities.

16.

Instructions have been issued by the United States authorities to the commanding officers of all their units in England and Wales that every facility is to be given for the service of documents in civil proceedings on members of the United States Air Force. The proper course to be followed by a creditor or other person having a claim against a member of the United States Air Force is for that person to communicate with the commanding officer or, where the unit concerned has a legal officer, with the legal officer of the defendant's unit requesting the provision of facilities for the service of documents on the defendant. It is not possible for the United States authorities to act as arbitrators when a civil claim is made against a member of their forces. It is, therefore, essential that the claim should either be admitted by the defendant or judgment should be obtained on it, whether in the High Court or a county court. If a claim has been admitted or judgment has been obtained and the claimant has failed to obtain satisfaction within a reasonable period, the claimant’s proper course is then to write to: Office of the Staff Judge Advocate, Headquarters, Third Air Force, R.A.F. Mildenhall, Suffolk, enclosing a copy of the defendant’s written admission of the claim or, as the case may be, a copy of the judgment. Steps will then be taken by the Staff Judge Advocate to ensure that the matter is brought to the defendant's attention with a view to prompt satisfaction of the claim.

Annex 2

1978 No 1910

European Communities (Services of Lawyers) Order 1978

Citation and commencement

1.

This Order may be cited as the European Communities (Services of Lawyers) Order 1978 and shall come into operation on 1st March 1979.

Interpretation

2.

In this Order, unless the context otherwise requires –

‘advocate’, ‘barrister’ and ‘solicitor’ mean, in relation to any part of the United Kingdom, a person practising in that part as an advocate, barrister or solicitor as the case may be;

‘country of origin’, in relation to a European lawyer, means the country or countries in which he is established;

‘the Directive’ means the European Communities Council Directive No. 77/249/EEC to facilitate the effective exercise by lawyers of freedom to provide services;

‘European lawyer’ means a person entitled to pursue his professional activities in a state in column 1 under the designation referred to in column 2 –

‘own professional authority’, in relation to a European lawyer, means an authority entitled to exercise disciplinary authority over him in his member State of origin.

3.

(1) The Interpretation Act 1978 shall apply to this Order as it applies to subordinate legislation made after the commencement of that Act.

(2) Unless the context otherwise requires, any reference in this Order to a numbered article or to the Schedule is a reference to an article of, or the Schedule to, this Order.

Purpose of Order

4.

The provisions of this Order shall have effect for the purpose of enabling a European lawyer to pursue his professional activities in any part of the United Kingdom by providing, under the conditions specified in or permitted by the Directive, services otherwise reserved to advocates, barristers and solicitors; and services which may be so provided are hereafter in this Order referred to as services.

Representation in legal proceedings

5.

No enactment or rule of law or practice shall prevent a European lawyer from providing any service in relation to any proceedings, whether civil or criminal, before any court, tribunal or public authority (including appearing before and addressing the court, tribunal or public authority) by reason only that he is not an advocate, barrister or solicitor; provided that throughout he is instructed with, and acts in conjunction with, an advocate, barrister or solicitor who is entitled to practise before the court, tribunal or public authority concerned and who could properly provide the service in question.

6.

Nothing in this Order shall enable a European lawyer –

(a) if he is established in practice as a barrister in the Republic of Ireland, to provide in the course of any proceedings any service which could not properly be provided by an advocate or barrister;

(b) if he is instructed with and acts in conjunction with an advocate or barrister in any proceedings, to provide in the course of those proceedings, or of any related proceedings, any service which an advocate or barrister could not properly provide;

(c) if he is instructed with and acts in conjunction with a solicitor in any proceedings, to provide in the course of those proceedings, or of any related proceedings, any service which a solicitor could not properly provide.

7.

A European lawyer in salaried employment who is instructed with and acts in conjunction with an advocate or barrister in any proceedings may provide a service on behalf of his employer in those proceedings only in so far as an advocate or barrister in such employment could properly do so.

Drawing of documents, etc not related to legal proceedings

8.

No enactment or rule of law or practice shall prevent a European lawyer from drawing or preparing for remuneration –

(i) in England, Wales or Northern Ireland, an instrument relating to personal estate, or

(ii) in Scotland, a writ relating to moveable property,

by reason only that he is not an advocate, barrister or solicitor.

9.

(i) creating or transferring an interest in land; or

(ii) for obtaining title to administer the estate of a deceased person.

Legal aid

10.

Services may be provided by a European lawyer by way of legal advice and assistance or legal aid under the enactments specified in Part 1 of the Schedule; and references to counsel and solicitors in those and any other enactments relating to legal advice and assistance or legal aid shall be construed accordingly.

11.

In providing any services, a European lawyer shall use the professional title and description applicable to him in his country of origin, expressed in the language or one of the languages of that country, together with the name of the professional organisation by which he is authorised to practise or the court of law before which he is entitled to practise in that country.

Power to require a European lawyer to verify his status

12.

A competent authority may at any time request a person seeking to provide any services to verify his status as a European lawyer.

13.

Where a request has been made under article 12, the person to whom it is made shall not, except to the extent (if any) allowed by the competent authority making the request, be entitled to provide services in the United Kingdom until he has verified his status as a European lawyer to the satisfaction of that authority.

14.

For the purposes of articles 12 and 13, a competent authority is –

(a) where the services which the person concerned seeks to provide are reserved to advocates or barristers, or in any case where the person concerned claims to be a barrister established in practice in the Republic of Ireland, the Senate of the Inns of Court and the Bar, the Faculty of Advocates, or the Benchers of the Inn of Court of Northern Ireland, according to the part of the United Kingdom concerned; or

(b) where sub-paragraph (a) does not apply, the Law Society, the Law Society of Scotland, or the Incorporated Law Society of Northern Ireland, according to the part of the United Kingdom concerned; or

(c) in any case, any court, tribunal or public authority before which the person concerned seeks to provide services.

Professional misconduct

15.

(1) A complaint may be made to a disciplinary authority that[a European lawyer providing any services has failed to observe a condition or rule of professional conduct referred to in article 4 of the Directive and applicable to him.

(2) Where a complaint is made under paragraph (1), the disciplinary authority concerned shall consider and adjudicate upon it in accordance with the same procedure, and subject to the same rights of appeal, as apply in relation to an advocate, barrister or solicitor (as the case may be) over whom that authority has jurisdiction.

(3) For the purposes of this article and article 16, a disciplinary authority is –

(a) where the services in question are reserved to advocates or barristers, or in any case where the person whose conduct is in question is established in practice as a barrister in the Republic of Ireland, an authority having disciplinary jurisdiction over advocates or barristers (as the case may be) in the part of the United Kingdom concerned;

(b) where sub-paragraph (a) does not apply, an authority having disciplinary jurisdiction over solicitors in the part of the United Kingdom concerned.

16.

(1) Where a disciplinary authority finds that a European lawyer against whom a complaint has been made under article 15(1) has committed a breach of a condition or a rule of professional conduct mentioned in that article, that authority –

(a) shall report that finding to the European lawyer's own professional authority; and

(b) may, if it thinks fit, direct him not to provide services in the United Kingdom, except to such extent and under such conditions (if any) as the disciplinary authority may specify in the direction.

(c) A disciplinary authority may at any time, if it thinks fit, vary, cancel or suspend the operation of a direction given by it under paragraph (1)(b).

17.

A European lawyer in respect of whom a direction is made under article 16(1)(b) shall not be entitled to provide services in the United Kingdom except as allowed by the direction.

Modification of enactments

18.

(1) Without prejudice to the generality of articles 5 and 8, the enactments specified in Part 2 of the Schedule (being enactments which reserve the provision of certain services to advocates, barristers, solicitors and other qualified persons) shall be construed subject to those articles.

(2) Notwithstanding anything in the Solicitors (Scotland) Act 1980, the Solicitors Act 1974 or the Solicitors (Northern Ireland) Order 1976, references to unqualified persons, however expressed, in the enactments specified in Part 3 of the Schedule (being enactments relating to unqualified persons acting as solicitors) shall not include a European lawyer providing services within the meaning of this Order.

(3) Nothing in section 33 of the Solicitors (Scotland) Act 1980 shall prevent a European lawyer from recovering any remuneration or expenses to which that section applies by reason only that he is not qualified as a solicitor.

SCHEDULE

Article 10

Part 1

Legal Aid and Advice Act (Northern Ireland) 1965 (c. 8).

Legal Aid (Scotland) Act 1986 (c 47).

Legal Advice and Assistance Act 1972 (c. 50).

Access to Justice (Northern Ireland) Order 2003.

Access to Justice Act 1999 (c 22).

Financial Services and Markets Act 2000 (c 8).

Part 2

Solicitors (Scotland) Act 1980 (c 46), section 32.

Magistrates' Courts (Northern Ireland) Order 1981, article 164(1).

County Courts (Northern Ireland) Order 1980, article 50.

Solicitors Act 1974 (c. 47), sections 20, 22 and 23.

Solicitors (Northern Ireland) Order 1976 (SI No. 582 (NI 12)), articles 19, 23.

Part 3

Solicitors (Scotland) Act 1980 (c 46), section 26.

Solicitors Act 1974 (c. 47), section 25(1).

Solicitors (Northern Ireland) Order 1976 (SI No. 582 (NI 12)), articles 25(1), 27.

PART 8 - ALTERNATIVE PROCEDURE FOR CLAIMS

Contents of this Part

Types of claim in which Part 8 procedure may be followed

8.1

(1) The Part 8 procedure is the procedure set out in this Part.

(2) A claimant may use the Part 8 procedure where –

(a) he seeks the court’s decision on a question which is unlikely to involve a substantial dispute of fact; or

(b) paragraph (6) applies.

(3) The court may at any stage order the claim to continue as if the claimant had not used the Part 8 procedure and, if it does so, the court may give any directions it considers appropriate.

(4) Paragraph (2) does not apply if a practice direction provides that the Part 8 procedure may not be used in relation to the type of claim in question.

(5) Where the claimant uses the Part 8 procedure he may not obtain default judgment under Part 12.

(6) A rule or practice direction may, in relation to a specified type of proceedings –

(a) require or permit the use of the Part 8 procedure; and

(b) disapply or modify any of the rules set out in this Part as they apply to those proceedings.

(Rule 8.9 provides for other modifications to the general rules where the Part 8 procedure is being used)

(Part 78 provides procedures for European orders for payment and for the European small claims procedure. It also provides procedures for applications for mediation settlement enforcement orders in relation to certain cross-border disputes.)

Contents of the claim form

8.2  Where the claimant uses the Part 8 procedure the claim form must state –

(a) that this Part applies;

(b)

(i) the question which the claimant wants the court to decide; or

(ii) the remedy which the claimant is seeking and the legal basis for the claim to that remedy;

(c) if the claim is being made under an enactment, what that enactment is;

(d) if the claimant is claiming in a representative capacity, what that capacity is; and

(e) if the defendant is sued in a representative capacity, what that capacity is.

(Part 22 provides for the claim form to be verified by a statement of truth)

(Rule 7.5 provides for service of the claim form)

Issue of claim form without naming defendants

8.2A

(1) A practice direction may set out circumstances in which a claim form may be issued under this Part without naming a defendant.

(2) The practice direction may set out those cases in which an application for permission must be made by application notice before the claim form is issued.

(3) The application notice for permission –

(a) need not be served on any other person; and

(b) must be accompanied by a copy of the claim form that the applicant proposes to issue.

(4) Where the court gives permission it will give directions about the future management of the claim.

Acknowledgment of service

8.3

(1) The defendant must –

(a) file an acknowledgment of service in the relevant practice form not more than 14 days after service of the claim form; and

(b) serve the acknowledgment of service on the claimant and any other party.

(2) The acknowledgment of service must state –

(a) whether the defendant contests the claim; and

(b) if the defendant seeks a different remedy from that set out in the claim form, what that remedy is.

(3) The following rules of Part 10 (acknowledgment of service) apply –

(a) rule 10.3(2) (exceptions to the period for filing an acknowledgment of service); and

(b) rule 10.5 (contents of acknowledgment of service).

(4) Omitted

Consequence of not filing an acknowledgment of service

8.4

(1) This rule applies where –

(a) the defendant has failed to file an acknowledgment of service; and

(b) the time period for doing so has expired.

(2) The defendant may attend the hearing of the claim but may not take part in the hearing unless the court gives permission.

Filing and serving written evidence

8.5

(1) The claimant must file any written evidence on which he intends to rely when he files his claim form.

(2) The claimant’s evidence must be served on the defendant with the claim form.

(3) A defendant who wishes to rely on written evidence must file it when he files his acknowledgment of service.

(4) If he does so, he must also, at the same time, serve a copy of his evidence on the other parties.

(5) The claimant may, within 14 days of service of the defendant’s evidence on him, file further written evidence in reply.

(6) If he does so, he must also, within the same time limit, serve a copy of his evidence on the other parties.

(7) The claimant may rely on the matters set out in his claim form as evidence under this rule if the claim form is verified by a statement of truth.

Evidence – general

8.6

(1) No written evidence may be relied on at the hearing of the claim unless –

(a) it has been served in accordance with rule 8.5; or

(b) the court gives permission.

(2) The court may require or permit a party to give oral evidence at the hearing.

(3) The court may give directions requiring the attendance for cross-examination(GL)of a witness who has given written evidence.

(Rule 32.1 contains a general power for the court to control evidence)

Part 20 claims

8.7  Where the Part 8 procedure is used, Part 20 (counterclaims and other additional claims) applies except that a party may not make a Part 20 claim (as defined by rule 20.2) without the court’s permission.

Procedure where defendant objects to use of the Part 8 procedure

8.8

(1) Where the defendant contends that the Part 8 procedure should not be used because –

(a) there is a substantial dispute of fact; and

(b) the use of the Part 8 procedure is not required or permitted by a rule or practice direction,

he must state his reasons when he files his acknowledgment of service.

(Rule 8.5 requires a defendant who wishes to rely on written evidence to file it when he files his acknowledgment of service)

(2) When the court receives the acknowledgment of service and any written evidence it will give directions as to the future management of the case.

(Rule 8.1(3) allows the court to make an order that the claim continue as if the claimant had not used the Part 8 procedure)

Modifications to the general rules

8.9  Where the Part 8 procedure is followed –

(a) provision is made in this Part for the matters which must be stated in the claim form and the defendant is not required to file a defence and therefore –

(i) Part 16 (statements of case) does not apply;

(ii) Part 15 (defence and reply) does not apply;

(iii) any time limit in these Rules which prevents the parties from taking a step before a defence is filed does not apply;

(iv) the requirement under rule 7.8 to serve on the defendant a form for defending the claim does not apply;

(b) the claimant may not obtain judgment by request on an admission and therefore –

(i) rules 14.4 to 14.7 do not apply; and

(ii) the requirement under rule 7.8 to serve on the defendant a form for admitting the claim does not apply; and

(c) the claim shall be treated as allocated to the multi-track and therefore Part 26 does not apply.

PRACTICE DIRECTION 19B – GROUP LITIGATION

This practice direction supplements Section III of Part 19

Contents of this Practice Direction

Introduction

1  This practice direction deals with group litigation where the multiple parties are claimants. Section III of Part 19 (group litigation orders) also applies where the multiple parties are defendants. The court will give such directions in such a case as are appropriate.

Preliminary steps

2.1  Before applying for a Group Litigation Order (‘GLO’) the solicitor acting for the proposed applicant should consult the Law Society’s Multi Party Action Information Service in order to obtain information about other cases giving rise to the proposed GLO issues.

2.2  It will often be convenient for the claimants’ solicitors to form a Solicitors’ Group and to choose one of their number to take the lead in applying for the GLO and in litigating the GLO issues. The lead solicitor’s role and relationship with the other members of the Solicitors’ Group should be carefully defined in writing and will be subject to any directions given by the court under CPR 19.13(c).

2.3  In considering whether to apply for a GLO, the applicant should consider whether any other order would be more appropriate. In particular he should consider whether, in the circumstances of the case, it would be more appropriate for –

(1) the claims to be consolidated; or

(2) the rules in Section II of Part 19 (representative parties) to be used.

Application for a GLO

3.1  An application for a GLO must be made in accordance with CPR Part 23, may be made at any time before or after any relevant claims have been issued and may be made either by a claimant or by a defendant.

3.2  The following information should be included in the application notice or in written evidence filed in support of the application:

(1) a summary of the nature of the litigation;

(2) the number and nature of claims already issued;

(3) the number of parties likely to be involved;

(4) the common issues of fact or law (the ‘GLO issues’) that are likely to arise in the litigation; and

(5) whether there are any matters that distinguish smaller groups of claims within the wider group.

3.3  A GLO may not be made –

(1) in the Queen’s Bench Division, without the consent of the President of the Queen’s Bench Division,

(2) in the Chancery Division, without the consent of the Chancellor of the High Court, or

(3) in a county court, without the consent of the Head of Civil Justice.

3.4  The court to which the application for a GLO is made will, if minded to make the GLO, send to the President of the Queen’s Bench Division, the Chancellor of the High Court, or the Head of Civil Justice, as appropriate –

(1) a copy of the application notice,

(2) a copy of any relevant written evidence, and

(3) a written statement as to why a GLO is considered to be desirable.

These steps may be taken either before or after a hearing of the application.

High Court in London

3.5  The application for the GLO should be made to the Senior Master in the Queen’s Bench Division or the Chief Chancery Master in the Chancery Division. For claims that are proceeding or are likely to proceed in a specialist list, the application should be made to the senior judge of that list.

High Court outside London

3.6  Outside London, the application should be made to a Presiding Judge or a Chancery Supervising Judge of the Circuit in which the District Registry which has issued the application notice is situated.

County courts

3.7  The application should be made to the Designated Civil Judge for the area in which the county court which has issued the application notice is situated.

3.8  The applicant for a GLO should request the relevant court to refer the application notice to the judge by whom the application will be heard as soon as possible after the application notice has been issued. This is to enable the judge to consider whether to follow the practice set out in paragraph 3.4 above prior to the hearing of the application.

3.9  The directions under paragraphs 3.5, 3.6 and 3.7 above do not prevent the judges referred to from making arrangements for other judges to hear applications for GLOs when they themselves are unavailable.

GLO made by court of its own initiative

4  Subject to obtaining the appropriate consent referred to in paragraph 3.3 and the procedure set out in paragraph 3.4, the court may make a GLO of its own initiative.

(CPR 3.3 deals with the procedure that applies when a court proposes to make an order of its own initiative)

The GLO

5  CPR 19.11(2) and (3) set out rules relating to the contents of GLOs.

The Group Register

6.1  Once a GLO has been made a Group Register will be established on which will be entered such details as the court may direct of the cases which are to be subject to the GLO.

6.1A  A claim must be issued before it can be entered on a Group Register.

6.2  An application for details of a case to be entered on a Group Register may be made by any party to the case.

6.3  An order for details of the case to be entered on the Group Register will not be made unless the case gives rise to at least one of the GLO issues.

(CPR 19.10 defines GLO issues)

6.4  The court, if it is not satisfied that a case can be conveniently case managed with the other cases on the Group Register, or if it is satisfied that the entry of the case on the Group Register would adversely affect the case management of the other cases, may refuse to allow details of the case to be entered on the Group Register, or order their removal from the Register if already entered, although the case gives rise to one or more of the Group issues.

6.5  The Group Register will normally be maintained by and kept at the court but the court may direct this to be done by the solicitor for one of the parties to a case entered on the Register.

6.6

(1) Rules 5.4 (Register of Claims), 5.4B (Supply of documents from court records – a party) and 5.4C (supply of documents from court records – a non-party) apply where the register is maintained by the court. A party to a claim on the group register may request documents relating to any other claim on the group register in accordance with rule 5.4 as if he were a party to those proceedings.

(2) Where the register is maintained by a solicitor, any person may inspect the Group Register during normal business hours and upon giving reasonable notice to the solicitor; the solicitor may charge a fee not exceeding the fee prescribed for a search at the court office.

6.7  In this paragraph, ‘the court’ means the management court specified in the GLO.

Allocation to track

7  Once a GLO has been made and unless the management court directs otherwise:

(1) every claim in a case entered on the Group Register will be automatically allocated, or re-allocated (as the case may be), to the multi-track;

(2) any case management directions that have already been given in any such case otherwise than by the management court will be set aside; and

(3) any hearing date already fixed otherwise than for the purposes of the group litigation will be vacated.

Managing judge

8  A judge (‘the managing judge’) will be appointed for the purpose of the GLO as soon as possible. He will assume overall responsibility fo the management of the claims and will generally hear the GLO issues. A Master or a District Judge may be appointed to deal with procedural matters, which he will do in accordance with any directions given by the managing judge. A costs judge may be appointed and may be invited to attend case management hearings.

Claims to be started in management court

9.1  The management court may order that as from a specified date all claims that raise one or more of the GLO issues shall be started in the management court.

9.2  Failure to comply with an order made under paragraph 9.1 will not invalidate the commencement of the claim but the claim should be transferred to the management court and details entered on the Group Register as soon as possible. Any party to the claim may apply to the management court for an order under CPR 19.14 removing the case from the Register or, as the case may be, for an order that details of the case be not entered on the Register.

Transfer

10  Where the management court is a county court and a claim raising one or more of the GLO issues is proceeding in the High Court, an order transferring the case to the management court and directing the details of the case to be entered on the Group Register can only be made in the High Court.

Publicising the GLO

11  After a GLO has been made, a copy of the GLO should be supplied –

(1) to the Law Society, 113 Chancery Lane, London WC2A 1PL; and

(2) to the Senior Master, Queen’s Bench Division, Royal Courts of Justice, Strand, London WC2A 2LL.

Case management

12.1  The management court may give case management directions at the time the GLO is made or subsequently. Directions given at a case management hearing will generally be binding on all claims that are subsequently entered on the Group Register (see CPR 19.12(1)).

12.2  Any application to vary the terms of the GLO must be made to the management court.

12.3  The management court may direct that one or more of the claims are to proceed as test claims.

12.4  The management court may give directions about how the costs of resolving common issues or the costs of claims proceeding as test claims are to be borne or shared as between the claimants on the Group Register.

Cut-off dates

13  The management court may specify a date after which no claim may be added to the Group Register unless the court gives permission. An early cut-off date may be appropriate in the case of ‘instant disasters’ (such as transport accidents). In the case of consumer claims, and particularly pharmaceutical claims, it may be necessary to delay the ordering of a cut-off date.

Statements of case

14.1  The management court may direct that the GLO claimants serve ‘Group Particulars of Claim’ which set out the various claims of all the claimants on the Group Register at the time the particulars are filed. Such particulars of claim will usually contain –

(1) general allegations relating to all claims; and

(2) a schedule containing entries relating to each individual claim specifying which of the general allegations are relied on and any specific facts relevant to the claimant.

14.2  The directions given under paragraph 14.1 should include directions as to whether the Group Particulars should be verified by a statement or statements of truth and, if so, by whom.

14.3  The specific facts relating to each claimant on the Group Register may be obtained by the use of a questionnaire. Where this is proposed, the management court should be asked to approve the questionnaire. The management court may direct that the questionnaires completed by individual claimants take the place of the schedule referred to in paragraph 14.1(2).

14.4  The management court may also give directions about the form that particulars of claim relating to claims which are to be entered on the Group Register should take.

The trial

15.1  The management court may give directions –

(1) for the trial of common issues; and

(2) for the trial of individual issues.

15.2  Common issues and test claims will normally be tried at the management court. Individual issues may be directed to be tried at other courts whose locality is convenient for the parties.

Costs

16.1  CPR 46 contains rules about costs where a GLO has been made.

16.2  Where the court has made an order about costs in relation to any application or hearing which involved both –

(1) one or more of the GLO issues; and

(2) an issue or issues relevant only to individual claims;

and the court has not directed the proportion of the costs that is to relate to common costs and the proportion that is to relate to individual costs in accordance with rule 46.6(5), the costs judge will make a decision as to the relevant proportions at or before the commencement of the detailed assessment of costs.

PRACTICE DIRECTION 26 – CASE MANAGEMENT – PRELIMINARY STAGE: ALLOCATION AND RE-ALLOCATION

This Practice Direction supplements CPR Part 26

Contents of this Practice Direction

Reminders of important rule provisions other than parts 26–29

Attention is drawn in particular to the following provisions of the Civil Procedure Rules:

Part 1

The Overriding Objective (defined in Rule 1.1).

The duty of the court to further that objective by actively managing cases (set out in Rule 1.4).

The requirement that the parties help the court to further that objective (set out in Rule 1.3).

Section I of Part 3

The court’s case management powers (which may be exercised on application or on its own initiative) and the sanctions which it may impose.

Part 24

The court’s power to grant summary judgment.

Parts 32–35

Evidence, especially the court’s power to control evidence.

Attention is also drawn to the practice directions which supplement those Parts and Parts27-29, and to those which relate to the various specialist jurisdictions.

The directions questionnaire

Form

2.1

(1) The notice of proposed allocation referred to in rule 26.3(1) will be –

in the small claims track, in form N149A (SCT);

in the fast track, in form N149B (FT); and

in the multi-track, in form N149C (MT),

and the directions questionnaire referred to in Part 26 will be in Forms N180 and N181.

(2) Attention is drawn to Part 3 of the Civil Procedure Rules which requires costs budgets in all multi-track cases.

Provision of extra information

2.2

(1) If a party wishes to give the court further information which is believed to be relevant to allocation or case management it shall be given when the party files the directions questionnaire and copied to all other parties.

(2) The general rule is that the court will not take such information into account unless the document containing it either:

(a) confirms that all parties have agreed that the information is correct and that it should be put before the court, or

(b) confirms that the party who has sent the document to the court has delivered a copy to all the other parties.

(3) The following are examples of information which will be likely to help the court:

(a) a party’s intention to apply for summary judgment or some other order that may dispose of the case or reduce the amount in dispute or the number of issues remaining to be decided,

(b) a party’s intention to issue a Part 20 claim or to add another party,

(c) the steps the parties have taken in the preparation of evidence (in particular expert evidence), the steps they intend to take and whether those steps are to be taken in co-operation with any other party,

(d) the directions the party believes will be appropriate to be given for the management of the case,

(e) about any particular facts that may affect the timetable the court will set,

(f) any facts which may make it desirable for the court to fix an allocation hearing or a hearing at which case management directions will be given.

Consultation

2.3

(1) The parties parties must consult one another and co-operate in completing the directions questionnaires and giving other information to the court.

(2) They parties must try to agree the case management directions which they will invite the court to make. Further details appear in the practice directions which supplement Parts 28 and 29.

(Specimen directions for a case which is allocated to the multi-track are available on the Justice website at: www.justice.gov.uk/courts/procedure-rules/civil)

(3) The process of consultation must not delay the filing of the the directions questionnaire or, where required, the proposed directions (whether or not agreed).

Hearings before allocation

2.4  Where a court hearing takes place (for example on an application for an interim injunction or for summary judgment under Part 24) before the claim is allocated to a track, the court may at that hearing:

(1) dispense with the need for the parties to file directions questionnaires, treat the hearing as an allocation hearing, make an order for allocation and give directions for case management, or

(2) fix a date for directions questionnaires to be filed and give other directions.

Consequences of failure to file a directions questionnaire

2.5

(1) Parties must comply with the notice served under rule 26.3(1) by the date specified in it. Rules 26.3(7A), which concerns designated money claims, and 26.3(8), which concerns claims other than designated money claims, apply where a party is in default.

(2) A party's statement of case may be struck out under rule 26.3(7A)(b).

(3) Under rule 26.3(8) the court may give directions of its own initiative or list the case for a case management conference. Alternatively, if it appears appropriate to do so, the claim may be struck out or, where a defendant is in default, judgment may be entered against that defendant.

(4) Rule 26.3(10) provides for a costs sanction if an order is made under either rules 26.3(7A)(b) or 26.3(8).

Stay to allow for settlement of the case

Procedure for the parties to apply to extend the stay

3.1

(1)

(a) The court will generally accept a letter from any party or from the solicitor for any party as an application to extend the stay under rule 26.4.

(b) The letter should –

(i) confirm that the application is made with the agreement of all parties, and

(ii) explain the steps being taken and identify any mediator or expert assisting with the process.

(2)

(a) An order extending the stay must be made by a judge.

(b) The extension will generally be for no more than 4 weeks unless clear reasons are given to justify a longer time.

(3) More than one extension of the stay may be granted.

Position at the end of the stay if no settlement is reached

3.2

(1) At the end of the stay the file will be referred to a judge for his directions.

(2) He will consider whether to allocate the claim to a track and what other directions to give, or may require any party to give further information or fix an allocation hearing.

3.3 Any party may apply for a stay to be lifted.

Position where settlement is reached during a stay

3.4

Where the whole of the proceedings are settled during a stay, the taking of any of the following steps will be treated as an application for the stay to be lifted:

(1) an application for a consent order (in any form) to give effect to the settlement,

(2) an application for the approval of a settlement where a party is a person under a disability,

(3) giving notice of acceptance of money paid into court in satisfaction of the claim or applying for money in court to be paid out.

Allocation, re-allocation and case management

The court’s general approach

4.1  The Civil Procedure Rules lay down the overriding objective, the powers and duties of the court and the factors to which it must have regard in exercising them. The court will expect to exercise its powers as far as possible in co-operation with the parties and their legal representatives so as to deal with the case justly in accordance with that objective.

Allocation to track

4.2

(1) In most cases the court will expect to have enough information from the statements of case and directions questionnaires to be able to allocate the claim to a track and to give case management directions.

(2) If the court does not have enough information to allocate the claim it will generally make an order under rule 26.5(3) requiring one or more parties to provide further information within 14 days.

(3) Where there has been no allocation hearing the notice of allocation will be in Forms N154 (fast track), N155 (multi-track) or N157–160 (small claims).

(4)

(a) The general rule is that the court will give brief reasons for its allocation decision, and these will be set out in the notice of allocation.

(b) The general rule does not apply where all the directions questionnaires which have been filed have expressed the wish for the claim to be allocated to the track to which the court has allocated it.

(5) Paragraph 6 of this practice direction deals with allocation hearings and Paragraph 7 deals with allocation principles.

(6) Paragraph 11 of this practice direction deals with re-allocation.

4.3  The practice directions supplementing Parts 27, 28 and 29 contain further information about the giving of case management directions at the allocation stage.

Summary judgment or other early termination

5.1  Part of the court’s duty of active case management is the summary disposal of issues which do not need full investigation and trial (rule 1.4(2)(c)),

5.2  The court’s powers to make orders to dispose of issues in that way include:

(a) under rule 3.4, striking out a statement of case, or part of a statement of case, and

(b) under Part 24, giving summary judgment where a claimant or a defendant has no reasonable prospect of success.

The court may use these powers on an application or on its own initiative. Practice Direction 24 contains further information.

5.3

(1) A party intending to make such an application should do so before or when filing his directions questionnaire.

(2) Where a party makes an application for such an order before a claim has been allocated to a track the court will not normally allocate the claim before the hearing of the application.

(3) Where a party files an directions questionnaire stating that he intends to make such an application but has not done so, the judge will usually direct that an allocation hearing is listed.

(4) The application may be heard at that allocation hearing if the application notice has been issued and served in sufficient time.

5.4

(1) This paragraph applies where the court proposes to make such an order of its own initiative.

(2) The court will not allocate the claim to a track but instead it will either:

(a) fix a hearing, giving the parties at least 14 days' notice of the date of the hearing and of the issues which it is proposed that the court will decide, or

(b) make an order directing a party to take the steps described in the order within a stated time and specifying the consequence of not taking those steps.

5.5  Where the court decides at the hearing of an application or a hearing fixed under paragraph 5.4(2)(a) that the claim (or part of the claim) is to continue it may:

(1) treat that hearing as an allocation hearing, allocate the claim and give case management directions, or

(2) give other directions.

Allocation hearings

General principle

6.1  The court will only hold an allocation hearing on its own initiative if it considers that it is necessary to do so.

Procedure

6.2  Where the court orders an allocation hearing to take place:

(1) it will give the parties at least 7 days' notice of the hearing in Form N153, and

(2) Form N153 will give a brief explanation of the decision to order the hearing.

Power to treat another hearing as an allocation hearing

6.3  Where the court may treat another hearing as an allocation hearing it does not need to give notice to any party that it proposes to do so.

6.4  The notice of allocation after an allocation hearing will be in Forms N154, N155 or N157.

Representation

6.5  A legal representative who attends an allocation hearing should, if possible, be the person responsible for the case and must in any event be familiar with the case, be able to provide the court with the information it is likely to need to take its decisions about allocation and case management, and have sufficient authority to deal with any issues that are likely to arise.

Sanctions

6.6

(1) This paragraph sets out the sanctions that the court will usually impose for default in connection with the allocation procedure, but the court may make a different order.

(2)

(a) Where a directions hearing takes place because a party has failed to file a directions questionnaire or to provide further information which the court has ordered, the court will usually order that party to pay on the indemnity basis the costs of any other party who has attended the hearing, summarily assess the amount of those costs, and order them to be paid forthwith or within a stated period.

(b) The court may order that if the party does not pay those costs within the time stated his statement of case will be struck out.

(3) Where a party whose default has led to a fixing of an allocation hearing is still in default and does not attend the hearing the court will usually make an order specifying the steps he is required to take and providing that unless he takes them within a stated time his statement of case will be struck out.

Allocation principles

Rules 26.6, 26.7 and 26.8

7.1

(1) Rule 26.6 sets out the scope of each track,

(2) Rule 26.7 states the general rule for allocation, and

(3) Rule 26.8 sets out the matters relevant to allocation to a track.

Objective of this paragraph

7.2  The object of this paragraph is to explain what will be the court’s general approach to some of the matters set out in rule 26.8.

‘the financial value of the claim’

7.3

(1) Rule 26.8(2) provides that it is for the court to assess the financial value of a claim.

(2) Where the court believes that the amount the claimant is seeking exceeds what he may reasonably be expected to recover it may make an order under rule 26.5(3) directing the claimant to justify the amount.

‘any amount not in dispute’

7.4  In deciding, for the purposes of rule 26.8(2), whether an amount is in dispute the court will apply the following general principles:

(1) Any amount for which the defendant does not admit liability is in dispute,

(2) Any sum in respect of an item forming part of the claim for which judgment has been entered (for example a summary judgment) is not in dispute,

(3) Any specific sum claimed as a distinct item and which the defendant admits he is liable to pay is not in dispute,

(4) Any sum offered by the defendant which has been accepted by the claimant in satisfaction of any item which forms a distinct part of the claim is not in dispute.

It follows from these provisions that if, in relation to a claim the value of which is above the small claims track limit of £10,000, the defendant makes, before allocation, an admission that reduces the amount in dispute to a figure below £10,000 (see CPR Part 14), the normal track for the claim will be the small claims track. As to recovery of pre-allocation costs, the claimant can, before allocation, apply for judgment with costs on the amount of the claim that has been admitted (see CPR rule 14.3 but see also paragraph 7.1(3) of Practice Direction 46 under which the court has a discretion to allow pre-allocation costs)..

‘the views expressed by the parties’

7.5  The court will treat these views as an important factor, but the allocation decision is one for the court, to be taken in the light of all the circumstances, and the court will not be bound by any agreement or common view of the parties.

‘the circumstances of the parties’

7.6  See paragraph 8.

‘the value of any counterclaim or other Part 20 claim’

7.7  Where the case involves more than one money claim (for example where there is a Part 20 claim or there is more than one claimant each making separate claims) the court will not generally aggregate the claims. Instead it will generally regard the largest of them as determining the financial value of the claims.

The small claims track – allocation and case management

Allocation

8.1

(1)

(a) The small claims track is intended to provide a proportionate procedure by which most straightforward claims with a financial value of not more than £10,000 can be decided, without the need for substantial pre-hearing preparation and the formalities of a traditional trial, and without incurring large legal costs. (Rule 26.6 provides for a lower financial value in certain types of case.)

(b) The procedure laid down in Part 27 for the preparation of the case and the conduct of the hearing are designed to make it possible for a litigant to conduct his own case without legal representation if he wishes.

(c) Cases generally suitable for the small claims track will include consumer disputes, accident claims, disputes about the ownership of goods and most disputes between a landlord and tenant other than opposed claims under Part 56, disputed claims for possession under Part 55 and demotion claims whether in the alternative to possession claims or under Part 65.

(d) A case involving a disputed allegation of dishonesty will not usually be suitable for the small claims track.

(2) The court may allocate to the small claims track a claim, the value of which is above the limits mentioned in rule 26.6(2). The court will not normally allow more than one day for the hearing of such a claim.

Case management

8.2

(1) Directions for case management of claims allocated to the small claims track will generally be given by the court on allocation.

(2) Rule 27.4 contains further provisions about directions and Practice Direction 27 sets out the standard directions which the court will usually give.

The fast track

Allocation

9.1

(1) Where the court is to decide whether to allocate to the fast track or the multi-track a claim for which the normal track is the fast track, it will allocate the claim to the fast track unless it believes that it cannot be dealt with justly on that track.

(2) The court will, in particular, take into account the limits likely to be placed on disclosure, the extent to which expert evidence may be necessary and whether the trial is likely to last more than a day.

(3)

(a) When it is considering the likely length of the trial the court will regard a day as being a period of 5 hours, and will consider whether that is likely to be sufficient time for the case to be heard.

(b) The court will also take into account the case management directions (including the fixing of a trial timetable) that are likely to be given and the court’s powers to control evidence and to limit cross-examination.

(c) The possibility that a trial might last longer than one day is not necessarily a conclusive reason for the court to allocate or to re-allocate a claim to the multi-track.

(d) A claim may be allocated to the fast track or ordered to remain on that track although there is to be a split trial.

(e) Where the case involves a counterclaim or other Part 20 claim that will be tried with the claim and as a result the trial will last more than a day, the court may not allocate it to the fast track.

Case management

9.2

(1) Directions for the case management of claims which have been allocated to the fast track will be given at the allocation stage or at the listing stage (in either case with or without a hearing) or at both, and if necessary at other times. The trial judge may, at or before the trial, give directions for its conduct.

(2) Practice Direction 28 contains further provisions and contains standard directions which the court may give.

The multi-track

10.1  Paragraph 10.2 does not apply–

(1) a claim for possession of land in the county court or a demotion claim whether in the alternative to a possession claim or under Part 65;

(2) any claim which is being dealt with at the Royal Courts of Justice.

Venue for allocation and case management

10.2

(1) The case management of a claim which is allocated to the multi-track will normally be dealt with at a Civil Trial Centre.

(2) In the case of a claim to which any of Parts 49 or 58–62 apply, case management must be dealt with at a Civil Trial Centre. Sub-paragraphs (4) to (10) do not apply to such a claim. The claim will be allocated to the multi-track irrespective of its value, and must be transferred to a Civil Trial Centre for allocation and case management if not already there.

(3) Where a claim is issued in or automatically transferred to a Civil Trial Centre it will be allocated and managed at that court.

(4) The following sub-paragraphs apply to a claim which is issued in or automatically transferred to a court which is not a Civil Trial Centre. Such a court is referred to as a ‘feeder court’.

(5) Where a judge sitting at a feeder court decides, on the basis of the directions questionnaires and any other documents filed by the parties, that the claim should be dealt with on the multi-track he will normally make an order:

(a) allocating the claim to that track,

(b) giving case management directions, and

(c) transferring the claim to a Civil Trial Centre.

(6) If he decides that an allocation hearing or some pre-allocation hearing is to take place (for example to strike out a statement of case under Part 3 of the Rules) that hearing will take place at the feeder court.

(7) If, before allocation, a hearing takes place at a feeder court and in exercising his powers under paragraph 2.4(1) above the judge allocates the claim to the multi-track, he will also normally make an order transferring the claim to a Civil Trial Centre.

(8) A judge sitting at a feeder court may, rather than making an allocation order himself, transfer the claim to a Civil Trial Centre for the decision about allocation to be taken there.

(9) When, following an order for transfer, the file is received at the Civil Trial Centre, a judge sitting at that Centre will consider it and give any further directions that appear necessary or desirable.

(10) Where there is reason to believe that more than one case management conference may be needed and the parties or their legal advisers are located inconveniently far from the Civil Trial Centre, a judge sitting at a feeder court may, with the agreement of the Designated Civil Judge and notwithstanding the allocation of the case to the multi-track, decide that in the particular circumstances of the case it should not be transferred to a Civil Trial Centre, but should be case managed for the time being at the feeder court.

(11) A Designated Civil Judge may at any time make an order transferring a claim from a feeder court to a Civil Trial Centre and he may do so irrespective of the track, if any, to which it has been allocated. He may also permit a feeder court to keep for trial a claim or (subject to review from time to time) a category of claims. Any such permisson should take into account the ability of the feeder court in relation to the Civil Trial Centre to provide suitable and effective trial within an appropriate trial period.

(12) No order will be made by a feeder court fixing a date for a hearing at a Civil Trial Centre unless that date has been given or confirmed by a judge or listing officer of that Centre.

Case management

10.3  Part 29 of the Rules and Practice Direction 29 set out the procedure to be adopted.

Re-allocation of claims and the variation of directions

11.1

(1) Where a party is dissatisfied with an order made allocating the claim to a track he may appeal or apply to the court to re-allocate the claim.

(2) He should appeal if the order was made at a hearing at which he was present or represented, or of which he was given due notice.

(3) In any other case he should apply to the court to re-allocate the claim.

11.2  Where there has been a change in the circumstances since an order was made allocating the claim to a track the court may re-allocate the claim. It may do so on application or on its own initiative.

The practice directions supplementing Parts 28 and 29 contain provisions about the variation of case management directions.

Determining the amount to be paid under a judgment or order

Scope

12.1

(1) In the following paragraphs –

(a) a ‘relevant order’ means a judgment or order of the court which requires the amount of money to be paid by one party to another to be decided by the court; and

(b) a ‘disposal hearing’ means a hearing in accordance with paragraph 12.4.

(2) A relevant order may have been obtained:

(a) by a judgment in default under Part 12;

(b) by a judgment on an admission under Part 14;

(c) on the striking out of a statement of case under Part 3;

(d) on a summary judgment application under Part 24;

(e) on the determination of a preliminary issue or on a trial as to liability; or

(f) at trial.

(3) A relevant order includes any order for the amount of a debt, damages or interest to be decided by the court (including an order for the taking of an account or the making of an inquiry as to any sum due, and any similar order), but does not include an order for the assessment of costs.

Directions

12.2

(1) When the court makes a relevant order it will give directions, which may include –

(a) listing the claim for a disposal hearing;

(b) allocating or re-allocating the claim (but see paragraph 12.3);

c) directing the parties to file directions questionnaires by a specified date; and

(d) staying the claim while the parties try to settle the case by alternative dispute resolution or other means.

(2) Directions may specify the level or type of judge before whom a hearing or a further hearing will take place and the nature and purpose of that hearing.

(3) Where the parties apply for a relevant order by consent, they should if possible file with their draft consent order agreed directions for the court's approval.

Allocation

12.3

(1) If, when the court makes a relevant order –

(a) the claim has not previously been allocated to a track; and

(b) the financial value of the claim (determined in accordance with Part 26) is such that the claim would, if defended be allocated to the small claims track,

the court will normally allocate it to that track.

(2) Where paragraph (1)(b) does not apply, the court will not normally allocate the claim to a track (other than the small claims track) unless –

(a) the amount payable appears to be genuinely disputed on substantial grounds; or

(b) the dispute is not suitable to be dealt with at a disposal hearing.

Disposal hearings

12.4

(1) A disposal hearing is a hearing –

(a) which will not normally last longer than 30 minutes, and

(b) at which the court will not normally hear oral evidence.

(2) At a disposal hearing the court may –

(a) decide the amount payable under or in consequence of the relevant order and give judgment for that amount; or

(b) give directions as to the future conduct of the proceedings.

(3) If the claim has been allocated to the small claims track, or the court decides at the disposal hearing to allocate it to that track, the court may treat the disposal hearing as a final hearing in accordance with Part 27.

(4) Rule 32.6 applies to evidence at a disposal hearing unless the court directs otherwise.

(5) Except where the claim has been allocated to the small claims track, the court will not exercise its power under sub-paragraph (2)(a) unless any written evidence on which the claimant relies has been served on the defendant at least 3 days before the disposal hearing.

Costs

12.5

(1) Attention is drawn to –

(a) Practice Directions 44 to 48 on costs and in particular to Subsections 8 and 9 of Practice Direction 44, which relate to the court's power to make a summary assessment of costs;

(b) rule 44.10(1) which provides that if an order makes no mention of costs, none are payable in respect of the proceedings to which it relates; and

(c) rule 27.14 (special rules about costs in cases allocated to the small claims track).

(2) Section VI of Part 45 (fast track trial costs) will not apply to a case dealt with at a disposal hearing whatever the financial value of the claim. So the costs of a disposal hearing will be in the discretion of the court.

Jurisdiction of Masters and district judges

12.6

Unless the court otherwise directs, a Master or a district judge may decide the amount payable under a relevant order irrespective of the financial value of the claim and of the track to which the claim may have been allocated.

PART 28 - THE FAST TRACK

Contents of this Part

Scope of this Part

28.1  This Part contains general provisions about management of cases allocated to the fast track and applies only to cases allocated to that track.

(Part 27 sets out the procedure for claims allocated to the small claims track)

(Part 29 sets out the procedure for claims allocated to the multi-track)

General provisions

28.2

(1) When it allocates a case to the fast track, the court will give directions for the management of the case and set a timetable for the steps to be taken between the giving of the directions and the trial.

(2) When it gives directions, the court will –

(a) fix the trial date; or

(b) fix a period, not exceeding 3 weeks, within which the trial is to take place.

(3) The trial date or trial period will be specified in the notice of allocation.

(4) The standard period between the giving of directions and the trial will be not more than 30 weeks.

(5) The court’s power to award trial costs is limited in accordance with Section
VI of Part 45.

Directions

28.3

(1) The matters to be dealt with by directions under rule 28.2(1) include –

(a) disclosure of documents;

(b) service of witness statements; and

(c) expert evidence.

(2) If the court decides not to direct standard disclosure, it may –

(a) direct that no disclosure take place; or

(b) specify the documents or the classes of documents which the parties must disclose.

(Rule 31.6 explains what is meant by standard disclosure)

(Rule 26.6(5) deals with limitations in relation to expert evidence and the likely length of trial in fast track cases)

Variation of case management timetable

28.4

(1) A party must apply to the court if he wishes to vary the date which the court has fixed for –

(a) the return of a pre-trial check list under rule 28.5;

(b) the trial; or

(c) the trial period.

(2) Any date set by the court or these Rules for doing any act may not be varied by the parties if the variation would make it necessary to vary any of the dates mentioned in paragraph (1).

(Rule 2.11 allows the parties to vary a date by written agreement except where the rules provide otherwise or the court orders otherwise)

Pre-trial check list (listing questionnaire)

28.5

(1) The court will send the parties a pre-trial check list (listing questionnaire) for completion and return by the date specified in the notice of allocation unless it considers that the claim can proceed to trial without the need for a pre-trial check list.

(2) The date specified for filing a pre-trial check list will not be more than 8 weeks before the trial date or the beginning of the trial period.

(3) If no party files the completed pre-trial checklist by the date specified, the court will order that unless a completed pre-trial checklist is filed within 7 days from service of that order, the claim, defence and any counterclaim will be struck out without further order of the court.

(4) If –

(a) a party files a completed pre-trial checklist but another party does not;

(b) a party has failed to give all the information requested by the pre-trial checklist; or

(c) the court considers that a hearing is necessary to enable it to decide what directions to give in order to complete preparation of the case for trial,

the court may give such directions as it thinks appropriate.

Fixing or confirming the trial date and giving directions

28.6

(1) As soon as practicable after the date specified for filing a completed pre-trial check list the court will –

(a) fix the date for the trial (or, if it has already done so, confirm that date);

(b) give any directions for the trial, including a trial timetable, which it considers appropriate; and

(c) specify any further steps that need to be taken before trial.

(2) The court will give the parties at least 3 weeks’ notice of the date of the trial unless, in exceptional circumstances, the court directs that shorter notice will be given.

Conduct of trial

28.7  Unless the trial judge otherwise directs, the trial will be conducted in accordance with any order previously made.

PRACTICE DIRECTION 29 – THE MULTI-TRACK

This Practice Direction supplements CPR Part 29

Contents of this Practice Direction

General

1.1  Attention is drawn in particular to the following Parts of the Civil Procedure Rules:

Part 1
The overriding objective

Section I of Part 3
The court’s case management powers

Part 26
Case management – preliminary stage

Part 31
Disclosure and inspection of documents

Part 32 to 34
Evidence

Part 35
Experts and assessors

and to the practice directions which relate to those Parts.

Case management in the Royal Courts of Justice

2.1  This part of the practice direction applies to claims begun by claim form issued in the Central Office or Chancery Chambers in the Royal Courts of Justice.

2.2  A claim with an estimated value of less than £50,000 will generally, unless:

(a) it is required by an enactment to be tried in the High Court,

(b) it falls within a specialist list, or

(c) it falls within one of the categories specified in 2.6 below or is otherwise within the criteria of article 7(5) of the High Court and County Courts Jurisdiction Order 1991,

be transferred to a county court.

2.3  Paragraph 2.2 is without prejudice to the power of the court in accordance with Part 30 to transfer to a county court a claim with an estimated value that exceeds £50,000.

2.4  The decision to transfer may be made at any stage in the proceedings but should, subject to paragraph 2.5, be made as soon as possible and in any event not later than the date for the filing of pre-trial check lists (listing questionnaires).

2.5  If an application is made under rule 3.4 (striking out) or under Part 24 (summary judgment) or under Part 25 (interim remedies), it will usually be convenient for the application to be dealt with before a decision to transfer is taken.

2.6  Each party should state in his directions questionnaire whether he considers the claim should be managed and tried at the Royal Courts of Justice and, if so, why. Claims suitable for trial in the Royal Courts of Justice include:

(1) professional negligence claims,

(2) Fatal Accident Act claims,

(3) fraud or undue influence claims,

(4) defamation claims,

(5) claims for malicious prosecution or false imprisonment,

(6) claims against the police,

(7) contentious probate claims.

Such claims may fall within the criteria of article 7(5) of the High Court and County Courts Jurisdiction Order 1991.

2.7  Attention is drawn to Practice Direction 30.

Case management – general provisions

3.1

(1) Case management of a claim which is proceeding at the Royal Courts of Justice will be undertaken there.

(2)

(a) Case management of any other claim which has been allocated to the multi-track will normally be undertaken at a Civil Trial Centre.

(b) Practice Direction 26 provides for what will happen in the case of a claim which is issued in or transferred to a court which is not a Civil Trial Centre.

3.2  The hallmarks of the multi-track are:

(1) the ability of the court to deal with cases of widely differing values and complexity, and

(2) the flexibility given to the court in the way it will manage a case in a way appropriate to its particular needs.

3.3

(1) On allocating a claim to the multi-track the court may give directions without a hearing, including fixing a trial date or a period in which the trial will take place,

(2) Alternatively, whether or not it fixes a trial date or period, it may either –

(a) give directions for certain steps to be taken and fix a date for a case management conference or a pre-trial review to take place after they have been taken, or

(b) fix a date for a case management conference.

(3) Attention is drawn to rule 29.2(2) which requires the court to fix a trial date or period as soon as practicable.

3.4  The court may give or vary directions at any hearing which may take place on the application of a party or of its own initiative.

3.5  When any hearing has been fixed it is the duty of the parties to consider what directions the court should be asked to give and to make any application that may be appropriate to be dealt with then.

3.6  The court will hold a hearing to give directions whenever it appears necessary or desirable to do so, and where this happens because of the default of a party or his legal representative it will usually impose a sanction.

3.7  When the court fixes a hearing to give directions it will give the parties at least 3 days’ notice of the hearing unless rule 29.7 applies (7 days' notice to be given in the case of a pre-trial review).

3.8  Where a party needs to apply for a direction of a kind not included in the case management timetable which has been set (for example to amend his statement of case or for further information to be given by another party) he must do so as soon as possible so as to minimise the need to change that timetable.

3.9  Courts will make arrangements to ensure that applications and other hearings are listed promptly to avoid delay in the conduct of cases.

3.10

(1) Case management will generally be dealt with by:

(a) a Master in cases proceeding in the Royal Courts of Justice,

(b) a district judge in cases proceeding in a District Registry of the High Court, and

(c) a district judge or a Circuit Judge in cases proceeding in a county court.

(2) A Master or a district judge may consult and seek the directions of a judge of a higher level about any aspect of case management.

(3) A member of the court staff who is dealing with the listing of a hearing may seek the directions of any judge about any aspect of that listing.

Case management – consideration of periodical payments

3A  Attention is drawn to Practice Direction 41B supplementing Part 41 and in particular to the direction that in a personal injury claim the court should consider and indicate to the parties as soon as practicable whether periodical payments or a lump sum is likely to be the more appropriate form for all or part of an award of damages for future pecuniary loss.

Directions on allocation

4.1  Attention is drawn to the court’s duties under Rule 29.2.

4.2  The court will seek to tailor its directions to the needs of the case and the steps which the parties have already taken to prepare the case of which it is aware. In particular it will have regard to the extent to which Practice Direction (Pre-Action Conduct) or any pre-action protocol has or (as the case may be) has not been complied with.

4.3  At this stage the court’s first concern will be to ensure that the issues between the parties are identified and that the necessary evidence is prepared and disclosed.

4.4  The court may have regard to any document filed by a party with his directions questionnaire containing further information, provided that the document states either that its contents has been agreed with every other party or that it has been served on every other party, and when it was served.

4.5  On the allocation of a claim to the multi-track the court will consider whether it is desirable or necessary to hold a case management conference straight away, or whether it is appropriate instead to give directions on its own initiative.

4.6  Attention is drawn to rule 29.4, which provides that parties must endeavour to agree appropriate directions for the management of the proceedings, and requires the agreed directions or proposals to be submitted to the court within a specified time period.

4.7

(1) To obtain the court’s approval the agreed directions must –

(a) set out a timetable by reference to calendar dates for the taking of steps for the preparation of the case,

(b) include a date or a period (the trial period) when it is proposed that the trial will take place,

(c) include provision about disclosure of documents, and

(d) include provision about both factual and expert evidence.

(2) The court will scrutinise the timetable carefully and in particular will be concerned to see that any proposed date or period for the trial and (if provided for) for a case management conference is no later than is reasonably necessary.

(3) The provision in (1)(c) above may –

(a) limit disclosure to standard disclosure or less than that, and/or

(b) direct that disclosure will take place by the supply of copy documents without a list, but it must in that case say either that the parties must serve a disclosure statement with the copies or that they have agreed to disclose in that way without such a statement.

(4) The provision in (1)(d) about expert evidence may be to the effect that none is required.

4.8  Directions agreed by the parties should also where appropriate contain provisions about:

(1) the filing of any reply or amended statement of case that may be required,

(2) dates for the service of requests for further information under Practice Direction 18 and of questions to experts under rule 35.6 and by when they are to be dealt with,

(3) the disclosure of evidence,

(4) the use of a single joint expert, or in cases where it is not agreed, the exchange of expert evidence (including whether exchange is to be simultaneous or sequential) and without prejudice discussions between experts.

(see paragraphs 6, 7 and 9 of Practice Direction 35)

4.9  If the court does not approve the agreed directions filed by the parties but decides that it will give directions of its own initiative without fixing a case management conference, it will take them into account in deciding what directions to give.

4.10  Where the court is to give directions on its own initiative without holding a case management conference and it is not aware of any steps taken by the parties other than the exchange of statements of case, its general approach will be:

(1) to give directions for the filing and service of any further information required to clarify either party’s case,

(2) to direct standard disclosure between the parties,

(3) to direct the disclosure of witness statements by way of simultaneous exchange,

(4) to give directions for a single joint expert on any appropriate issue unless there is a good reason not to do so,

(5) unless paragraph 4.11 (below) applies, to direct disclosure of experts’ reports by way of simultaneous exchange on those issues where a single joint expert is not directed,

(6) if experts’ reports are not agreed, to direct a discussion between experts for the purpose set out in rule 35.12(1) and the preparation of a statement under rule 35.12(3),

(7) to list a case management conference to take place after the date for compliance with those directions,

(8) to specify a trial period; and

(9) in such cases as the court thinks appropriate, the court may give directions requiring the parties to consider ADR. Such directions may be, for example, in the following terms:

The parties shall by [date] consider whether the case is capable of resolution by ADR. If any party considers that the case is unsuitable for resolution by ADR, that party shall be prepared to justify that decision at the conclusion of the trial, should the judge consider that such means of resolution were appropriate, when he is considering the appropriate costs order to make.

The party considering the case unsuitable for ADR shall, not less than 28 days before the commencement of the trial, file with the court a witness statement without prejudice save as to costs, giving reasons upon which they rely for saying that the case was unsuitable.

4.11  If it appears that expert evidence will be required both on issues of liability and on the amount of damages, the court may direct that the exchange of those reports that relate to liability will be exchanged simultaneously but that those relating to the amount of damages will be exchanged sequentially.

4.12

(1) If it appears to the court that it cannot properly give directions on its own initiative and no agreed directions have been filed which it can approve, the court will direct a case management conference to be listed.

(2) The conference will be listed as promptly as possible.

4.13  Where the court is proposing on its own initiative to make an order under rule 35.7 (which gives the court power to direct that evidence on a particular issue is to be given by a single expert) or under rule 35.15 (which gives the court power to appoint an assessor), the court must, unless the parties have consented in writing to the order, list a case management conference.

Case management conferences

5.1  The court will at any case management conference:

(1) review the steps which the parties have taken in the preparation of the case, and in particular their compliance with any directions that the court may have given,

(2) decide and give directions about the steps which are to be taken to secure the progress of the claim in accordance with the overriding objective, and

(3) ensure as far as it can that all agreements that can be reached between the parties about the matters in issue and the conduct of the claim are made and recorded.

5.2

(1) Rule 29.3(2) provides that where a party has a legal representative, a representative familiar with the case and with sufficient authority to deal with any issues that are likely to arise must attend case management conferences and pre-trial reviews.

(2) That person should be someone who is personally involved in the conduct of the case, and who has the authority and information to deal with any matter which may reasonably be expected to be dealt with at such a hearing, including the fixing of the timetable, the identification of issues and matters of evidence.

(3) Where the inadequacy of the person attending or of his instructions leads to the adjournment of a hearing, the court will expect to make a wasted costs order.

5.3  The topics the court will consider at a case management conference are likely to include:

(1) whether the claimant has made clear the claim he is bringing, in particular the amount he is claiming, so that the other party can understand the case he has to meet,

(2) whether any amendments are required to the claim, a statement of case or any other document,

(3) what disclosure of documents, if any, is necessary,

(4) what expert evidence is reasonably required in accordance with rule 35.1 and how and when that evidence should be obtained and disclosed,

(5) what factual evidence should be disclosed,

(6) what arrangements should be made about the giving of clarification or further information and the putting of questions to experts, and

(7) whether it will be just and will save costs to order a split trial or the trial of one or more preliminary issues.

5.4  In all cases the court will set a timetable for the steps it decides are necessary to be taken. These steps may include the holding of a case management conference or a pre-trial review, and the court will be alert to perform its duty to fix a trial date or period as soon as it can.

5.5

(1) The court will not at this stage give permission to use expert evidence unless it can identify each expert by name or field in its order and say whether his evidence is to be given orally or by the use of his report.

(2) A party who obtains expert evidence before obtaining a direction about it does so at his own risk as to costs, except where he obtained the evidence in compliance with a pre-action protocol.

5.6  To assist the court, the parties and their legal advisers should:

(1) ensure that all documents that the court is likely to ask to see (including witness statements and experts’ reports) are brought to the hearing,

(2) consider whether the parties should attend,

(3) consider whether a case summary will be useful, and

(4) consider what orders each wishes to be made and give notice of them to the other parties.

5.7

(1) A case summary:

(a) should be designed to assist the court to understand and deal with the questions before it,

(b) should set out a brief chronology of the claim, the issues of fact which are agreed or in dispute and the evidence needed to decide them,

(c) should not normally exceed 500 words in length, and

(d) should be prepared by the claimant and agreed with the other parties if possible.

5.8

(1) Where a party wishes to obtain an order not routinely made at a case management conference and believes that his application will be opposed, he should issue and serve the application in time for it to be heard at the case management conference.

(2) If the time allowed for the case management conference is likely to be insufficient for the application to be heard he should inform the court at once so that a fresh date can be fixed.

(3) A costs sanction may be imposed on a party who fails to comply with sub-paragraph (1) or (2).

5.9  At a case management conference the court may also consider whether the case ought to be tried by a High Court judge or by a judge who specialises in that type of claim and how that question will be decided. In that case the claim may need to be transferred to another court.

Variation of directions

6.1  This paragraph deals with the procedure to be adopted:

(1) where a party is dissatisfied with a direction given by the court,

(2) where the parties have agreed about changes they wish made to the directions given, or

(3) where a party wishes to apply to vary a direction.

6.2

(1) It is essential that any party who wishes to have a direction varied takes steps to do so as soon as possible.

(2) The court will assume for the purposes of any later application that a party who did not appeal, and who made no application to vary within 14 days of service of the order containing the directions, was content that they were correct in the circumstances then existing.

6.3

(1) Where a party is dissatisfied with a direction given or other order made by the court he may appeal or apply to the court for it to reconsider its decision.

(2) Unless paragraph 6.4 applies, a party should appeal if the direction was given or the order was made at a hearing at which he was present, or of which he had due notice.

(3) In any other case he should apply to the court to reconsider its decision.

(4) If an application is made for the court to reconsider its decision:

(a) it will usually be heard by the judge who gave the directions or another judge of the same level,

(b) the court will give all parties at least 3 days notice of the hearing, and

(c) the court may confirm its directions or make a different order.

6.4  Where there has been a change in the circumstances since the order was made the court may set aside or vary a direction it has given. It may do so on application or on its own initiative.

6.5  Where the parties agree about changes they wish made to the directions given:

(1) If rule 2.11 (variation by agreement of a date set by the court for doing any act other than those stated in the note to that rule) or rule 31.5, 31.10(8) or 31.13 (agreements about disclosure) applies the parties need not file the written agreement.

(2)

(a) In any other case the parties must apply for an order by consent.

(b) The parties must file a draft of the order sought and an agreed statement of the reasons why the variation is sought.

(c) The court may make an order in the agreed terms or in other terms without a hearing, but it may direct that a hearing is to be listed.

Failure to comply with case management directions

7.1  Where a party fails to comply with a direction given by the court any other party may apply for an order that he must do so or for a sanction to be imposed or both of these.

7.2  The party entitled to apply for such an order must do so without delay but should first warn the other party of his intention to do so.

7.3  The court may take any such delay into account when it decides whether to make an order imposing a sanction or to grant relief from a sanction imposed by the rules or any other practice direction.

7.4

(1) The court will not allow a failure to comply with directions to lead to the postponement of the trial unless the circumstances are exceptional.

(2) If it is practical to do so the court will exercise its powers in a manner that enables the case to come on for trial on the date or within the period previously set.

(3) In particular the court will assess what steps each party should take to prepare the case for trial, direct that those steps are taken in the shortest possible time and impose a sanction for non-compliance. Such a sanction may, for example, deprive a party of the right to raise or contest an issue or to rely on evidence to which the direction relates.

(4) Where it appears that one or more issues are or can be made ready for trial at the time fixed while others cannot, the court may direct that the trial will proceed on the issues which are then ready, and direct that no costs will be allowed for any later trial of the remaining issues or that those costs will be paid by the party in default.

(5) Where the court has no option but to postpone the trial it will do so for the shortest possible time and will give directions for the taking of the necessary steps in the meantime as rapidly as possible.

(6) Litigants and lawyers must be in no doubt that the court will regard the postponement of a trial as an order of last resort. Where it appears inevitable the court may exercise its power to require a party as well as his legal representative to attend court at the hearing where such an order is to be sought.

(7) The court will not postpone any other hearing without a very good reason, and for that purpose the failure of a party to comply on time with directions previously given will not be treated as a good reason.

Pre-trial check lists (listing questionnaires)

8.1

(1) The pre-trial check list (listing questionnaire) will be in Form N170.

(2) Unless it dispenses with pre-trial check lists and orders an early trial on a fixed date, the court will specify the date for filing completed pre-trial check lists when it fixes the trial date or trial period under rule 29.2(2).

(3) The date for filing the completed pre-trial check list will be not later than 8 weeks before the trial date or the start of the trial period.

(4) The court will serve the pre-trial check lists on the parties at least 14 days before that date.

(5) Although the rules do not require the parties to exchange copies of the check lists before they are filed they are encouraged to do so to avoid the court being given conflicting or incomplete information.

(6) The file will be placed before a judge for his directions when all the check lists have been filed or when the time for filing them has expired and where a party has filed a checklist but another party has not done so.

8.2  The court’s general approach will be as set out in the following paragraphs. The court may however decide to make other orders, and in particular the court will take into account the steps, if any, of which it is aware which the parties have taken to prepare the case for trial.

8.3

(1) Where no party files a pre-trial checklist the court will order that unless a completed pre-trial checklist is filed within 7 days from service of that order, the claim, defence and any counterclaim will be struck out without further order of the court.

(2) Where a party files a pre-trial check list but another party (the defaulting party) does not do so, the court will fix a hearing under rule 29.6(4). Whether or not the defaulting party attends the hearing, the court will normally fix or confirm the trial date and make other orders about the steps to be taken to prepare the case for trial.

8.4  Where the court decides to hold a hearing under rule 29.6(4) the court will fix a date which is as early as possible and the parties will be given at least 3 days notice of the date.

8.5  Where the court decides to hold a pre-trial review (whether or not this is in addition to a hearing under rule 29.6(4)) the court will give the parties at least 7 days notice of the date.

Directions the court will give on listing

9.1

Directions the court must give

The court must fix the trial date or week, give a time estimate and fix the place of trial.

9.2

Other directions

(1) The parties should seek to agree directions and may file an agreed order. The court may make an order in those terms or it may make a different order.

(2) Agreed directions should include provision about:

(a) evidence especially expert evidence,

(b) a trial timetable and time estimate,

(c) the preparation of a trial bundle, and

(d) any other matter needed to prepare the case for trial.

(3) The court will include such of these provisions as are appropriate in any order that it may make, whether or not the parties have filed agreed directions.

(4) Unless a direction doing so has been given before, a direction giving permission to use expert evidence will say whether it gives permission to use oral evidence or reports or both and will name the experts concerned.

9.3  The principles set out in paragraph 6 of this practice direction about variation of directions applies equally to directions given at this stage.

The trial

10.1  The trial will normally take place at a Civil Trial Centre but it may be at another court if it is appropriate having regard to the needs of the parties and the availability of court resources.

10.2  The judge will generally have read the papers in the trial bundle and may dispense with an opening address.

10.3  The judge may confirm or vary any timetable given previously, or if none has been given set his own.

10.4  Attention is drawn to the provisions in Part 32 and the following parts of the Rules about evidence, and in particular:

(1) to rule 32.1 (court’s power to control evidence and to restrict cross-examination), and

(2) to rule 32.5(2) statements and reports to stand as evidence in chief.

10.5  In an appropriate case the judge may summarily assess costs in accordance with rule 44.6. Attention is drawn to the practice directions about costs and the steps the parties are required to take.

10.6  Once the trial of a multi-track claim has begun, the judge will normally sit on consecutive court days until it has been concluded.

PART 32 - EVIDENCE

Contents of this Part

Power of court to control evidence

32.1

(1) The court may control the evidence by giving directions as to –

(a) the issues on which it requires evidence;

(b) the nature of the evidence which it requires to decide those issues; and

(c) the way in which the evidence is to be placed before the court.

(2) The court may use its power under this rule to exclude evidence that would otherwise be admissible.

(3) The court may limit cross-examination(GL).

Evidence of witnesses – general rule

32.2

(1) The general rule is that any fact which needs to be proved by the evidence of witnesses is to be proved –

(a) at trial, by their oral evidence given in public; and

(b) at any other hearing, by their evidence in writing.

(2) This is subject –

(a) to any provision to the contrary contained in these Rules or elsewhere; or

(b) to any order of the court.

(3) The court may give directions –

(a) identifying or limiting the issues to which factual evidence may be directed;

(b) identifying the witnesses who may be called or whose evidence may be read; or

(c) limiting the length or format of witness statements.

Evidence by video link or other means

32.3  The court may allow a witness to give evidence through a video link or by other means.

Requirement to serve witness statements for use at trial

32.4

(1) A witness statement is a written statement signed by a person which contains the evidence which that person would be allowed to give orally.

(2) The court will order a party to serve on the other parties any witness statement of the oral evidence which the party serving the statement intends to rely on in relation to any issues of fact to be decided at the trial.

(3) The court may give directions as to –

(a) the order in which witness statements are to be served; and

(b) whether or not the witness statements are to be filed.

Use at trial of witness statements which have been served

32.5

(1) If –

(a) a party has served a witness statement; and

(b) he wishes to rely at trial on the evidence of the witness who made the statement,

he must call the witness to give oral evidence unless the court orders otherwise or he puts the statement in as hearsay evidence.

(Part 33 contains provisions about hearsay evidence)

(2) Where a witness is called to give oral evidence under paragraph (1), his witness statement shall stand as his evidence in chief(GL) unless the court orders otherwise.

(3) A witness giving oral evidence at trial may with the permission of the court –

(a) amplify his witness statement; and

(b) give evidence in relation to new matters which have arisen since the witness statement was served on the other parties.

(4) The court will give permission under paragraph (3) only if it considers that there is good reason not to confine the evidence of the witness to the contents of his witness statement.

(5) If a party who has served a witness statement does not–

(a) call the witness to give evidence at trial; or

(b) put the witness statement in as hearsay evidence, any other party may put the witness statement in as hearsay evidence.

Evidence in proceedings other than at trial

32.6

(1) Subject to paragraph (2), the general rule is that evidence at hearings other than the trial is to be by witness statement unless the court, a practice direction or any other enactment requires otherwise.

(2) At hearings other than the trial, a party may, rely on the matters set out in –

(a) his statement of case; or

(b) his application notice, if the statement of case or application notice is verified by a statement of truth.

Order for cross-examination

32.7

(1) Where, at a hearing other than the trial, evidence is given in writing, any party may apply to the court for permission to cross-examine the person giving the evidence.

(2) If the court gives permission under paragraph (1) but the person in question does not attend as required by the order, his evidence may not be used unless the court gives permission.

(Rules 78.26 to 78.28 contain rules in relation to evidence arising out of mediation of certain cross-border disputes. Rule 78.27(1)(b) relates specifically to this rule.)

Form of witness statement

32.8  A witness statement must comply with the requirements set out in Practice Direction 32.

(Part 22 requires a witness statement to be verified by a statement of truth)

Witness summaries

32.9

(1) A party who –

(a) is required to serve a witness statement for use at trial; but

(b) is unable to obtain one, may apply, without notice, for permission to serve a witness summary instead.

(2) A witness summary is a summary of –

(a) the evidence, if known, which would otherwise be included in a witness statement; or

(b) if the evidence is not known, the matters about which the party serving the witness summary proposes to question the witness.

(3) Unless the court orders otherwise, a witness summary must include the name and address of the intended witness.

(4) Unless the court orders otherwise, a witness summary must be served within the period in which a witness statement would have had to be served.

(5) Where a party serves a witness summary, so far as practicable rules 32.4 (requirement to serve witness statements for use at trial), 32.5(3) (amplifying witness statements), and 32.8 (form of witness statement) shall apply to the summary.

Consequence of failure to serve witness statement or summary

32.10  If a witness statement or a witness summary for use at trial is not served in respect of an intended witness within the time specified by the court, then the witness may not be called to give oral evidence unless the court gives permission.

Cross-examination on a witness statement

32.11  Where a witness is called to give evidence at trial, he may be cross-examined on his witness statement whether or not the statement or any part of it was referred to during the witness’s evidence in chief(GL).

Use of witness statements for other purposes

32.12

(1) Except as provided by this rule, a witness statement may be used only for the purpose of the proceedings in which it is served.

(2) Paragraph (1) does not apply if and to the extent that–

(a) the witness gives consent in writing to some other use of it;

(b) the court gives permission for some other use; or

(c) the witness statement has been put in evidence at a hearing held in public.

Availability of witness statements for inspection

32.13

(1) A witness statement which stands as evidence in chief(GL) is open to inspection during the course of the trial unless the court otherwise directs.

(2) Any person may ask for a direction that a witness statement is not open to inspection.

(3) The court will not make a direction under paragraph (2) unless it is satisfied that a witness statement should not be open to inspection because of –

(a) the interests of justice;

(b) the public interest;

(c) the nature of any expert medical evidence in the statement;

(d) the nature of any confidential information (including information relating to personal financial matters) in the statement; or

(e) the need to protect the interests of any child or protected party.

(4) The court may exclude from inspection words or passages in the statement.

False statements

32.14

(1) Proceedings for contempt of court may be brought against a person if he makes, or causes to be made, a false statement in a document verified by a statement of truth without an honest belief in its truth.

(Part 22 makes provision for a statement of truth)

(Section 6 of Part 81 contains provisions in relation to committal for making a false statement of truth.)

2 Proceedings under this rule may be brought only – a by the Attorney General; or b with the permission of the court.

Affidavit evidence

32.15

(1) Evidence must be given by affidavit(GL) instead of or in addition to a witness statement if this is required by the court, a provision contained in any other rule, a practice direction or any other enactment.

(2) Nothing in these Rules prevents a witness giving evidence by affidavit at a hearing other than the trial if he chooses to do so in a case where paragraph (1) does not apply, but the party putting forward the affidavit may not recover the additional cost of making it from any other party unless the court orders otherwise.

Form of affidavit

32.16  An affidavit(GL) must comply with the requirements set out in Practice Direction 32.

Affidavit made outside the jurisdiction

32.17  A person may make an affidavit(GL) outside the jurisdiction in accordance with –

(a) this Part; or

(b) the law of the place where he makes the affidavit.

Notice to admit facts

32.18

(1) A party may serve notice on another party requiring him to admit the facts, or the part of the case of the serving party, specified in the notice.

(2) A notice to admit facts must be served no later than 21 days before the trial.

(3) Where the other party makes any admission in response to the notice, the admission may be used against him only –

(a) in the proceedings in which the notice to admit is served; and

(b) by the party who served the notice.

(4) The court may allow a party to amend or withdraw any admission made by him on such terms as it thinks just.

Notice to admit or produce documents

32.19

(1) A party shall be deemed to admit the authenticity of a document disclosed to him under Part 31 (disclosure and inspection of documents) unless he serves notice that he wishes the document to be proved at trial.

(2) A notice to prove a document must be served –

(a) by the latest date for serving witness statements; or

(b) within 7 days of disclosure of the document, whichever is later.

Notarial acts and instruments

32.20  A notarial act or instrument may be received in evidence without further proof as duly authenticated in accordance with the requirements of law unless the contrary is proved.

PRACTICE DIRECTION 34B – FEES FOR EXAMINERS OF THE COURT

This Practice Direction supplements CPR Part 34

Scope

1.1

This practice direction sets out –

(1) how to calculate the fees an examiner of the court (‘an examiner’) may charge; and

(2) the expenses he may recover.

(CPR Rule 34.8 (3) (b) provides that the court may make an order for evidence to be obtained by the examination of a witness before an examiner of the court).

1.2

The party who obtained the order for the examination must pay the fees and expenses of the examiner.

(CPR rule 34.14 permits an examiner to charge a fee for the examination and contains other provisions about his fees and expenses, and rule 34.15 provides who may be appointed as an examiner of the court).

The examination fee

2.1

An examiner may charge an hourly rate for each hour (or part of an hour) that he is engaged in examining the witness.

2.2

The hourly rate is to be calculated by reference to the formula set out in paragraph 3.

2.3

The examination fee will be the hourly rate multiplied by the number of hours the examination has taken. For example –

Examination fee = hourly rate x number of hours.

How to calculate the hourly rate – the formula

3.1

Divide the amount of the minimum annual salary of a post within Group 7 of the judicial salary structure as designated by the Review Body on Senior Salaries[1], by 220 to give ‘x’; and then divide ‘x’ by 6 to give the hourly rate.

For example –

Single fee chargeable on making the appointment for examination

4.1

An examiner of court is also entitled to charge a single fee of twice the hourly rate (calculated in accordance with paragraph 3 above) as ‘the appointment fee’ when the appointment for the examination is made.

4.2

The examiner is entitled to retain the appointment fee where the witness fails to attend on the date and time arranged.

4.3

Where the examiner fails to attend on the date and time arranged he may not charge a further appointment fee for arranging a subsequent appointment.

(The examiner need not send the deposition to the court until his fees are paid – see CPR rule 34.14 (2)).

Examiner’s expenses

5.1

The examiner of court is also entitled to recover the following expenses –

(1) all reasonable travelling expenses;

(2) any other expenses reasonably incurred; and

(3) subject to paragraph 5.2, any reasonable charge for the room where the examination takes place.

5.2

No expenses may be recovered under sub-paragraph (3) above if the examination takes place at the examiner’s usual business address.

(If the examiner’s fees and expenses are not paid within a reasonable time he may report the fact to the court, see CPR Rule 34.14 (4) and (5)).

Footnotes

1. The Report of the Review Body on Senior Salaries is published annually by the Stationery Office. Back to text

PART 35 - EXPERTS AND ASSESSORS

Duty to restrict expert evidence

35.1

Expert evidence shall be restricted to that which is reasonably required to resolve the proceedings.

Interpretation and definitions

35.2

(1) A reference to an ‘expert’ in this Part is a reference to a person who has been instructed to give or prepare expert evidence for the purpose of proceedings.

(2) ‘Single joint expert’ means an expert instructed to prepare a report for the court on behalf of two or more of the parties (including the claimant) to the proceedings.

Experts – overriding duty to the court

35.3

(1) It is the duty of experts to help the court on matters within their expertise.

(2) This duty overrides any obligation to the person from whom experts have received instructions or by whom they are paid.

Court’s power to restrict expert evidence

35.4

(1) No party may call an expert or put in evidence an expert’s report without the court’s permission.

(2) When parties apply for permission they must provide an estimate of the costs of the proposed expert evidence and identify –

(a) the field in which expert evidence is required and the issues which the expert evidence will address; and

(b) where practicable, the name of the proposed expert.

(3) If permission is granted it shall be in relation only to the expert named or the field identified under paragraph (2). The order granting permission may specify the issues which the expert evidence should address.

(3A) Where a claim has been allocated to the small claims track or the fast track, if permission is given for expert evidence, it will normally be given for evidence from only one expert on a particular issue.

(Paragraph 7 of Practice Direction 35 sets out some of the circumstances the court will consider when deciding whether expert evidence should be given by a single joint expert.)

(4) The court may limit the amount of a party’s expert’s fees and expenses that may be recovered from any other party.

General requirement for expert evidence to be given in a written report

35.5

(1) Expert evidence is to be given in a written report unless the court directs otherwise.

(2) If a claim is on the small claims track or the fast track, the court will not direct an expert to attend a hearing unless it is necessary to do so in the interests of justice.

Written questions to experts

35.6

(1) A party may put written questions about an expert's report (which must be proportionate) to –

(a) an expert instructed by another party; or

(b) a single joint expert appointed under rule 35.7.

(2) Written questions under paragraph (1) –

(a) may be put once only;

(b) must be put within 28 days of service of the expert’s report; and

(c) must be for the purpose only of clarification of the report,

unless in any case –

(i) the court gives permission; or

(ii) the other party agrees.

(3) An expert’s answers to questions put in accordance with paragraph (1) shall be treated as part of the expert’s report.

(4) Where –

(a) a party has put a written question to an expert instructed by another party; and

(b) the expert does not answer that question,

the court may make one or both of the following orders in relation to the party who instructed the expert –

(i) that the party may not rely on the evidence of that expert; or

(ii) that the party may not recover the fees and expenses of that expert from any other party.

Court’s power to direct that evidence is to be given by a single joint expert

35.7

(1) Where two or more parties wish to submit expert evidence on a particular issue, the court may direct that the evidence on that issue is to be given by a single joint expert.

(2) Where the parties who wish to submit the evidence (‘the relevant parties’) cannot agree who should be the single joint expert, the court may –

(a) select the expert from a list prepared or identified by the relevant parties; or

(b) direct that the expert be selected in such other manner as the court may direct.

Instructions to a single joint expert

35.8

(1) Where the court gives a direction under rule 35.7 for a single joint expert to be used, any relevant party may give instructions to the expert.

(2) When a party gives instructions to the expert that party must, at the same time, send a copy to the other relevant parties.

(3) The court may give directions about –

(a) the payment of the expert’s fees and expenses; and

(b) any inspection, examination or experiments which the expert wishes to carry out.

(4) The court may, before an expert is instructed –

(a) limit the amount that can be paid by way of fees and expenses to the expert; and

(b) direct that some or all of the relevant parties pay that amount into court.

(5) Unless the court otherwise directs, the relevant parties are jointly and severally liable[GL] for the payment of the expert’s fees and expenses.

Power of court to direct a party to provide information

35.9

Where a party has access to information which is not reasonably available to another party, the court may direct the party who has access to the information to –

(a) prepare and file a document recording the information; and

(b) serve a copy of that document on the other party.

Contents of report

35.10

(1) An expert’s report must comply with the requirements set out in Practice Direction 35.

(2) At the end of an expert’s report there must be a statement that the expert understands and has complied with their duty to the court.

(3) The expert’s report must state the substance of all material instructions, whether written or oral, on the basis of which the report was written.

(4) The instructions referred to in paragraph (3) shall not be privileged[GL] against disclosure but the court will not, in relation to those instructions –

(a) order disclosure of any specific document; or

(b) permit any questioning in court, other than by the party who instructed the expert,

unless it is satisfied that there are reasonable grounds to consider the statement of instructions given under paragraph (3) to be inaccurate or incomplete.

Use by one party of expert’s report disclosed by another

35.11

Where a party has disclosed an expert’s report, any party may use that expert’s report as evidence at the trial.

Discussions between experts

35.12

(1) The court may, at any stage, direct a discussion between experts for the purpose of requiring the experts to –

(a) identify and discuss the expert issues in the proceedings; and

(b) where possible, reach an agreed opinion on those issues.

(2) The court may specify the issues which the experts must discuss.

(3) The court may direct that following a discussion between the experts they must prepare a statement for the court setting out those issues on which –

(a) they agree; and

(b) they disagree, with a summary of their reasons for disagreeing.

(4) The content of the discussion between the experts shall not be referred to at the trial unless the parties agree.

(5) Where experts reach agreement on an issue during their discussions, the agreement shall not bind the parties unless the parties expressly agree to be bound by the agreement.

Consequence of failure to disclose expert’s report

35.13

A party who fails to disclose an expert’s report may not use the report at the trial or call the expert to give evidence orally unless the court gives permission.

Expert’s right to ask court for directions

35.14

(1) Experts may file written requests for directions for the purpose of assisting them in carrying out their functions.

(2) Experts must, unless the court orders otherwise, provide copies of the proposed requests for directions under paragraph (1) –

(a) to the party instructing them, at least 7 days before they file the requests; and

(b) to all other parties, at least 4 days before they file them.

(3) The court, when it gives directions, may also direct that a party be served with a copy of the directions.

Assessors

35.15

(1) This rule applies where the court appoints one or more persons under section 70 of the Senior Courts Act 1981[1] or section 63 of the County Courts Act 1984[2]as an assessor.

(2) An assessor will assist the court in dealing with a matter in which the assessor has skill and experience.

(3) An assessor will take such part in the proceedings as the court may direct and in particular the court may direct an assessor to –

(a) prepare a report for the court on any matter at issue in the proceedings; and

(b) attend the whole or any part of the trial to advise the court on any such matter.

(4) If an assessor prepares a report for the court before the trial has begun –

(a) the court will send a copy to each of the parties; and

(b) the parties may use it at trial.

(5) The remuneration to be paid to an assessor is to be determined by the court and will form part of the costs of the proceedings.

(6) The court may order any party to deposit in the court office a specified sum in respect of an assessor’s fees and, where it does so, the assessor will not be asked to act until the sum has been deposited.

(7) Paragraphs (5) and (6) do not apply where the remuneration of the assessor is to be paid out of money provided by Parliament.

Footnotes

1. 1981 c. 54. Back to text

2. 1984 c. 28. Back to text

PRACTICE DIRECTION 35 – EXPERTS AND ASSESSORS

This Practice Direction supplements CPR Part 35

Introduction

1

Part 35 is intended to limit the use of oral expert evidence to that which is reasonably required. In addition, where possible, matters requiring expert evidence should be dealt with by only one expert. Experts and those instructing them are expected to have regard to the guidance contained in the Protocol for the Instruction of Experts to give Evidence in Civil Claims annexed to this practice direction. (Further guidance on experts is contained in Annex C to the Practice Direction (Pre-Action Conduct)).

Expert Evidence – General Requirements

2.1

Expert evidence should be the independent product of the expert uninfluenced by the pressures of litigation.

2.2

Experts should assist the court by providing objective, unbiased opinions on matters within their expertise, and should not assume the role of an advocate.

2.3

Experts should consider all material facts, including those which might detract from their opinions.

2.4

Experts should make it clear –

(a) when a question or issue falls outside their expertise; and

(b) when they are not able to reach a definite opinion, for example because they have insufficient information.

2.5

If, after producing a report, an expert's view changes on any material matter, such change of view should be communicated to all the parties without delay, and when appropriate to the court.

Form and Content of an Expert’s Report

3.1

An expert's report should be addressed to the court and not to the party from whom the expert has received instructions.

3.2

An expert's report must:

(1) give details of the expert's qualifications;

(2) give details of any literature or other material which has been relied on in making the report;

(3) contain a statement setting out the substance of all facts and instructions which are material to the opinions expressed in the report or upon which those opinions are based;

(4) make clear which of the facts stated in the report are within the expert's own knowledge;

(5) say who carried out any examination, measurement, test or experiment which the expert has used for the report, give the qualifications of that person, and say whether or not the test or experiment has been carried out under the expert's supervision;

(6) where there is a range of opinion on the matters dealt with in the report –

(a) summarise the range of opinions; and

(b) give reasons for the expert's own opinion;

(7) contain a summary of the conclusions reached;

(8) if the expert is not able to give an opinion without qualification, state the qualification; and

(9) contain a statement that the expert –

(a) understands their duty to the court, and has complied with that duty; and

(b) is aware of the requirements of Part 35, this practice direction and the Protocol for Instruction of Experts to give Evidence in Civil Claims.

3.3

An expert's report must be verified by a statement of truth in the following form –

I confirm that I have made clear which facts and matters referred to in this report are within my own knowledge and which are not. Those that are within my own knowledge I confirm to be true. The opinions I have expressed represent my true and complete professional opinions on the matters to which they refer.

(Part 22 deals with statements of truth. Rule 32.14 sets out the consequences of verifying a document containing a false statement without an honest belief in its truth.)

Information

4

Under rule 35.9 the court may direct a party with access to information, which is not reasonably available to another party to serve on that other party a document, which records the information. The document served must include sufficient details of all the facts, tests, experiments and assumptions which underlie any part of the information to enable the party on whom it is served to make, or to obtain, a proper interpretation of the information and an assessment of its significance.

Instructions

5

Cross-examination of experts on the contents of their instructions will not be allowed unless the court permits it (or unless the party who gave the instructions consents). Before it gives permission the court must be satisfied that there are reasonable grounds to consider that the statement in the report of the substance of the instructions is inaccurate or incomplete. If the court is so satisfied, it will allow the cross-examination where it appears to be in the interests of justice.

Questions to Experts

6.1

Where a party sends a written question or questions under rule 35.6 direct to an expert, a copy of the questions must, at the same time, be sent to the other party or parties.

6.2

The party or parties instructing the expert must pay any fees charged by that expert for answering questions put under rule 35.6. This does not affect any decision of the court as to the party who is ultimately to bear the expert's fees.

Single joint expert

7

When considering whether to give permission for the parties to rely on expert evidence and whether that evidence should be from a single joint expert the court will take into account all the circumstances in particular, whether:

(a) it is proportionate to have separate experts for each party on a particular issue with reference to –

(i) the amount in dispute;

(ii) the importance to the parties; and

(iii) the complexity of the issue;

(b) the instruction of a single joint expert is likely to assist the parties and the court to resolve the issue more speedily and in a more cost-effective way than separately instructed experts;

(c) expert evidence is to be given on the issue of liability, causation or quantum;

(d) the expert evidence falls within a substantially established area of knowledge which is unlikely to be in dispute or there is likely to be a range of expert opinion;

(e) a party has already instructed an expert on the issue in question and whether or not that was done in compliance with any practice direction or relevant pre-action protocol;

(f) questions put in accordance with rule 35.6 are likely to remove the need for the other party to instruct an expert if one party has already instructed an expert;

(g) questions put to a single joint expert may not conclusively deal with all issues that may require testing prior to trial;

(h) a conference may be required with the legal representatives, experts and other witnesses which may make instruction of a single joint expert impractical; and

(i) a claim to privilege[GL] makes the instruction of any expert as a single joint expert inappropriate.

Orders

8

Where an order requires an act to be done by an expert, or otherwise affects an expert, the party instructing that expert must serve a copy of the order on the expert. The claimant must serve the order on a single joint expert.

Discussions between experts

9.1

Unless directed by the court discussions between experts are not mandatory. Parties must consider, with their experts, at an early stage, whether there is likely to be any useful purpose in holding an experts’ discussion and if so when.

9.2

The purpose of discussions between experts is not for experts to settle cases but to agree and narrow issues and in particular to identify:

(i) the extent of the agreement between them;

(ii) the points of and short reasons for any disagreement;

(iii) action, if any, which may be taken to resolve any outstanding points of disagreement; and

(iv) any further material issues not raised and the extent to which these issues are agreed.

9.3

Where the experts are to meet, the parties must discuss and if possible agree whether an agenda is necessary, and if so attempt to agree one that helps the experts to focus on the issues which need to be discussed. The agenda must not be in the form of leading questions or hostile in tone.

9.4

Unless ordered by the court, or agreed by all parties, and the experts, neither the parties nor their legal representatives may attend experts discussions.

9.5

If the legal representatives do attend –

(i) they should not normally intervene in the discussion, except to answer questions put to them by the experts or to advise on the law; and

(ii) the experts may if they so wish hold part of their discussions in the absence of the legal representatives.

9.6

A statement must be prepared by the experts dealing with paragraphs 9.2(i) - (iv) above. Individual copies of the statements must be signed by the experts at the conclusion of the discussion, or as soon thereafter as practicable, and in any event within 7 days. Copies of the statements must be provided to the parties no later than 14 days after signing.

9.7

Experts must give their own opinions to assist the court and do not require the authority of the parties to sign a joint statement.

9.8

If an expert significantly alters an opinion, the joint statement must include a note or addendum by that expert explaining the change of opinion.

Assessors

10.1

An assessor may be appointed to assist the court under rule 35.15. Not less than 21 days before making any such appointment, the court will notify each party in writing of the name of the proposed assessor, of the matter in respect of which the assistance of the assessor will be sought and of the qualifications of the assessor to give that assistance.

10.2

Where any person has been proposed for appointment as an assessor, any party may object to that person either personally or in respect of that person's qualification.

10.3

Any such objection must be made in writing and filed with the court within 7 days of receipt of the notification referred to in paragraph 10.1 and will be taken into account by the court in deciding whether or not to make the appointment.

10.4

Copies of any report prepared by the assessor will be sent to each of the parties but the assessor will not give oral evidence or be open to cross-examination or questioning.

Concurrent expert evidence

11.1

At any stage in the proceedings the court may direct that some or all of the experts from like disciplines shall give their evidence concurrently. The following procedure shall then apply.

11.2

The court may direct that the parties agree an agenda for the taking of concurrent evidence, based upon the areas of disagreement identified in the experts' joint statements made pursuant to rule 35.12.

11.3

At the appropriate time the relevant experts will each take the oath or affirm. Unless the court orders otherwise, the experts will then address the items on the agenda in the manner set out in paragraph 11.4.

11.4

In relation to each issue on the agenda, and subject to the judge's discretion to modify the procedure –

(1) the judge may initiate the discussion by asking the experts, in turn, for their views. Once an expert has expressed a view the judge may ask questions about it. At one or more appropriate stages when questioning a particular expert, the judge may invite the other expert to comment or to ask that expert's own questions of the first expert;

(2) after the process set out in (1) has been completed for all the experts, the parties' representatives may ask questions of them. While such questioning may be designed to test the correctness of an expert's view, or seek clarification of it, it should not cover ground which has been fully explored already. In general a full cross-examination or re-examination is neither necessary nor appropriate; and

(3) after the process set out in (2) has been completed, the judge may summarise the experts' different positions on the issue and ask them to confirm or correct that summary.

Annex

Protocol for the Instruction of Experts to give Evidence in Civil Claims (PDF - opens in new window)

PRACTICE DIRECTION 36B – 36B

This Practice Direction supplements CPR Part 36

From 6th April 2007, new rules came into force concerning offers to settle, and Part 36, as it was in force immediately before 6th April 2007, was substituted by a new Part 36.

Rule 7 of the Civil Procedure (Amendment No.3) Rules 2006 that brought those new rules into force and replaced the previous rules contained some provisions that dealt with how the rules are to apply to offers and payments into court made before 6th April 2007.

This Practice Direction explains how those provisions will operate.

Offers and Payments made before 6th April 2007

1.1

Paragraph (2) of rule 7 provides that where a Part 36 offer or Part 36 payment was made before 6th April 2007, if it would have had the consequences set out in the rules of court contained in Part 36 as it was in force immediately before 6th April 2007, it will have the consequences set out in rules 36.10, 36.11 and 36.14 after that date.

1.2

This provision makes clear that a Part 36 offer or Part 36 payment that was valid before 6th April 2007, will continue to be a valid Part 36 offer under the rules in force from 6th April 2007, and will have the consequences set out in those rules, specifically in relation to costs and the effect of acceptance.

Permission of the court

2.1

Paragraph (3) of rule 7 provides that where a Part 36 offer or Part 36 payment was made before 6th April 2007, the permission of the court is required to accept that offer or payment, if permission would have been required under the rules of court contained in Part 36 as it was in force immediately before 6th April 2007.

2.2

This provision preserves the requirement to obtain the permission of the court to accept an offer as it existed under the rules in force immediately before 6th April 2007. Therefore, if permission would have been required before 6th April 2007, it will be required after that date. But, if permission would not have been required because the parties have been able to agree liability for costs, or if a further offer has been made triggering a new period for acceptance, permission will not be required after 6th April 2007.

Payments into court made before 6th April 2007

3.1

Paragraph (4) of rule 7 provides that rule 37.3 will apply to a Part 36 payment made before 6th April 2007 as if that payment into court had been made under a court order.

3.2

Rule 37.3 applies to all payments under Part 37, including payments into court under order, and permission is required to take the money out of court.

3.3

By applying rule 37.3 to payments into court made before 6th April 2007, this provision preserves in particular the requirement that permission be obtained to withdraw such payment.

3.4

But, rule 37.3 also provides that money may be taken out of court without the court’s permission where a Part 36 offer (including an offer underlying a Part 36 payment) is accepted without needing the permission of the court and the defendant agrees that the sum may be paid out in satisfaction of the offer. Paragraph 3.4 of the Practice Direction to Part 37 makes provision about how to take money out of court.

3.5

This exception to the permission requirement preserves the right under rule 37.2, as it was in force immediately before 6th April 2007, to treat a payment into court made under order or by way of a defence of tender before claim as a Part 36 payment.

3.6

This provision has the effect that a Part 36 payment made before 6th April 2007 may be taken out of court simply by filing a request for payment if the offer underlying the Part 36 payment is accepted without needing permission. In those circumstances, it may be assumed that the defendant agrees to the money being used in satisfaction of the sum offered, and the requirement in paragraph 3.4 of the Practice Direction to Part 37 to file a Form 202 will not apply.

Offers remaining open for acceptance

4.1

Paragraph (5) of rule 7 provides that the rules of court contained in Part 36 as it was in force immediately before 6th April 2007 shall continue to apply to a Part 36 offer or Part 36 payment made less than 21 days before 6th April 2007.

4.2

This provision preserves those rules in their entirety in relation to offers and payments made less than 21 days before 6th April 2007 for the period that they are expressed to remain open for acceptance.

4.3

Paragraph (6) of rule 7 provides that paragraph (5) ceases to apply at the expiry of 21 days from the date that the offer or payment was made, unless the trial has started within that period.

4.4

This provision has the effect that once the 21 day period has expired, the new regime (including the modifications at paragraphs (2), (3) and (4) of rule 7) will apply to the offer or payment.

4.5

If the trial has started within the 21 day period, the rules that were in force before 6th April 2007 will continue to apply to the offer or payment.

Offers made before commencement of proceedings

5.1

Paragraph (7) of rule 7 deals with the position where, before 6th April 2007, a person made an offer to settle before commencement of proceedings which complied with the provisions of rule 36.10 as it was in force immediately before 6th April 2007.

5.2

The court will take that offer into account when making any order as to costs. This preserves the discretion of the court to take into account an offer made before commencement of proceedings as it existed before 6th April 2007.

5.3

The permission of the court will be required to accept such an offer after proceedings have been commenced. This preserves the position under rule 36.10(4) as it was in force immediately before 6th April 2007.

5.4

If proceedings are commenced after 6th April 2007, the requirement to pay money into court in respect of a defendant's money offer under rule 36.10(3)(a) (as it was in force before 6th April 2007) will not an apply to a defendant's money offer made before the proceedings were commenced.

PART 39 - MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS RELATING TO HEARINGS

Contents of this Part

Interpretation

39.1  In this Part, reference to a hearing includes a reference to the trial.

General rule – hearing to be in public

39.2

(1) The general rule is that a hearing is to be in public.

(2) The requirement for a hearing to be in public does not require the court to make special arrangements for accommodating members of the public.

(3) A hearing, or any part of it, may be in private if –

(a) publicity would defeat the object of the hearing;

(b) it involves matters relating to national security;

(c) it involves confidential information (including information relating to personal financial matters) and publicity would damage that confidentiality;

(d) a private hearing is necessary to protect the interests of any child or protected party;

(e) it is a hearing of an application made without notice and it would be unjust to any respondent for there to be a public hearing;

(f) it involves uncontentious matters arising in the administration of trusts or in the administration of a deceased person’s estate; or

(g) the court considers this to be necessary, in the interests of justice.

(4) The court may order that the identity of any party or witness must not be disclosed if it considers non-disclosure necessary in order to protect the interests of that party or witness.

Failure to attend the trial

39.3

(1) The court may proceed with a trial in the absence of a party but –

(a) if no party attends the trial, it may strike out(GL) the whole of the proceedings;

(b) if the claimant does not attend, it may strike out his claim and any defence to counterclaim; and

(c) if a defendant does not attend, it may strike out his defence or counterclaim (or both).

(2) Where the court strikes out proceedings, or any part of them, under this rule, it may subsequently restore the proceedings, or that part.

(3) Where a party does not attend and the court gives judgment or makes an order against him, the party who failed to attend may apply for the judgment or order to be set aside(GL).

(4) An application under paragraph (2) or paragraph (3) must be supported by evidence.

(5) Where an application is made under paragraph (2) or (3) by a party who failed to attend the trial, the court may grant the application only if the applicant –

(a) acted promptly when he found out that the court had exercised its power to strike out(GL) or to enter judgment or make an order against him;

(b) had a good reason for not attending the trial; and

(c) has a reasonable prospect of success at the trial.

Timetable for trial

39.4  When the court sets a timetable for a trial in accordance with rule 28.6 (confirming the trial date and giving directions – fast track) or rule 29.8 (setting a trial timetable and fixing or confirming the trial date or week – multi-track) it will do so in consultation with the parties.

Trial bundles

39.5

(1) Unless the court orders otherwise, the claimant must file a trial bundle containing documents required by –

(a) a relevant practice direction; and

(b) any court order.

(2) The claimant must file the trial bundle not more than 7 days and not less than 3 days before the start of the trial.

Representation at trial of companies or other corporations

39.6  A company or other corporation may be represented at trial by an employee if –

(a) the employee has been authorised by the company or corporation to appear at trial on its behalf; and

(b) the court gives permission.

Impounded documents

39.7

(1) Documents impounded by order of the court must not be released from the custody of the court except in compliance –

(a) with a court order; or

(b) with a written request made by a Law Officer or the Director of Public Prosecutions.

(2) A document released from the custody of the court under paragraph(1)(b) must be released into the custody of the person who requested it.

(3) Documents impounded by order of the court, while in the custody of the court, may not be inspected except by a person authorised to do so by a court order.

Omitted

39.8

PRACTICE DIRECTION 39A – MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS RELATING TO HEARINGS

This Practice Direction supplements CPR Part 39

Hearings

1.1

In Part 39, reference to a hearing includes reference to the trial[1].

1.2

The general rule is that a hearing is to be in public[2].

1.3

Rule 39.2(3) sets out the type of proceedings which may be dealt with in private.

1.4

The decision as to whether to hold a hearing in public or in private must be made by the judge conducting the hearing having regard to any representations which may have been made to him.

1.4A

The judge should also have regard to Article 6(1) of the European Convention on Human Rights. This requires that, in general, court hearings are to be held in public, but the press and public may be excluded in the circumstances specified in that Article. Article 6(1) will usually be relevant, for example, where a party applies for a hearing which would normally be held in public to be held in private as well as where a hearing would normally be held in private. The judge may need to consider whether the case is within any of the exceptions permitted by Article 6(1).

1.5

The hearings set out below shall in the first instance be listed by the court as hearings in private under rule 39.2(3)(c), namely:

(1) a claim by a mortgagee against one or more individuals for an order for possession of land,

(2) a claim by a landlord against one or more tenants or former tenants for the repossession of a dwelling house based on the non-payment of rent,

(3) an application to suspend a warrant of execution or a warrant of possession or to stay execution where the court is being invited to consider the ability of a party to make payments to another party,

(4) a redetermination under rule 14.13 or an application to vary or suspend the payment of a judgment debt by instalments,

(5) an application for a charging order (including an application to enforce a charging order), third party debt order, attachment of earnings order, administration order, or the appointment of a receiver,

(6) an order to attend court for questioning,

(7) the determination of the liability of an LSC funded client under regulations 9 and 10 of the Community Legal Service (Costs) Regulations 2000, or of an assisted person’s liability for costs under regulation 127 of the Civil Legal Aid (General) Regulations 1989,

(8) an application for security for costs to be provided by a claimant who is a company or a limited liability partnership in the circumstances set out in rule 25.13(2)(c),

(9) proceedings brought under the Consumer Credit Act 1974, the Inheritance (Provision for Family and Dependants) Act 1975 or the Protection from Harassment Act 1997,

(10) an application by a trustee or personal representative for directions as to bringing or defending legal proceedings.

1.6

Rule 39.2(3)(d) states that a hearing may be in private where it involves the interests of a child or protected party. This includes the approval of a compromise or settlement on behalf of a child or protected party or an application for the payment of money out of court to such a person.

1.7

Attention is drawn to paragraph 5.1 of Practice Direction 27 (relating to the hearing of claims in the small claims track), which provides that the judge may decide to hold a small claim hearing in private if the parties agree or if a ground mentioned in rule 39.2(3) applies. A hearing of a small claim in premises other than the court will not be a hearing in public.

1.7A

Attention is drawn to paragraph 31.2(8) of Practice Direction 52D, which provides that an appeal to a county court against certain decisions under the Representation of the People Act 1983 is to be heard in private unless the court orders otherwise. Attention is also drawn to paragraph 31.2(9) of that practice direction, which provides that an appeal to the Court of Appeal against such a decision of a county court may be heard in private if the Court of Appeal so orders.

1.8

Nothing in this practice direction prevents a judge ordering that a hearing taking place in public shall continue in private, or vice-versa.

1.9

If the court or judge’s room in which the proceedings are taking place has a sign on the door indicating that the proceedings are private, members of the public who are not parties to the proceedings will not be admitted unless the court permits.

1.10

Where there is no such sign on the door of the court or judge’s room, members of the public will be admitted where practicable. The judge may, if he thinks it appropriate, adjourn the proceedings to a larger room or court.

1.11

When a hearing takes place in public, members of the public may obtain a transcript of any judgment given or a copy of any order made, subject to payment of the appropriate fee.

1.12

When a judgment is given or an order is made in private, if any member of the public who is not a party to the proceedings seeks a transcript of the judgment or a copy of the order, he must seek the leave of the judge who gave the judgment or made the order.

1.13

A judgment or order given or made in private, when drawn up, must have clearly marked in the title:

‘Before [title and name of judge] sitting in Private’

1.14

References to hearings being in public or private or in a judge’s room contained in the Civil Procedure Rules (including the Rules of the Supreme Court and the County Court Rules scheduled to Part 50) and the practice directions which supplement them do not restrict any existing rights of audience or confer any new rights of audience in respect of applications or proceedings which under the rules previously in force would have been heard in court or in chambers respectively.

1.15

Where the court lists a hearing of a claim by a mortgagee for an order for possession of land under paragraph 1.5(1) above to be in private, any fact which needs to be proved by the evidence of witnesses may be proved by evidence in writing.

(CPR rule 32.2 sets out the general rule as to how evidence is to be given and facts are to be proved.)

Failure to attend the trial

2.1

Rule 39.3 sets out the consequences of a party’s failure to attend the trial.

2.2

The court may proceed with a trial in the absence of a party[3]. In the absence of:

(1) the defendant, the claimant may –

(a) prove his claim at trial and obtain judgment on his claim and for costs, and

(b) seek the striking out of any counterclaim,

(2) the claimant, the defendant may –

(a) prove any counterclaim at trial and obtain judgment on his counterclaim and for costs, and

(b) seek the striking out of the claim, or

(3) both parties, the court may strike out the whole of the proceedings.

2.3

Where the court has struck out proceedings, or any part of them, on the failure of a party to attend, that party may apply in accordance with Part 23 for the proceedings, or that part of them, to be restored and for any judgment given against that party to be set aside[4].

2.4

The application referred to in paragraph 2.3 above must be supported by evidence giving reasons for the failure to attend court and stating when the applicant found out about the order against him.

Bundles of documents for hearings or trial

3.1

Unless the court orders otherwise, the claimant must file the trial bundle not more than 7 days and not less than 3 days before the start of the trial.

3.2

Unless the court orders otherwise, the trial bundle should include a copy of:

(1) the claim form and all statements of case,

(2) a case summary and/or chronology where appropriate,

(3) requests for further information and responses to the requests,

(4) all witness statements to be relied on as evidence,

(5) any witness summaries,

(6) any notices of intention to rely on hearsay evidence under rule 32.2,

(7) any notices of intention to rely on evidence (such as a plan, photograph etc.) under rule 33.6 which is not –

(a) contained in a witness statement, affidavit or experts report,

(b) being given orally at trial,

(c) hearsay evidence under rule 33.2,

(8) any medical reports and responses to them,

(9) any experts’ reports and responses to them,

(10) any order giving directions as to the conduct of the trial, and

(11) any other necessary documents.

3.3

The originals of the documents contained in the trial bundle, together with copies of any other court orders should be available at the trial.

3.4

The preparation and production of the trial bundle, even where it is delegated to another person, is the responsibility of the legal representative[5] who has conduct of the claim on behalf of the claimant.

3.5

The trial bundle should be paginated (continuously) throughout, and indexed with a description of each document and the page number. Where the total number of pages is more than 100, numbered dividers should be placed at intervals between groups of documents.

3.6

The bundle should normally be contained in a ring binder or lever arch file. Where more than one bundle is supplied, they should be clearly distinguishable, for example, by different colours or letters. If there are numerous bundles, a core bundle should be prepared containing the core documents essential to the proceedings, with references to the supplementary documents in the other bundles.

3.7

For convenience, experts’ reports may be contained in a separate bundle and cross referenced in the main bundle.

3.8

If a document to be included in the trial bundle is illegible, a typed copy should be included in the bundle next to it, suitably cross-referenced.

3.9

The contents of the trial bundle should be agreed where possible. The parties should also agree where possible:

(1) that the documents contained in the bundle are authentic even if not disclosed under Part 31, and

(2) that documents in the bundle may be treated as evidence of the facts stated in them even if a notice under the Civil Evidence Act 1995 has not been served.

Where it is not possible to agree the contents of the bundle, a summary of the points on which the parties are unable to agree should be included.

3.10

The party filing the trial bundle should supply identical bundles to all the parties to the proceedings and for the use of the witnesses.

Settlement or discontinuance after the trial date is fixed

4.1

Where:

(1) an offer to settle a claim is accepted,

(2) or a settlement is reached, or

(3) a claim is discontinued, which disposes of the whole of a claim for which a date or ‘window’ has been fixed for the trial, the parties must ensure that the listing officer for the trial court is notified immediately.

4.2

If an order is drawn up giving effect to the settlement or discontinuance, a copy of the sealed order should be filed with the listing officer.

Representation at hearings

5.1

At any hearing, a written statement containing the following information should be provided for the court:

(1) the name and address of each advocate,

(2) his qualification or entitlement to act as an advocate, and

(3) the party for whom he so acts.

5.2

Where a party is a company or other corporation and is to be represented at a hearing by an employee the written statement should contain the following additional information:

(1) The full name of the company or corporation as stated in its certificate of registration.

(2) The registered number of the company or corporation.

(3) The position or office in the company or corporation held by the representative.

(4) The date on which and manner in which the representative was authorised to act for the company or corporation, e.g. ________ 19____: written authority from managing director; or ________ 19____: Board resolution dated ________ 19____ .

5.3

Rule 39.6 is intended to enable a company or other corporation to represent itself as a litigant in person. Permission under rule 39.6(b) should therefore be given by the court unless there is some particular and sufficient reason why it should be withheld. In considering whether to grant permission the matters to be taken into account include the complexity of the issues and the experience and position in the company or corporation of the proposed representative.

5.4

Permission under rule 39.6(b) should be obtained in advance of the hearing from, preferably, the judge who is to hear the case, but may, if it is for any reason impracticable or inconvenient to do so, be obtained from any judge by whom the case could be heard.

5.5

The permission may be obtained informally and without notice to the other parties. The judge who gives the permission should record in writing that he has done so and supply a copy to the company or corporation in question and to any other party who asks for one.

5.6

Permission should not normally be granted under Rule 39.6:

(a) in jury trials;

(b) in contempt proceedings.

Recording of proceedings

6.1

At any hearing, whether in the High Court or a county court, the proceedings will be tape recorded unless the judge directs otherwise.

6.2

No party or member of the public may use unofficial recording equipment in any court or judge’s room without the permission of the court. To do so without permission constitutes a contempt of court[6].

6.3

Any party or person may require a transcript or transcripts of the recording of any hearing to be supplied to him, upon payment of the charges authorised by any scheme in force for the making of the recording or the transcript.

6.4

Where the person requiring the transcript or transcripts is not a party to the proceedings and the hearing or any part of it was held in private under CPR rule 39.2, paragraph 6.3 does not apply unless the court so orders.

6.5

Attention is drawn to paragraph 7.9 of the Court of Appeal (Civil Division) Practice Direction which deals with the provision of transcripts for use in the Court of Appeal at public expense.

Exhibits at trial

7

Exhibits which are handed in and proved during the course of the trial should be recorded on an exhibit list and kept in the custody of the court until the conclusion of the trial, unless the judge directs otherwise. At the conclusion of the trial it is the parties’responsibility to obtain the return of those exhibits which they handed in and to preserve them for the period in which any appeal may take place.

Citation of Authorities Human Rights

8.1

If it is necessary for a party to give evidence at a hearing of an authority referred to in section 2 of the Human Rights Act 1998–

(1) the authority to be cited should be an authoritative and complete report; and

(2) the party must give to the court and any other party a list of the authorities he intends to cite and copies of the reports not less than three days before the hearing.

(Section 2(1) of the Human Rights Act 1998 requires the court to take into account the authorities listed there)

(3) Copies of the complete original texts issued by the European Court and Commission either paper based or from the Court’s judgment database (HUDOC), which is available on the Internet, may be used.

Footnotes

1. Rule 39.1. Back to text

2. Rule 39.2(1). Back to text

3. Rule 39.3(1). Back to text

4. Rule 39.3(2) and (3). Back to text

5. For the definition of legal representative see rule 2.3. Back to text

6. Section 9 of the Contempt of Court Act 1981. Back to text

PRACTICE DIRECTION 54A – JUDICIAL REVIEW

This Practice Direction supplements Part 54

SECTION I – GENERAL PROVISIONS RELATING TO JUDICIAL REVIEW

1.1

In addition to Part 54 and this practice direction attention is drawn to:

section 31 of the Senior Courts Act 1981; and
the Human Rights Act 1998

The Court

2.1

Part 54 claims for judicial review are dealt with in the Administrative Court.

(Practice Direction 54D) contains provisions about where a claim for judicial review may be started, administered and heard.)

2.2

Omitted

2.3

Omitted

2.4

Omitted

3.1

Omitted

3.2

Omitted

Rule 54.5 – Time limit for filing claim form

4.1

Where the claim is for a quashing order in respect of a judgment, order or conviction, the date when the grounds to make the claim first arose, for the purposes of rule 54.5(1)(b), is the date of that judgment, order or conviction.

Rule 54.6 – Claim form

Interested parties

5.1

Where the claim for judicial review relates to proceedings in a court or tribunal, any other parties to those proceedings must be named in the claim form as interested parties under rule 54.6(1)(a) (and therefore served with the claim form under rule 54.7(b)).

5.2

For example, in a claim by a defendant in a criminal case in the Magistrates or Crown Court for judicial review of a decision in that case, the prosecution must always be named as an interested party.

Human rights

5.3

Where the claimant is seeking to raise any issue under the Human Rights Act 1998, or seeks a remedy available under that Act, the claim form must include the information required by paragraph 15 of Practice Direction 16.

Devolution issues

5.4

Where the claimant intends to raise a devolution issue, the claim form must:

(1) specify that the applicant wishes to raise a devolution issue and identify the relevant provisions of the Government of Wales Act 2006, the Northern Ireland Act 1998 or the Scotland Act 1998; and

(2) contain a summary of the facts, circumstances and points of law on the basis of which it is alleged that a devolution issue arises.

5.5

In this practice direction ‘devolution issue’ has the same meaning as in paragraph 1, Schedule 9 to the Government of Wales Act 2006, paragraph 1, Schedule 10 to the Northern Ireland Act 1998; and paragraph 1, Schedule 6 to the Scotland Act 1998.

Claim form

5.6

The claim form must include or be accompanied by –

(1) a detailed statement of the claimant’s grounds for bringing the claim for judicial review;

(2) a statement of the facts relied on;

(3) any application to extend the time limit for filing the claim form;

(4) any application for directions.

5.7

In addition, the claim form must be accompanied by

(1) any written evidence in support of the claim or application to extend time;

(2) a copy of any order that the claimant seeks to have quashed;

(3) where the claim for judicial review relates to a decision of a court or tribunal, an approved copy of the reasons for reaching that decision;

(4) copies of any documents on which the claimant proposes to rely;

(5) copies of any relevant statutory material; and

(6) a list of essential documents for advance reading by the court (with page references to the passages relied on).

5.8

Where it is not possible to file all the above documents, the claimant must indicate which documents have not been filed and the reasons why they are not currently available.

Bundle of documents

5.9

The claimant must file two copies of a paginated and indexed bundle containing all the documents referred to in paragraphs 5.6 and 5.7.

5.10

Attention is drawn to rules 8.5(1) and 8.5(7).

Rule 54.7 – Service of claim form

6.1

Except as required by rules 54.11 or 54.12(2), the Administrative Court will not serve documents and service must be effected by the parties.

6.2

Where the defendant or interested party to the claim for judicial review is –

(a) the Immigration and Asylum Chamber of the First-tier Tribunal, the address for service of the claim form is Official Correspondence Unit, PO Box 6987, Leicester, LE1 6ZX or fax number 0116 249 4240;

(b) the Crown, service of the claim form must be effected on the solicitor acting for the relevant government department as if the proceedings were civil proceedings as defined in the Crown Proceedings Act 1947.

(Practice Direction 66 gives the list published under section 17 of the Crown Proceedings Act 1947 of the solicitors acting in civil proceedings (as defined in that Act) for the different government departments on whom service is to be effected, and of their addresses.)

(Part 6 contains provisions about the service of claim forms.)

Rule 54.8 – Acknowledgment of service

7.1

Attention is drawn to rule 8.3(2) and the relevant practice direction and to rule 10.5.

Rule 54.10 – Permission given

Directions

8.1

Case management directions under rule 54.10(1) may include directions about serving the claim form and any evidence on other persons.

8.2

Where a claim is made under the Human Rights Act 1998, a direction may be made for giving notice to the Crown or joining the Crown as a party. Attention is drawn to rule 19.4A and paragraph 6 of Practice Direction 19A.

8.3

Omitted

Permission without a hearing

8.4

The court will generally, in the first instance, consider the question of permission without a hearing.

Permission hearing

8.5

Neither the defendant nor any other interested party need attend a hearing on the question of permission unless the court directs otherwise.

8.6

Where the defendant or any party does attend a hearing, the court will not generally make an order for costs against the claimant.

Rule 54.11 – Service of order giving or refusing permission

9.1

An order refusing permission or giving it subject to conditions or on certain grounds only must set out or be accompanied by the court’s reasons for coming to that decision.

Rule 54.14 – Response

10.1

Where the party filing the detailed grounds intends to rely on documents not already filed, he must file a paginated bundle of those documents when he files the detailed grounds.

Rule 54.15 – Where claimant seeks to rely on additional grounds

11.1

Where the claimant intends to apply to rely on additional grounds at the hearing of the claim for judicial review, he must give notice to the court and to any other person served with the claim form no later than 7 clear days before the hearing (or the warned date where appropriate).

Rule 54.16 – Evidence

12.1

Disclosure is not required unless the court orders otherwise.

Rule 54.17 – Court’s powers to hear any person

13.1

Where all the parties consent, the court may deal with an application under rule 54.17 without a hearing.

13.2

Where the court gives permission for a person to file evidence or make representations at the hearing of the claim for judicial review, it may do so on conditions and may give case management directions.

13.3

An application for permission should be made by letter to the Administrative Court office, identifying the claim, explaining who the applicant is and indicating why and in what form the applicant wants to participate in the hearing.

13.4

If the applicant is seeking a prospective order as to costs, the letter should say what kind of order and on what grounds.

13.5

Applications to intervene must be made at the earliest reasonable opportunity, since it will usually be essential not to delay the hearing.

Rule 54.20 – Transfer

14.1

Attention is drawn to rule 30.5.

14.2

In deciding whether a claim is suitable for transfer to the Administrative Court, the court will consider whether it raises issues of public law to which Part 54 should apply.

Skeleton arguments

15.1

The claimant must file and serve a skeleton argument not less than 21 working days before the date of the hearing of the judicial review (or the warned date).

15.2

The defendant and any other party wishing to make representations at the hearing of the judicial review must file and serve a skeleton argument not less than 14 working days before the date of the hearing of the judicial review (or the warned date).

15.3

Skeleton arguments must contain:

(1) a time estimate for the complete hearing, including delivery of judgment;

(2) a list of issues;

(3) a list of the legal points to be taken (together with any relevant authorities with page references to the passages relied on);

(4) a chronology of events (with page references to the bundle of documents (see paragraph 16.1);

(5) a list of essential documents for the advance reading of the court (with page references to the passages relied on) (if different from that filed with the claim form) and a time estimate for that reading; and

(6) a list of persons referred to.

Bundle of documents to be filed

16.1

The claimant must file a paginated and indexed bundle of all relevant documents required for the hearing of the judicial review when he files his skeleton argument.

16.2

The bundle must also include those documents required by the defendant and any other party who is to make representations at the hearing.

Agreed final order

17.1

If the parties agree about the final order to be made in a claim for judicial review, the claimant must file at the court a document (with 2 copies) signed by all the parties setting out the terms of the proposed agreed order together with a short statement of the matters relied on as justifying the proposed agreed order and copies of any authorities or statutory provisions relied on.

17.2

The court will consider the documents referred to in paragraph 17.1 and will make the order if satisfied that the order should be made.

17.3

If the court is not satisfied that the order should be made, a hearing date will be set.

17.4

Where the agreement relates to an order for costs only, the parties need only file a document signed by all the parties setting out the terms of the proposed order.

SECTION II – APPLICATIONS FOR PERMISSION TO APPLY FOR JUDICIAL REVIEW IN IMMIGRATION AND ASYLUM CASES – CHALLENGING REMOVAL

18.1

(1) This Section applies where –

(a) a person has been served with a copy of directions for his removal from the United Kingdom by the UK Border Agency of the Home Office and notified that this Section applies; and

(b) that person makes an application for permission to apply for judicial review before his removal takes effect.

(2) This Section does not prevent a person from applying for judicial review after he has been removed.

(3) The requirements contained in this Section of this Practice Direction are additional to those contained elsewhere in the Practice Direction.

18.2

(1) A person who makes an application for permission to apply for judicial review must file a claim form and a copy at court, and the claim form must –

(a) indicate on its face that this Section of the Practice Direction applies; and

(b) be accompanied by –

(i) a copy of the removal directions and the decision to which the application relates; and

(ii) any document served with the removal directions including any document which contains the UK Border Agency’s factual summary of the case; and

(c) contain or be accompanied by the detailed statement of the claimant's grounds for bringing the claim for judicial review; or

(d) if the claimant is unable to comply with paragraph (b) or (c), contain or be accompanied by a statement of the reasons why.

(2) The claimant must, immediately upon issue of the claim, send copies of the issued claim form and accompanying documents to the address specified by the UK Border Agency.

(Rule 54.7 also requires the defendant to be served with the claim form within 7 days of the date of issue. Rule 6.10 provides that service on a Government Department must be effected on the solicitor acting for that Department, which in the case of the UK Border Agency is the Treasury Solicitor. The address for the Treasury Solicitor may be found in the Annex to Part 66 of these Rules.)

18.3

Where the claimant has not complied with paragraph 18.2(1)(b) or (c) and has provided reasons why he is unable to comply, and the court has issued the claim form, the Administrative Court –

(a) will refer the matter to a Judge for consideration as soon as practicable; and

(b) will notify the parties that it has done so.

18.4

If, upon a refusal to grant permission to apply for judicial review, the Court indicates that the application is clearly without merit, that indication will be included in the order refusing permission.

SECTION III – APPLICATIONS FOR PERMISSION TO APPLY FOR JUDICIAL REVIEW OF DECISIONS OF THE UPPER TRIBUNAL

19.1

A person who makes an application for permission to apply for judicial review of the decision of the Upper Tribunal refusing permission to appeal must file a claim form which must –

(a)state on its face that the application is made under Rule 54. 7A;

(b)set out succinctly the grounds on which it is argued that the criteria in Rule 54.7A(7) are met; and

(c)be accompanied by the supporting documents required under Rule 54.7A(4).

19.2

If the Upper Tribunal or any interested party wishes there to be a hearing of the substantive application under Rule 54.7A(9), it must make its request in writing (by letter copied to the claimant ) for such a hearing no later than 14 days after service of the order granting permission.

PRACTICE DIRECTION 54D – ADMINISTRATIVE COURT (VENUE)

This Practice Direction supplements Part 54

Scope and purpose

1.1

This Practice Direction concerns the place in which a claim before the Administrative Court should be started and administered and the venue at which it will be determined.

1.2

This Practice Direction is intended to facilitate access to justice by enabling cases to be administered and determined in the most appropriate location. To achieve this purpose it provides flexibility in relation to where claims are to be administered and enables claims to be transferred to different venues.

Venue – general provisions

2.1

The claim form in proceedings in the Administrative Court may be issued at the Administrative Court Office of the High Court at –

(1) the Royal Courts of Justice in London; or

(2) at the District Registry of the High Court at Birmingham, Cardiff, Leeds, or Manchester unless the claim is one of the excepted classes of claim set out in paragraph 3 of this Practice Direction which may only be started and determined at the Royal Courts of Justice in London.

2.2

Any claim started in Birmingham will normally be determined at a court in the Midland region (geographically covering the area of the Midland Circuit); in Cardiff in Wales; in Leeds in the North-Eastern Region (geographically covering the area of the North Eastern Circuit); in London at the Royal Courts of Justice; and in Manchester, in the North-Western Region (geographically covering the Northern Circuit).

Excepted classes of claim

3.1

The excepted classes of claim referred to in paragraph 2.1(2) are –

(1) proceedings to which Part 76 or Part 79 applies, and for the avoidance of doubt –

(a) proceedings relating to control orders (within the meaning of Part 76);

(b) financial restrictions proceedings (within the meaning of Part 79);

(c) proceedings relating to terrorism or alleged terrorists (where that is a relevant feature of the claim); and

(d) proceedings in which a special advocate is or is to be instructed;

(2) proceedings to which RSC Order 115 applies;

(3) proceedings under the Proceeds of Crime Act 2002;

(4) appeals to the Administrative Court under the Extradition Act 2003;

(5) proceedings which must be heard by a Divisional Court; and

(6) proceedings relating to the discipline of solicitors.

3.2

If a claim form is issued at an Administrative Court office other than in London and includes one of the excepted classes of claim, the proceedings will be transferred to London.

Urgent applications

4.1

During the hours when the court is open, where an urgent application needs to be made to the Administrative Court outside London, the application must be made to the judge designated to deal with such applications in the relevant District Registry.

4.2

Any urgent application to the Administrative Court during the hours when the court is closed, must be made to the duty out of hours High Court judge by telephoning 020 7947 6000.

Assignment to another venue

5.1

The proceedings may be transferred from the office at which the claim form was issued to another office. Such transfer is a judicial act.

5.2

The general expectation is that proceedings will be administered and determined in the region with which the claimant has the closest connection, subject to the following considerations as applicable –

(1) any reason expressed by any party for preferring a particular venue;

(2) the region in which the defendant, or any relevant office or department of the defendant, is based;

(3) the region in which the claimant’s legal representatives are based;

(4) the ease and cost of travel to a hearing;

(5) the availability and suitability of alternative means of attending a hearing (for example, by videolink);

(6) the extent and nature of media interest in the proceedings in any particular locality;

(7) the time within which it is appropriate for the proceedings to be determined;

(8) whether it is desirable to administer or determine the claim in another region in the light of the volume of claims issued at, and the capacity, resources and workload of, the court at which it is issued;

(9) whether the claim raises issues sufficiently similar to those in another outstanding claim to make it desirable that it should be determined together with, or immediately following, that other claim; and

(10) whether the claim raises devolution issues and for that reason whether it should more appropriately be determined in London or Cardiff.

5.3

(1) When an urgent application is made under paragraph 4.1 or 4.2, this will not by itself decide the venue for the further administration or determination of the claim.

(2) The court dealing with the urgent application may direct that the case be assigned to a particular venue.

(3) When an urgent application is made under paragraph 4.2, and the court does not make a direction under sub-paragraph (2), the claim will be assigned in the first place to London but may be reassigned to another venue at a later date.

5.4

The court may on an application by a party or of its own initiative direct that the claim be determined in a region other than that of the venue in which the claim is currently assigned. The considerations in paragraph 5.2 apply.

5.5

Once assigned to a venue, the proceedings will be both administered from that venue and determined by a judge of the Administrative Court at a suitable court within that region, or, if the venue is in London, at the Royal Courts of Justice. The choice of which court (of those within the region which are identified by the Presiding Judge of the circuit suitable for such hearing) will be decided, subject to availability, by the considerations in paragraph 5.2.

5.6

When giving directions under rule 54.10, the court may direct that proceedings be reassigned to another region for hearing (applying the considerations in paragraph 5.2). If no such direction is given, the claim will be heard in the same region as that in which the permission application was determined (whether on paper or at a hearing).

PART 58 - COMMERCIAL COURT

Scope of this Part and interpretation

58.1

(1) This Part applies to claims in the Commercial Court of the Queen's Bench Division.

(2) In this Part and Practice Direction 58, ‘commercial claim’ means any claim arising out of the transaction of trade and commerce and includes any claim relating to –

(a) a business document or contract;

(b) the export or import of goods;

(c) the carriage of goods by land, sea, air or pipeline;

(d) the exploitation of oil and gas reserves or other natural resources;

(e) insurance and re-insurance;

(f) banking and financial services;

(g) the operation of markets and exchanges;

(h) the purchase and sale of commodities;

(i) the construction of ships;

(j) business agency; and

(k) arbitration.

Specialist list

58.2

(1) The commercial list is a specialist list for claims proceeding in the Commercial Court.

(2) One of the judges of the Commercial Court shall be in charge of the commercial list.

Application of the Civil Procedure Rules

58.3

These Rules and their practice directions apply to claims in the commercial list unless this Part or a practice direction provides otherwise.

Proceedings in the commercial list

58.4

(1) A commercial claim may be started in the commercial list.

(2) Rule 30.5 applies to claims in the commercial list, except that a Commercial Court judge may order a claim to be transferred to any other specialist list.

(Rule 30.5(3) provides that an application for the transfer of proceedings to or from a specialist list must be made to a judge dealing with claims in that list.)

Claim form and particulars of claim

58.5

(1) If, in a Part 7 claim, particulars of claim are not contained in or served with the claim form –

(a) the claim form must state that, if an acknowledgment of service is filed which indicates an intention to defend the claim, particulars of claim will follow;

(b) when the claim form is served, it must be accompanied by the documents specified in rule 7.8(1);

(c) the claimant must serve particulars of claim within 28 days of the filing of an acknowledgment of service which indicates an intention to defend; and

(d) rule 7.4(2) does not apply.

(2) A statement of value is not required to be included in the claim form.

(3) If the claimant is claiming interest, he must –

(a) include a statement to that effect; and

(b) give the details set out in rule 16.4(2),

in both the claim form and the particulars of claim.

Acknowledgment of service

58.6

(1) A defendant must file an acknowledgment of service in every case.

(2) Unless paragraph (3) applies, the period for filing an acknowledgment of service is 14 days after service of the claim form.

(3) Where the claim form is served out of the jurisdiction, or on the agent of a defendant who is overseas, the time periods provided by rules 6.12(3), 6.35 and 6.37(5) apply after service of the claim form.

Disputing the court's jurisdiction

58.7

(1) Part 11 applies to claims in the commercial list with the modifications set out in this rule.

(2) An application under rule 11(1) must be made within 28 days after filing an acknowledgment of service.

(3) If the defendant files an acknowledgment of service indicating an intention to dispute the court's jurisdiction, the claimant need not serve particulars of claim before the hearing of the application.

Default judgment

58.8

(1) If, in a Part 7 claim in the commercial list, a defendant fails to file an acknowledgment of service, the claimant need not serve particulars of claim before he may obtain or apply for default judgment in accordance with Part 12.

(2) Rule 12.6(1) applies with the modification that paragraph (a) shall be read as if it referred to the claim form instead of the particulars of claim.

Admissions

58.9

(1) Rule 14.5 does not apply to claims in the commercial list.

(2) If the defendant admits part of a claim for a specified amount of money, the claimant may apply under rule 14.3 for judgment on the admission.

(3) Rule 14.14(1) applies with the modification that paragraph (a) shall be read as if it referred to the claim form instead of the particulars of claim.

Defence and Reply

58.10

(1) Part 15 (defence and reply) applies to claims in the commercial list with the modification to rule 15.8 that the claimant must –

(a) file any reply to a defence; and

(b) serve it on all other parties,

within 21 days after service of the defence.

(2) Rule 6.35 (in relation to the period for filing a defence where the claim form is served out of the jurisdiction) applies to claims in the commercial list, except that if the particulars of claim are served after the defendant has filed an acknowledgment of service the period for filing a defence is 28 days from service of the particulars of claim.

Statements of case

58.11

The court may at any time before or after the issue of the claim form order a claim in the commercial list to proceed without the filing or service of statements of case.

Part 8 claims

58.12

Part 8 applies to claims in the commercial list, with the modification that a defendant to a Part 8 claim who wishes to rely on written evidence must file and serve it within 28 days after filing an acknowledgment of service.

Case management

58.13

(1) All proceedings in the commercial list are treated as being allocated to the multi-track and Part 26 does not apply.

(2) The following parts only of Part 29 apply –

(a) rule 29.3(2) (legal representative to attend case management conferences and pre-trial reviews);

(b) rule 29.5 (variation of case management timetable) with the exception of rule 29.5(1)(c).

(3) As soon as practicable the court will hold a case management conference which must be fixed in accordance with Practice Direction 58.

(4) At the case management conference or at any hearing at which the parties are represented the court may give such directions for the management of the case as it considers appropriate.

Disclosure – ships papers

58.14

(1) If, in proceedings relating to a marine insurance policy, the underwriters apply for specific disclosure under rule 31.12, the court may –

(a) order a party to produce all the ships papers; and

(b) require that party to use his best endeavours to obtain and disclose documents which are not or have not been in his control.

(2) An order under this rule may be made at any stage of the proceedings and on such terms, if any, as to staying the proceedings or otherwise, as the court thinks fit.

Judgments and orders

58.15

(1) Except for orders made by the court on its own initiative and unless the court orders otherwise, every judgment or order will be drawn up by the parties, and rule 40.3 is modified accordingly.

(2) An application for a consent order must include a draft of the proposed order signed on behalf of all the parties to whom it relates.

(3) Rule 40.6 (consent judgments and orders) does not apply.

PRACTICE DIRECTION 59 – MERCANTILE COURTS

This practice direction supplements Part 59

General

1.1

This practice direction applies to mercantile claims.

1.2

Mercantile Courts are established in –

(1) the following district registries of the High Court – Birmingham, Bristol, Cardiff, Chester, Leeds, Liverpool, Manchester, Mold and Newcastle upon Tyne; and

(2) the Commercial Court of the Queen’s Bench Division at the Royal Courts of Justice (called ‘The London Mercantile Court’).

1.3

All mercantile claims will be heard or determined by a Mercantile judge, except that –

(1) an application may be heard and determined by any other judge who, if the claim were not a mercantile claim, would have jurisdiction to determine it, if –

(a) the application is urgent and no Mercantile judge is available to hear it; or

(b) a Mercantile judge directs it to be heard by another judge; and

(2) unless the court otherwise orders, all proceedings for the enforcement of a Mercantile Court judgment or order for the payment of money will be dealt with by a district judge.

1.4

Provisions in other practice directions which refer to a master or district judge are to be read, in relation to mercantile claims, as if they referred to a Mercantile judge.

Starting proceedings in a Mercantile Court

2.1

A claim should only be started in a Mercantile Court if it will benefit from the expertise of a Mercantile judge.

2.2

The claim form must be marked in the top right hand corner ‘Queen's Bench Division, __________ District Registry, Mercantile Court’ or ‘Queen’s Bench Division, The London Mercantile Court’ as appropriate.

2.3

Omitted

2.4

Omitted

Applications before proceedings are issued

3.1

A party who intends to bring a claim in a Mercantile Court must make any application before the claim form is issued to a judge of that court.

3.2

The written evidence in support of such an application should show why the claim is suitable to proceed as a mercantile claim.

Transfer of proceedings to or from a Mercantile Court

4.1

If a claim which has not been issued in a Mercantile Court is suitable to continue as a mercantile claim –

(1) any party wishing the claim to be transferred to a Mercantile Court may make an application for transfer to the court to which transfer is sought;

(2) if all parties consent to the transfer, the application may be made by letter to the mercantile listing officer of the court to which transfer is sought, stating why the case is suitable to be transferred to that court and enclosing the written consents of the parties, the claim form and statements of case.

4.2

If an application for transfer is made to a court which does not have power to make the order, that court may –

(1) adjourn the application to be heard by a Mercantile judge; or

(2) dismiss the application.

4.3

A Mercantile judge may make an order under rule 59.3 of his own initiative.

Default judgment and admissions

5.

The practice directions supplementing Parts 12 and 14 apply with the following modifications –

(1) paragraph 4.1(1) of Practice Direction 12 is to be read as referring to the service of the claim form; and

(2) the references to ‘particulars of claim’ in paragraphs 2.1, 3.1 and 3.2 of Practice Direction 14 are to be read as referring to the claim form.

Variation of time limits by agreement

6.1

If the parties, in accordance with rule 2.11, agree in writing to vary a time limit, the claimant must notify the court in writing, giving brief written reasons for the agreed variation.

6.2

The court may make an order overriding an agreement by the parties varying a time limit.

Case management

7.1

The following parts only of Practice Direction 29 apply –

(1) paragraph 5 (case management conferences), excluding paragraph 5.9 and modified so far as is made necessary by other specific provisions of this practice direction; and

(2) paragraph 7 (failure to comply with case management directions).

7.2

If proceedings are started in a Mercantile Court, the claimant must apply for a case management conference –

(1) for a Part 7 claim, within 14 days of the date when all defendants who intend to file and serve a defence have done so; and

(2) for a Part 8 claim, within 14 days of the date when all defendants who intend to serve evidence have done so.

7.3

If proceedings are transferred to a Mercantile Court, the claimant must apply for a case management conference within 14 days of receiving an acknowledgment of the transfer from the receiving court, unless the judge held, or gave directions for, a case management conference when he made the order transferring the proceedings.

7.4

Any party may, at a time earlier than that provided in paragraphs 7.2 or 7.3, apply in writing to the court to fix a case management conference.

7.5

If the claimant does not make an application in accordance with paragraphs 7.2 or 7.3, any other party may apply for a case management conference.

7.6

The court may fix a case management conference at any time on its own initiative. If it does so, the court will give at least 7 days notice to the parties, unless there are compelling reasons for a shorter period of notice.

7.7

Not less than 7 days before a case management conference –

(1) each party shall file and serve –

(a) a case management information sheet substantially in the form set out at Appendix A to this practice direction; and

(b) an application notice for any order which that party intends to seek at the case management conference, other than directions referred to in the case management information sheet; and

(2) the claimant (or other party applying for the conference) shall in addition file and serve –

(a) a case management file containing –

—  the claim form;

—   the statements of case (excluding schedules of more than 15 pages);

—   any orders already made;

—   the case management information sheets; and

—   a short list of the principal issues to be prepared by the claimant; and

(b) a draft order substantially in the form set out at Appendix B to this practice direction, setting out the directions which that party thinks appropriate.

7.8

In appropriate cases –

(1) the parties may, not less than 7 days before the date fixed for the case management conference, submit agreed directions for the approval of the judge;

(2) the judge will then either –

(a) make the directions proposed; or

(b) make them with alterations; or

(c) require the case management conference to proceed; but

(3) the parties must assume that the conference will proceed until informed to the contrary.

7.9

If the parties submit agreed directions and the judge makes them with alterations, any party objecting to the alterations may, within 7 days of receiving the order containing the directions, apply to the court for the directions to be varied.

7.10

The directions given at the case management conference –

(1) will normally cover all steps in the case through to trial, including the fixing of a trial date or window, or directions for the taking of steps to fix the trial date or window; and

(2) may include the fixing of a progress monitoring date or dates, and make provision for the court to be informed as to the progress of the case at the date or dates fixed.

7.11

If the court fixes a progress monitoring date, it may after that date fix a further case management conference or a pre-trial review on its own initiative if –

(1) no or insufficient information is provided by the parties; or

(2) it is appropriate in view of the information provided.

Pre-trial review and questionnaire

8.1

The court may order a pre-trial review at any time.

8.2

Each party must file and serve a completed pre-trial check list substantially in the form set out in Appendix C to this practice direction –

(1) if a pre-trial review has been ordered, not less than 7 days before the date of the review; or

(2) if no pre-trial review has been ordered, not less than 6 weeks before the trial date.

8.3

When pre-trial check lists are filed under paragraph 8.2(2) –

(1) the judge will consider them and decide whether to order a pre-trial review; and

(2) if he does not order a pre-trial review, he may on his own initiative give directions for the further preparation of the case or as to the conduct of the trial.

8.4

At a pre-trial review –

(1) the parties should if possible be represented by the advocates who will be appearing at the trial;

(2) any representatives appearing must be fully informed and authorised for the purposes of the review; and

(3) the court will give such directions for the conduct of the trial as it sees fit.

Evidence for applications

9.1

The general requirement is that, unless the court orders otherwise –

(1) evidence in support of an application must be filed and served with the application: see rule 23.7(3);

(2) evidence in answer must be filed and served within 14 days after the application is served;

(3) evidence in reply must be filed and served within 7 days of the service of the evidence in answer.

9.2

In any case in which the application is likely to require an oral hearing of more than half a day the periods set out in paragraphs 9.1(2) and (3) will be 28 days and 14 days respectively.

9.3

If the date fixed for the hearing of the application means that the times in paragraphs 9.1(2) and (3) cannot both be achieved, the evidence must be filed and served –

(1) as soon as possible; and

(2) in sufficient time to ensure that the application may fairly proceed on the date fixed.

9.4

The parties may, in accordance with rule 2.11, agree different periods from those provided above, provided that the agreement does not affect the ability to proceed on the date fixed for the hearing of the application.

Files for applications

10.

Before the hearing of any application, the applicant must –

(1) provide to the court and each other party an appropriate indexed file for the application with consecutively numbered pages; and

(2) attach to the file an estimate of the reading time required by the judge.

Judgments and orders

11.1

After any hearing the claimant must draw up a draft order, unless the decision was made on the application of another party in which case that party must do so.

11.2

A draft order must be submitted by the party responsible for drawing it up within 3 clear days of the decision, with sufficient copies for each party and for one to be retained by the court.

11.3

The sealed orders will be returned to the party submitting them, who will be responsible for serving the order on the other parties.

11.4

Orders must be dated with the date of the decision, except for consent orders submitted for approval, which must be left undated.

Annex A

Case Management Information Sheet – Mercantile Courts (PDF - opens in new window)

Annex B

Standard Directions in Mercantile Courts (PDF - opens in new window)

Annex C

Pre-trial Check List – Mercantile Courts (PDF - opens in new window)

PART 61 - ADMIRALTY CLAIMS

Scope and interpretation

61.1

(1) This Part applies to admiralty claims.

(2) In this Part –

(a) ‘admiralty claim’ means a claim within the Admiralty jurisdiction of the High Court as set out in section 20 of the Supreme Court Act 1981[1];

(b) ‘the Admiralty Court’ means the Admiralty Court of the Queen's Bench Division of the High Court of Justice;

(c) ‘claim in rem’ means a claim in an admiralty action in rem;

(d) ‘collision claim’ means a claim within section 20(3)(b) of the Supreme Court Act 1981;

(e) ‘limitation claim’ means a claim under the Merchant Shipping Act 1995[2] for the limitation of liability in connection with a ship or other property;

(f) ‘salvage claim’ means a claim –

(i) for or in the nature of salvage;

(ii) for special compensation under Article 14 of Schedule 11 to the Merchant Shipping Act 1995;

(iii) for the apportionment of salvage; and

(iv) arising out of or connected with any contract for salvage services;

(g) ‘caution against arrest’ means a caution entered in the Register under rule 61.7;

(h) ‘caution against release’ means a caution entered in the Register under rule 61.8;

(i) ‘the Register’ means the Register of cautions against arrest and release which is open to inspection as provided by Practice Direction 61;

(j) ‘the Marshal’ means the Admiralty Marshal;

(k) ‘ship’ includes any vessel used in navigation; and

(l) ‘the Registrar’ means the Queen's Bench Master with responsibility for Admiralty claims.

(3) Part 58 (Commercial Court) applies to claims in the Admiralty Court except where this Part provides otherwise.

(4) The Registrar has all the powers of the Admiralty judge except where a rule or practice direction provides otherwise.

Admiralty claims

61.2

(1) The following claims must be started in the Admiralty Court –

(a) a claim –

(i) in rem;

(ii) for damage done by a ship;

(iii) concerning the ownership of a ship;

(iv) under the Merchant Shipping Act 1995;

(v) for loss of life or personal injury specified in section 20(2)(f) of the Supreme Court Act 1981;

(vi) by a master or member of a crew for wages;

(vii) in the nature of towage; or

(viii) in the nature of pilotage;

(b) a collision claim;

(c) a limitation claim; or

(d) a salvage claim.

(2) Any other admiralty claim may be started in the Admiralty Court.

(3) Rule 30.5 applies to claims in the Admiralty Court except that the Admiralty Court may order the transfer of a claim to –

(a) the Commercial list;

(b) a Mercantile Court;

(c) the Mercantile list at the Central London County Court; or

(d) any other appropriate court.

Claims in rem

61.3

(1) This rule applies to claims in rem.

(2) A claim in rem is started by the issue of an in rem claim form as set out in Practice Direction 61.

(3) Subject to rule 61.4, the particulars of claim must –

(a) be contained in or served with the claim form; or

(b) be served on the defendant by the claimant within 75 days after service of the claim form.

(4) An acknowledgment of service must be filed within 14 days after service of the claim form.

(5) The claim form must be served –

(a) in accordance with Practice Direction 61; and

(b) within 12 months after the date of issue and rules 7.5 and 7.6 are modified accordingly.

(6) If a claim form has been issued (whether served or not), any person who wishes to defend the claim may file an acknowledgment of service.

Special provisions relating to collision claims

61.4

(1) This rule applies to collision claims.

(2) A claim form need not contain or be followed by particulars of claim and rule 7.4 does not apply.

(3) An acknowledgment of service must be filed.

(4) A party who wishes to dispute the court's jurisdiction must make an application under Part 11 within 2 months after filing his acknowledgment of service.

(5) Every party must –

(a) within 2 months after the defendant files the acknowledgment of service; or

(b) where the defendant applies under Part 11, within 2 months after the defendant files the further acknowledgment of service,

file at the court a completed collision statement of case in the form specified in Practice Direction 61.

(6) A collision statement of case must be –

(a) in the form set out in Practice Direction 61; and

(b) verified by a statement of truth.

(7) A claim form in a collision claim may not be served out of the jurisdiction unless –

(a) the case falls within section 22(2)(a), (b) or (c) of the Supreme Court Act 1981[3]; or

(b) the defendant has submitted to or agreed to submit to the jurisdiction; and

the court gives permission in accordance with Section IV of Part 6.

(8) Where permission to serve a claim form out of the jurisdiction is given, the court will specify the period within which the defendant may file an acknowledgment of service and, where appropriate, a collision statement of case.

(9) Where, in a collision claim in rem (‘the original claim’) –

(a)

(i) a Part 20 claim; or

(ii) a cross claim in rem

arising out of the same collision or occurrence is made; and

(b)

(i) the party bringing the original claim has caused the arrest of a ship or has obtained security in order to prevent such arrest; and

(ii) the party bringing the Part 20 claim or cross claim is unable to arrest a ship or otherwise obtain security,

the party bringing the Part 20 claim or cross claim may apply to the court to stay the original claim until sufficient security is given to satisfy any judgment that may be given in favour of that party.

(10) The consequences set out in paragraph (11) apply where a party to a claim to establish liability for a collision claim (other than a claim for loss of life or personal injury) –

(a) makes an offer to settle in the form set out in paragraph (12) not less than 21 days before the start of the trial;

(b) that offer is not accepted; and

(c) the maker of the offer obtains at trial an apportionment equal to or more favourable than his offer.

(11) Where paragraph (10) applies the parties will, unless the court considers it unjust, be entitled to the following costs –

(a) the maker of the offer will be entitled to –

(i) all his costs from 21 days after the offer was made; and

(ii) his costs before then in the percentage to which he would have been entitled had the offer been accepted; and

(b) all other parties to whom the offer was made –

(i) will be entitled to their costs up to 21 days after the offer was made in the percentage to which they would have been entitled had the offer been accepted; but

(ii) will not be entitled to their costs thereafter.

(12) An offer under paragraph (10) must be in writing and must contain –

(a) an offer to settle liability at stated percentages;

(b) an offer to pay costs in accordance with the same percentages;

(c) a term that the offer remain open for 21 days after the date it is made; and

(d) a term that, unless the court orders otherwise, on expiry of that period the offer remains open on the same terms except that the offeree should pay all the costs from that date until acceptance.

Arrest

61.5

(1) In a claim in rem –

(a) a claimant; and

(b) a judgment creditor

may apply to have the property proceeded against arrested.

(2) Practice Direction 61 sets out the procedure for applying for arrest.

(3) A party making an application for arrest must –

(a) request a search to be made in the Register before the warrant is issued to determine whether there is a caution against arrest in force with respect to that property; and

(b) file a declaration in the form set out in Practice Direction 61.

(4) A warrant of arrest may not be issued as of right in the case of property in respect of which the beneficial ownership, as a result of a sale or disposal by any court in any jurisdiction exercising admiralty jurisdiction in rem, has changed since the claim form was issued.

(5) A warrant of arrest may not be issued against a ship owned by a State where by any convention or treaty, the United Kingdom has undertaken to minimise the possibility of arrest of ships of that State until –

(a) notice in the form set out in Practice Direction 61 has been served on a consular officer at the consular office of that State in London or the port at which it is intended to arrest the ship; and

(b) a copy of that notice is attached to any declaration under paragraph (3)(b).

(6) Except –

(a) with the permission of the court; or

(b) where notice has been given under paragraph (5),

a warrant of arrest may not be issued in a claim in rem against a foreign ship belonging to a port of a State in respect of which an order in council has been made under section 4 of the Consular Relations Act 1968[4], until the expiration of 2 weeks from appropriate notice to the consul.

(7) A warrant of arrest is valid for 12 months but may only be executed if the claim form –

(a) has been served; or

(b) remains valid for service at the date of execution.

(8) Property may only be arrested by the Marshal or his substitute.

(9) Property under arrest –

(a) may not be moved unless the court orders otherwise; and

(b) may be immobilised or prevented from sailing in such manner as the Marshal may consider appropriate.

(10) Where an in rem claim form has been issued and security sought, any person who has filed an acknowledgment of service may apply for an order specifying the amount and form of security to be provided.

Security in claim in rem

61.6

(1) This rule applies if, in a claim in rem, security has been given to –

(a) obtain the release of property under arrest; or

(b) prevent the arrest of property.

(2) The court may order that the –

(a) amount of security be reduced and may stay the claim until the order is complied with; or

(b) claimant may arrest or re-arrest the property proceeded against to obtain further security.

(3) The court may not make an order under paragraph (2)(b) if the total security to be provided would exceed the value of the property at the time –

(a) of the original arrest; or

(b) security was first given (if the property was not arrested).

Cautions against arrest

61.7

(1) Any person may file a request for a caution against arrest.

(2) When a request under paragraph (1) is filed the court will enter the caution in the Register if the request is in the form set out in Practice Direction 61 and –

(a) the person filing the request undertakes –

(i) to file an acknowledgment of service; and

(ii) to give sufficient security to satisfy the claim with interest and costs; or

(b) where the person filing the request has constituted a limitation fund in accordance with Article 11 of the Convention on Limitation of Liability for Maritime Claims 1976[5] he –

(i) states that such a fund has been constituted; and

(ii) undertakes that the claimant will acknowledge service of the claim form by which any claim may be begun against the property described in the request.

(3) A caution against arrest –

(a) is valid for 12 months after the date it is entered in the Register; but

(b) may be renewed for a further 12 months by filing a further request.

(4) Paragraphs (1) and (2) apply to a further request under paragraph (3)(b).

(5) Property may be arrested if a caution against arrest has been entered in the Register but the court may order that –

(a) the arrest be discharged; and

(b) the party procuring the arrest pays compensation to the owner of or other persons interested in the arrested property.

Release and cautions against release

61.8

(1) Where property is under arrest –

(a) an in rem claim form may be served upon it; and

(b) it may be arrested by any other person claiming to have an in rem claim against it.

(2) Any person who –

(a) claims to have an in rem right against any property under arrest; and

(b) wishes to be given notice of any application in respect of that property or its proceeds of sale,

may file a request for a caution against release in the form set out in Practice Direction 61.

(3) When a request under paragraph (2) is filed, a caution against release will be entered in the Register.

(4) Property will be released from arrest if –

(a) it is sold by the court;

(b) the court orders release on an application made by any party;

(c)

(i) the arresting party; and

(ii) all persons who have entered cautions against release

file a request for release in the form set out in Practice Direction 61; or

(d) any party files –

(i) a request for release in the form set out in Practice Direction 61 (containing an undertaking); and

(ii) consents to the release of the arresting party and all persons who have entered cautions against release.

(5) Where the release of any property is delayed by the entry of a caution against release under this rule any person who has an interest in the property may apply for an order that the person who entered the caution pay damages for losses suffered by the applicant because of the delay.

(6) The court may not make an order under paragraph (5) if satisfied that there was good reason to –

(a) request the entry of; and

(b) maintain

the caution.

(7) Any person –

(a) interested in property under arrest or in the proceeds of sale of such property; or

(b) whose interests are affected by any order sought or made,

may be made a party to any claim in rem against the property or proceeds of sale.

(8) Where –

(a)

(i) a ship is not under arrest but cargo on board her is; or

(ii) a ship is under arrest but cargo on board her is not; and

(b) persons interested in the ship or cargo wish to discharge the cargo,

they may, without being made parties, request the Marshal to authorise steps to discharge the cargo.

(9) If –

(a) the Marshal considers a request under paragraph (8) reasonable; and

(b) the applicant gives an undertaking in writing acceptable to the Marshal to pay –

(i) his fees; and

(ii) all expenses to be incurred by him or on his behalf

on demand,

the Marshal will apply to the court for an order to permit the discharge of the cargo.

(10) Where persons interested in the ship or cargo are unable or unwilling to give an undertaking as referred to in paragraph (9)(b), they may –

(a) be made parties to the claim; and

(b) apply to the court for an order for –

(i) discharge of the cargo; and

(ii) directions as to the fees and expenses of the Marshal with regard to the discharge and storage of the cargo.

Judgment in default

61.9

(1) In a claim in rem (other than a collision claim) the claimant may obtain judgment in default of –

(a) an acknowledgment of service only if –

(i) the defendant has not filed an acknowledgment of service; and

(ii) the time for doing so set out in rule 61.3(4) has expired; and

(b) defence only if –

(i) a defence has not been filed; and

(ii) the relevant time limit for doing so has expired.

(2) In a collision claim, a party who has filed a collision statement of case within the time specified by rule 61.4(5) may obtain judgment in default of a collision statement of case only if –

(a) the party against whom judgment is sought has not filed a collision statement of case; and

(b) the time for doing so set out in rule 61.4(5) has expired.

(3) An application for judgment in default –

(a) under paragraph (1) or paragraph (2) in an in rem claim must be made by filing –

(i) an application notice as set out in Practice Direction 61;

(ii) a certificate proving service of the claim form; and

(iii) evidence proving the claim to the satisfaction of the court; and

(b) under paragraph (2) in any other claim must be made in accordance with Part 12 with any necessary modifications.

(4) An application notice seeking judgment in default and, unless the court orders otherwise, all evidence in support, must be served on all persons who have entered cautions against release on the Register.

(5) The court may set aside or vary any judgment in default entered under this rule.

(6) The claimant may apply to the court for judgment against a party at whose instance a notice against arrest was entered where –

(a) the claim form has been served on that party;

(b) the sum claimed in the claim form does not exceed the amount specified in the undertaking given by that party in accordance with rule 61.7(2)(a)(ii); and

(c) that party has not fulfilled that undertaking within 14 days after service on him of the claim form.

Sale by the court, priorities and payment out

61.10

(1) An application for an order for the survey, appraisement or sale of a ship may be made in a claim in rem at any stage by any party.

(2) If the court makes an order for sale, it may –

(a) set a time within which notice of claims against the proceeds of sale must be filed; and

(b) the time and manner in which such notice must be advertised.

(3) Any party with a judgment against the property or proceeds of sale may at any time after the time referred to in paragraph (2) apply to the court for the determination of priorities.

(4) An application notice under paragraph (3) must be served on all persons who have filed a claim against the property.

(5) Payment out of the proceeds of sale will be made only to judgment creditors and –

(a) in accordance with the determination of priorities; or

(b) as the court orders.

Limitation claims

61.11

(1) This rule applies to limitation claims.

(2) A claim is started by the issue of a limitation claim form as set out in Practice Direction 61.

(3) The –

(a) claimant; and

(b) at least one defendant

must be named in the claim form, but all other defendants may be described.

(4) The claim form –

(a) must be served on all named defendants and any other defendant who requests service upon him; and

(b) may be served on any other defendant.

(5) The claim form may not be served out of the jurisdiction unless –

(a) the claim falls within section 22(2)(a), (b) or (c) of the Supreme Court Act 1981[6];

(b) the defendant has submitted to or agreed to submit to the jurisdiction of the court; or

(c) the Admiralty Court has jurisdiction over the claim under any applicable Convention; and

the court grants permission in accordance with Section IV of Part 6.

(6) An acknowledgment of service is not required.

(7) Every defendant upon whom a claim form is served must –

(a) within 28 days of service file –

(i) a defence; or

(ii) a notice that the defendant admits the right of the claimant to limit liability; or

(b) if the defendant wishes to –

(i) dispute the jurisdiction of the court; or

(ii) argue that the court should not exercise its jurisdiction,

file within 14 days of service (or where the claim form is served out of the jurisdiction, within the time specified in rule 6.35) an acknowledgment of service as set out in Practice Direction 61.

(8) If a defendant files an acknowledgment of service under paragraph (7)(b) he will be treated as having accepted that the court has jurisdiction to hear the claim unless he applies under Part 11 within 14 days after filing the acknowledgment of service.

(9) Where one or more named defendants admits the right to limit –

(a) the claimant may apply for a restricted limitation decree in the form set out in Practice Direction 61; and

(b) the court will issue a decree in the form set out in Practice Direction 61 limiting liability only against those named defendants who have admitted the claimant's right to limit liability.

(10) A restricted limitation decree –

(a) may be obtained against any named defendant who fails to file a defence within the time specified for doing so; and

(b) need not be advertised, but a copy must be served on the defendants to whom it applies.

(11) Where all the defendants upon whom the claim form has been served admit the claimant's right to limit liability –

(a) the claimant may apply to the Admiralty Registrar for a general limitation decree in the form set out in Practice Direction 61; and

(b) the court will issue a limitation decree.

(12) Where one or more of the defendants upon whom the claim form has been served do not admit the claimant's right to limit, the claimant may apply for a general limitation decree in the form set out in Practice Direction 61.

(13) When a limitation decree is granted the court –

(a) may –

(i) order that any proceedings relating to any claim arising out of the occurrence be stayed;

(ii) order the claimant to establish a limitation fund if one has not been established or make such other arrangements for payment of claims against which liability is limited; or

(iii) if the decree is a restricted limitation decree, distribute the limitation fund; and

(b) will, if the decree is a general limitation decree, give directions as to advertisement of the decree and set a time within which notice of claims against the fund must be filed or an application made to set aside the decree.

(14) When the court grants a general limitation decree the claimant must –

(a) advertise it in such manner and within such time as the court directs; and

(b) file –

(i) a declaration that the decree has been advertised in accordance with paragraph (a); and

(ii) copies of the advertisements.

(15) No later than the time set in the decree for filing claims, each of the defendants who wishes to assert a claim must file and serve his statement of case on –

(a) the limiting party; and

(b) all other defendants except where the court orders otherwise.

(16) Any person other than a defendant upon whom the claim form has been served may apply to the court within the time fixed in the decree to have a general limitation decree set aside.

(17) An application under paragraph (16) must be supported by a declaration –

(a) stating that the applicant has a claim against the claimant arising out of the occurrence; and

(b) setting out grounds for contending that the claimant is not entitled to the decree, either in the amount of limitation or at all.

(18) The claimant may constitute a limitation fund by making a payment into court.

(19) A limitation fund may be established before or after a limitation claim has been started.

(20) If a limitation claim is not commenced within 75 days after the date the fund was established –

(a) the fund will lapse; and

(b) all money in court (including interest) will be repaid to the person who made the payment into court.

(21) Money paid into court under paragraph (18) will not be paid out except under an order of the court.

(22) A limitation claim for –

(a) a restricted decree may be brought by counterclaim; and

(b) a general decree may only be brought by counterclaim with the permission of the court.

Stay of proceedings

61.12

Where the court orders a stay of any claim in rem –

(a) any property under arrest in the claim remains under arrest; and

(b) any security representing the property remains in force,

unless the court orders otherwise.

Assessors

61.13

The court may sit with assessors when hearing –

(a) collision claims; or

(b) other claims involving issues of navigation or seamanship, and

the parties will not be permitted to call expert witnesses unless the court orders otherwise.

Footnotes

1. 1981 c. 54; section 20 was amended by the Merchant Shipping (Salvage and Pollution) Act 1994 (c. 28), section 1(6) and Schedule 2, paragraph 6; the Merchant Shipping Act 1995 (c. 21), section 314(2) and Schedule 13, paragraph 59 and by the Merchant Shipping and Maritime Security Act 1997 (c. 28), section 29(1) and Schedule 6, paragraph 2.

2. 1995 c. 21.

3. 1981 c. 54.

4. 1968 c. 18.

5. The text of the Convention is set out in Schedule 7 to the Merchant Shipping Act 1995 (c. 21).

6. 1981 c. 54.

PRACTICE DIRECTION 68 – REFERENCES TO THE EUROPEAN COURT

This Practice Direction supplements CPR Part 68

Wording of references

1.1

Where the court intends to refer a question to the European Court it may direct the parties to produce a draft of the reference but responsibility for the terms of the reference lies with the court making the reference and not with the parties.

1.2

The reference should identify as clearly and succinctly as possible the question on which the court seeks the ruling of the European Court. In choosing the wording of the reference, it should be remembered that it will need to be translated into many other languages.

1.3

The court will incorporate the reference as a schedule to its order. The schedule must –

(1) give the full name of the referring court;

(2) identify the parties;

(3) summarise the nature and history of the proceedings, including the salient facts, indicating whether these are proved or admitted or assumed;

(4) set out the relevant rules of national law;

(5) summarise the relevant contentions of the parties;

(6) explain why a ruling of the European Court is sought;

(7) identify the provisions of Community law which the European Court is being requested to interpret;

(8) state the question on which a ruling of the European Court is sought; and

(9) state any opinion on the answer to the question that may have been expressed by the court in the course of delivering judgment.

1.4

If some of these matters are conveniently set out in a judgment, the relevant passages should be summarised succinctly. If it is not possible to produce such a summary, only those passages that contain information of the kind referred to in paragraph 1.3 should be cited.

1.5

The reference should not exceed 20 pages in length.

Request to apply the urgent preliminary ruling procedure

1A.1

The request to the European Court to apply its urgent preliminary ruling procedure must set out –

(1) the matters of fact and law which establish the urgency;

(2) the reasons why the urgent preliminary ruling procedure applies; and

(3) in so far as possible, the court’s view on the answer to the question referred to the European Court for a preliminary ruling.

Transmission to the European Court

2.1

The order containing the reference, and where relevant any request to the European Court to apply its urgent preliminary ruling procedure, must be sent to the Senior Master, Room E101, Queen’s Bench Division, Royal Courts of Justice, Strand, London, WC2A 2LL, for onward transmission to the European Court.

2.2

The relevant court file must also be sent to the Senior Master at the above address.

European Court Information Note

3.

There are annexed to this Practice Direction –

(1) an Information Note issued by the European Court; and

(2) a supplement to the Information Note following the implementation of the urgent ruling procedure applicable to references concerning the area of freedom, security and justice.

ANNEX 1

Information Note: References from National Courts for a Preliminary Ruling (PDF - opens in new window)

ANNEX 2

Information Note Supplement: Urgent Preliminary Ruling Procedure (PDF - opens in new window)

PART 69 - COURT'S POWER TO APPOINT A RECEIVER

Scope of this Part

69.1

(1) This Part contains provisions about the court's power to appoint a receiver.

(2) In this Part ‘receiver’ includes a manager.

Court's power to appoint receiver

69.2

(1) The court may appoint a receiver –

(a) before proceedings have started;

(b) in existing proceedings; or

(c) on or after judgment.

(2) A receiver must be an individual.

(3) The court may at any time –

(a) terminate the appointment of a receiver; and

(b) appoint another receiver in his place.

(Practice Direction 69 describes the powers for the court to appoint a receiver.)

How to apply for the appointment of a receiver

69.3

An application for the appointment of a receiver –

(a) may be made without notice ; and

(b) must be supported by written evidence.

Service of order appointing receiver

69.4

An order appointing a receiver must be served by the party who applied for it on –

(a) the person appointed as receiver;

(b) unless the court orders otherwise, every other party to the proceedings; and

(c) such other persons as the court may direct.

Security

69.5

(1) The court may direct that before a receiver begins to act or within a specified time he must either –

(a) give such security as the court may determine; or

(b) file and serve on all parties to the proceedings evidence that he already has in force sufficient security,

to cover his liability for his acts and omissions as a receiver.

(2) The court may terminate the appointment of the receiver if he fails to –

(a) give the security; or

(b) satisfy the court as to the security he has in force,

by the date specified.

Receiver's application for directions

69.6

(1) The receiver may apply to the court at any time for directions to assist him in carrying out his function as a receiver.

(2) The court, when it gives directions, may also direct the receiver to serve on any person –

(a) the directions; and

(b) the application for directions.

(Practice Direction 69 makes provision for the form of applications by, and directions to, a receiver.)

Receiver's remuneration

69.7

(1) A receiver may only charge for his services if the court –

(a) so directs; and

(b) specifies the basis on which the receiver is to be remunerated.

(2) The court may specify –

(a) who is to be responsible for paying the receiver; and

(b) the fund or property from which the receiver is to recover his remuneration.

(3) If the court directs that the amount of a receiver's remuneration is to be determined by the court –

(a) the receiver may not recover any remuneration for his services without a determination by the court; and

(b) the receiver or any party may apply at any time for such a determination to take place.

(4) Unless the court orders otherwise, in determining the remuneration of a receiver the court shall award such sum as is reasonable and proportionate in all the circumstances and which takes into account –

(a) the time properly given by him and his staff to the receivership;

(b) the complexity of the receivership;

(c) any responsibility of an exceptional kind or degree which falls on the receiver in consequence of the receivership;

(d) the effectiveness with which the receiver appears to be carrying out, or to have carried out, his duties; and

(e) the value and nature of the subject matter of the receivership.

(5) The court may refer the determination of a receiver's remuneration to a costs judge.

Accounts

69.8

(1) The court may order a receiver to prepare and serve accounts.

(Practice Direction 69 contains provisions about directions for the preparation and service of accounts.)

(2) A party served with such accounts may apply for an order permitting him to inspect any document in the possession of the receiver relevant to those accounts.

(3) Any party may, within 14 days of being served with the accounts, serve notice on the receiver –

(a) specifying any item in the accounts to which he objects;

(b) giving the reason for such objection; and

(c) requiring the receiver, within 14 days of receipt of the notice, either –

(i) to notify all the parties who were served with the accounts that he accepts the objection; or

(ii) if he does not accept the objection, to apply for an examination of the accounts in relation to the contested item.

(4) When the receiver applies for the examination of the accounts he must at the same time file –

(a) the accounts; and

(b) a copy of the notice served on him under this rule.

(5) If the receiver fails to comply with paragraph (3)(c) of this rule, any party may apply to the court for an examination of the accounts in relation to the contested item.

(6) At the conclusion of its examination of the accounts the court will certify the result.

(Practice Direction 40A provides for inquiries into accounts.)

Non-compliance by receiver

69.9

(1) If a receiver fails to comply with any rule, practice direction or direction of the court the court may order him to attend a hearing to explain his non-compliance.

(2) At the hearing the court may make any order it considers appropriate, including –

(a) terminating the appointment of the receiver;

(b) reducing the receiver's remuneration or disallowing it altogether; and

(c) ordering the receiver to pay the costs of any party.

(3) Where –

(a) the court has ordered a receiver to pay a sum of money into court; and

(b) the receiver has failed to do so,

the court may order him to pay interest on that sum for the time he is in default at such rate as it considers appropriate.

Application for discharge of receiver

69.10

(1) A receiver or any party may apply for the receiver to be discharged on completion of his duties.

(2) The application notice must be served on the persons who were required under rule 69.4 to be served with the order appointing the receiver.

Order discharging or terminating appointment of receiver

69.11

(1) An order discharging or terminating the appointment of a receiver may –

(a) require him to pay into court any money held by him; or

(b) specify the person to whom he must pay any money or transfer any assets still in his possession; and

(c) make provision for the discharge or cancellation of any guarantee given by the receiver as security.

(2) The order must be served on the persons who were required under rule 69.4 to be served with the order appointing the receiver.

PRACTICE DIRECTION 69 – COURT'S POWER TO APPOINT A RECEIVER

This practice direction supplements CPR Part 69

Contents of this Practice Direction

Court's power to appoint receiver

1.1  The court's powers to appoint a receiver are set out in –

(1) section 37 of the Senior Courts Act 1981 (powers of the High Court with respect to injunctions and receivers);

(2) section 38 of the County Courts Act 1984 (remedies available in county courts); and

(3) section 107 of the County Courts Act 1984 (receivers by way of equitable execution).

Applications before proceedings are started – rule 69.2(1)(a)

2.1  The court will normally only consider an application for the appointment of a receiver before proceedings are started after notice of the application has been served.

2.2  Rule 25.2(2) contains provisions about the grant of an order before proceedings are started.

Related injunctions

3.1  If a person applies at the same time for –

(1) the appointment of a receiver; and

(2) a related injunction,

he must use the same claim form or application notice for both applications.

3.2  Practice Direction 2B sets out who may grant injunctions. Among other things, it provides that a Master or a District Judge may grant an injunction related to an order appointing a receiver by way of equitable execution.

Evidence in support of an application – rule 69.3

4.1  The written evidence in support of an application for the appointment of a receiver must –

(1) explain the reasons why the appointment is required;

(2) give details of the property which it is proposed that the receiver should get in or manage, including estimates of –

(a) the value of the property; and

(b) the amount of income it is likely to produce;

(3) if the application is to appoint a receiver by way of equitable execution, give details of –

(a) the judgment which the applicant is seeking to enforce;

(b) the extent to which the debtor has failed to comply with the judgment;

(c) the result of any steps already taken to enforce the judgment; and

(d) why the judgment cannot be enforced by any other method; and

(4) if the applicant is asking the court to allow the receiver to act –

(a) without giving security; or

(b) before he has given security or satisfied the court that he has security in place,

explain the reasons why that is necessary.

4.2  In addition, the written evidence should normally identify an individual whom the court is to be asked to appoint as receiver (‘the nominee’), and should –

(1) state the name, address and position of the nominee;

(2) include written evidence by a person who knows the nominee, stating that he believes the nominee is a suitable person to be appointed as receiver, and the basis of that belief; and

(3) be accompanied by written consent, signed by the nominee, to act as receiver if appointed.

4.3  If the applicant does not nominate a person to be appointed as receiver, or if the court decides not to appoint the nominee, the court may –

(1) order that a suitable person be appointed as receiver; and

(2) direct any party to nominate a suitable individual to be appointed.

4.4  A party directed to nominate a person to be appointed as receiver must file written evidence containing the information required by paragraph 4.2 and accompanied by the written consent of the nominee.

Appointment of receiver to enforce a judgment

5.  Where a judgment creditor applies for the appointment of a receiver as a method of enforcing a judgment, in considering whether to make the appointment the court will have regard to –

(1) the amount claimed by the judgment creditor;

(2) the amount likely to be obtained by the receiver; and

(3) the probable costs of his appointment.

Court's directions

6.1  The court may give directions to the receiver when it appoints him or at any time afterwards.

6.2  The court will normally, when it appoints a receiver, give directions in relation to security – see paragraph 7 below.

6.3  Other matters about which the court may give directions include –

(1) whether, and on what basis, the receiver is to be remunerated for carrying out his functions;

(2) the preparation and service of accounts – see rule 69.8(1) and paragraph 10 below;

(3) the payment of money into court; and

(4) authorising the receiver to carry on an activity or incur an expense.

Directions relating to security – rule 69.5

7.1  An order appointing a receiver will normally specify the date by which the receiver must –

(1) give security; or

(2) file and serve evidence to satisfy the court that he already has security in force.

7.2  Unless the court directs otherwise, security will be given –

(1) if the receiver is an authorised insolvency practitioner, by the bond provided by him under the Insolvency Practitioner Regulations 1990 or the Insolvency Practitioners Regulations 2005 extended to cover appointment as a court appointed receiver; or

(2) in any other case, by a guarantee.

7.3  Where the court has given directions about giving security, then either –

(1) written evidence of the bond, the sufficiency of its cover and that it includes appointment as a court appointed receiver must be filed at court; or

(2) a guarantee should be prepared in a form, and entered into with a clearing bank or insurance company, approved by the court.

Receiver's application for directions – rule 69.6

8.1  An application by a receiver for directions may be made by filing an application notice in accordance with Part 23.

8.2  If the directions sought by the receiver are unlikely to be contentious or important to the parties, he may make the application by letter, and the court may reply by letter. In such cases the receiver need not serve his letter or the court's reply on the parties, unless the court orders him to do so.

8.3  Where a receiver applies for directions by letter, the court may direct him to file and serve an application notice.

Receiver's remuneration – rule 69.7

9.1  A receiver may only charge for his services if the court gives directions permitting it and specifying how the remuneration is to be determined.

9.2  The court will normally determine the amount of the receiver's remuneration on the basis of the criteria in rule 69.7(4). Parts 44 to 48 (costs) do not apply to the determination of the remuneration of a receiver.

9.3  Unless the court orders otherwise, the receiver will only be paid or be able to recover his remuneration after the amount of it has been determined.

9.4  An application by a receiver for the amount of his remuneration to be determined must be supported by –

(1) written evidence showing –

(a) on what basis the remuneration is claimed; and

(b) that it is justified and in accordance with this Part; and

(2) a certificate signed by the receiver that he considers that the remuneration he claims is reasonable and proportionate.

9.5  The court may, before determining the amount of a receiver's remuneration –

(1) require the receiver to provide further information in support of his claim; and

(2) appoint an assessor under rule 35.15 to assist the court.

9.6  Paragraphs 9.1 to 9.5 do not apply to expenses incurred by a receiver in carrying out his functions. These are accounted for as part of his account for the assets he has recovered, and not dealt with as part of the determination of his remuneration.

Accounts – rule 69.8

10.1  When the court gives directions under rule 69.8(1) for the receiver to prepare and serve accounts, it may –

(1) direct the receiver to prepare and serve accounts either by a specified date or at specified intervals; and

(2) specify the persons on whom he must serve the accounts.

10.2  A party should not apply for an order under rule 69.8(2) permitting him to inspect documents in the possession of the receiver, without first asking the receiver to permit such inspection without an order.

10.3  Where the court makes an order under rule 69.8(2), it will normally direct that the receiver must –

(1) permit inspection within 7 days after being served with the order; and

(2) provide a copy of any documents the subject of the order within 7 days after receiving a request for a copy from the party permitted to inspect them, provided that party has undertaken to pay the reasonable cost of making and providing the copy.

PRACTICE DIRECTION 81 – APPLICATIONS AND PROCEEDINGS IN RELATION TO CONTEMPT OF COURT

This Practice Direction supplements CPR Part 81

SECTION 2 OF PART 81 – Committal for breach of a judgment, order or undertaking to do or abstain from doing an act

Requirement for a penal notice on judgments and orders –form of penal notice – Rule 81.9

1.

A judgment or order which restrains a party from doing an act or requires an act to be done must, if disobedience is to be dealt with by proceedings for contempt of court, have a penal notice endorsed on it as follows (or in words to substantially the same effect) –

“If you the within-named [   ] do not comply with this order you may be held to be in contempt of court and imprisoned or fined, or your assets may be seized.”

Requirement for a penal notice on judgments and orders –undertakings – Rule 81.9

2.1

The provisions of paragraph 8.1 of Practice Direction 40B – Judgments and orders that supplements Part 40 apply to an order which contains an undertaking by a party to do or not do an act, subject to paragraph 2.2 below.

(Paragraph 8.1 of Practice Direction 40B contains provisions about specifying the time within which acts must be done.)

2.2

The court may decline to –

(1) accept an undertaking; and

(2) deal with disobedience in respect of an undertaking by contempt of court proceedings,

unless the party giving the undertaking has made a signed statement to the effect that that party understands the terms of the undertaking and the consequences of failure to comply with it.

2.3

The statement may be endorsed on the order containing the undertaking or may be filed in a separate document such as a letter.

2.4

Where the order containing an undertaking is made in a county court, form N117 may be used.

SECTION 4 OF PART 81 – (1) Certifications by any court, tribunal etc to the High Court under any enactment; (2) Applications to the High Court under section 336 of the Charities Act 2011

Scope of Section 4 of Part 81

3.

Section 4 of Part 81 contains rules in relation to statutory powers of the High Court to commit any person for contempt in respect of anything done or not done in relation to a court, tribunal or person. The statutory powers include –

(1) section 336 of the Charities Act 2011;

(2) sections 436 and 453C of the Companies Act 1985;

(3) paragraph 8 of Schedule 6 to the Data Protection Act 1998; and

(4) sections 18, 161 and 232 of the Financial Services and Markets Act 2000.

SECTION 5 OF PART 81 – Contempt in the face of the court

Committal for contempt in the face of the court – Rule 81.16

4.1

Where the committal proceedings relate to a contempt in the face of the court the matters referred to in paragraph 4.3 should be given particular attention. Normally, it will be appropriate to defer consideration of the respondent's actions and behaviour to allow the respondent time to reflect on what has occurred. The time needed for the following procedures should allow such a period of reflection.

4.2

A Part 8 claim form and an application notice are not required for contempt falling under Section 5 of Part 81, but other provisions of this Practice Direction should be applied, as necessary, or adapted to the circumstances.

4.3

The judge should –

(1) tell the respondent of the possible penalty that the respondent faces;

(2) inform the respondent in detail, and preferably in writing, of the actions and behaviour of the respondent which have given rise to the committal application;

(3) if the judge considers that an apology would remove the need for the committal application, tell the respondent;

(4) have regard to the need for the respondent to be –

(a) allowed a reasonable time for responding to the committal application, including, if necessary, preparing a defence;

(b) made aware of the availability of assistance from the Community Legal Service and how to contact the Service;

(c) given the opportunity, if unrepresented, to obtain legal advice;

(d) if unable to understand English, allowed to make arrangements, seeking the court’s assistance if necessary, for an interpreter to attend the hearing; and

(e) brought back before the court for the committal application to be heard within a reasonable time;

(5) allow the respondent an opportunity to –

(a) apologise to the court;

(b) explain the respondent’s actions and behaviour; and

(c) if the contempt is proved, to address the court on the penalty to be imposed on the respondent; and

(6) where appropriate, nominate a suitable person to give the respondent the information. (It is likely to be appropriate to nominate a person where the effective communication of information by the judge to the respondent was not possible when the incident occurred.)

4.4

If there is a risk of the appearance of bias, the judge should ask another judge to hear the committal application.

4.5

Where the committal application is to be heard by another judge, a written statement by the judge before whom the actions and behaviour of the respondent which have given rise to the committal application took place may be admitted as evidence of those actions and behaviour.

SECTION 6 OF PART 81 – Committal for making a false statement of truth or disclosure statement

Committal application in relation to a false statement of truth or disclosure statement – Rule 81.18

5.1

Rules 81.18(1)(b) and 81.18(3)(b) provide that a committal application may be made by the Attorney General. However, the Attorney General prefers a request that comes from the court to one made direct by a party to the proceedings in which the alleged contempt occurred without prior consideration by the court. A request to the Attorney General is not a way of appealing against, or reviewing, the decision of the judge.

5.2

Where the permission of the court is sought under rule 81.18(1)(a) or 81.18(3)(a) so that rule 81.14 is applied by rule 81.18(2) or 81.18(4), the affidavit evidence in support of the application must –

(1) identify the statement said to be false;

(2) explain –

(a) why it is false; and

(b) why the maker knew the statement to be false at the time it was made; and

(3) explain why contempt proceedings would be appropriate in the light of the overriding objective in Part 1.

5.3

The court may –

(1) exercise any of its powers under the rules (including the power to give directions under rule 81.14(6));

(2) initiate steps to consider if there is a contempt of court and, where there is, to punish it; or

(3) as provided by rule 81.18(5), direct that the matter be referred to the Attorney General with a request to consider whether to bring proceedings for contempt of court.

5.4

A request to the Attorney General to consider whether to bring proceedings for contempt of court must be made in writing and sent to the Attorney General’s Office at 20 Victoria Street, London, SW1H 0NF.

5.5

A request to the Attorney General must be accompanied by a copy of any order directing that the matter be referred to the Attorney General and must –

(1) identify the statement said to be false;

(2) explain –

(a) why it is false; and

(b) why the maker knew the statement to be false at the time it was made; and

(3) explain why contempt proceedings would be appropriate in the light of the overriding objective in Part 1.

5.6

Once the applicant receives the result of the request to the Attorney General, the applicant must send a copy of it to the court that will deal with the committal application, and the court will give such directions as it sees fit.

5.7

The rules do not change the law of contempt or introduce new categories of contempt. A person applying to commence such proceedings should consider whether the incident complained of does amount to contempt of court and whether such proceedings would further the overriding objective in Part 1.

SECTION 7 OF PART 81 – Writ of sequestration to enforce a judgment, order or undertaking

Requirement for a penal notice on judgments and orders –form of penal notice – Rule 81.25

6.

Paragraphs 1 and 2.1 to 2.4 apply to judgments and orders to be enforced by a writ of sequestration.

Levying execution on certain days

7.1

Unless the court orders otherwise, a writ of sequestration to enforce a judgment, order or undertaking must not be executed on a Sunday, Good Friday or Christmas Day.

7.2

Paragraph 7.1 does not apply to an Admiralty claim in rem.

SECTION 8 OF PART 81 – General rules about committal applications, orders for committal and writs of sequestration

General rules

8.1

Subject to paragraph 8.2, this Section of the Practice Direction applies in relation to all matters covered by Part 81.

8.2

Where there is a conflict between the provisions in this Section of the Practice Direction and specific provisions elsewhere in this Practice Direction or in Part 81, the specific provisions prevail.

Human rights

9.

In all cases the Convention rights of those involved should particularly be borne in mind. It should be noted that the standard of proof, having regard to the possibility that a person may be sent to prison, is that the allegation be proved beyond reasonable doubt.

(Section 1 of the Human Rights Act 1998 defines ’the Convention rights’.)

Court to which applications should be made and levels of judiciary

10.1

A committal application or an application for permission to make a committal application –

(1) may be made in a county court if the alleged contempt is a contempt which a county court has power to punish; and

(2) must otherwise be made in the High Court.

10.2

Except where under an enactment a Master or district judge has power to make a committal order, a committal order can only be made–

(1) in High Court proceedings, by a High Court Judge or a person authorised to act as such; or

(2) in county court proceedings, by a Circuit Judge or a person authorised to act as such.

10.3

Paragraph 10.4 applies in relation to proceedings in any court (the first court) where the judge or judges exercising the jurisdiction of the first court are deemed to constitute a court of the High Court by virtue of an enactment.

10.4

The reference in paragraph 10.2(1) to a High Court Judge will be construed as a reference to a judge of the first court.

General rules about applications: applications which cannot be made without permission

11.

If the committal application is one which cannot be made without permission –

(1) the permission may only be granted by a judge who would have power to hear the committal application if permission were granted;

(2) the date on which and the name of the judge by whom the requisite permission was granted must be stated on the claim form or application notice by which the committal application is commenced;

(3) the claim form or application notice may not be issued or filed until the requisite permission has been granted; and

(4) Rules 23.9 and 23.10 do not apply.

General rules about applications: applications by claim form

12.

If the application for permission to make a committal application or the committal application is commenced by the issue of a claim form –

(1) Part 8 will apply –

(a) subject to the provisions of Part 81 and this Practice Direction, in particular sub-paragraphs (2) to (4);

(b) as though references to‘claimant’ were references to the applicant; and

(c) as though references to‘defendant’ were references to the respondent;

(2) an amendment to the claim form may be made with the permission of the court but not otherwise;

(3) rule 8.4 does not apply; and

(4) the claim form must contain a prominent notice stating the possible consequences of the court making a committal order and of the respondent not attending the hearing. A form of notice which may be used is annexed to this Practice Direction at Annex 3.

General rules about applications: applications by application notice

13.1

Where the application is made by application notice, the application notice must state that the application is made in the proceedings in question, and its title and reference number must correspond with the title and reference number of those proceedings.

13.2

If the application for permission to make a committal application or the committal application is commenced by the filing of an application notice –

(1) Part 23 will apply subject to the provisions of Part 81 and this Practice Direction, in particular sub-paragraphs (2) to (4);

(2) an amendment to the application notice may be made with the permission of the court but not otherwise;

(3) the court may not dispose of the application without a hearing; and

(4) the application notice must contain a prominent notice stating the possible consequences of the court making a committal order and of the respondent not attending the hearing. A form of notice which may be used is annexed to this Practice Direction at Annex 3.

Evidence and information

14.1

Written evidence in support of or in opposition to a committal application must be given by affidavit.

14.2

Written evidence served in support of or in opposition to a committal application must, unless the court otherwise directs, be filed.

14.3

The following rules do not apply to committal applications –

(1) rule 35.7 (Court’s power to direct that evidence is to be given by a single joint expert);

(2) rule 35.8 (Instructions to single joint expert); and

(3) rule 35.9 (Power of court to direct a party to provide information).

14.4

An order under rule 18.1 (Obtaining further information) may not be made against a respondent to a committal application.

The hearing – Rule 81.28

15.1

When issuing or filing the claim form or application notice for a committal application, the applicant must obtain from the court a date for the hearing of the committal application.

15.2

Unless the court otherwise directs, the hearing date of a committal application must not be less than 14 days after service of the claim form or application notice on the respondent. The hearing date must be specified in the claim form or application notice or in a Notice of Hearing attached to and served with the claim form or application notice.

15.3

Paragraphs 15.1 and 15.2 apply to certifications of conduct and applications under section 336 of the Charities Act 2011 (‘section 336 application’) referred to in Section 4 of Part 81 as if references to the claim form or application notice were references to the certification or section 336 application.

(The definition of‘applicant’ in rule 81.3 includes a person who makes a committal application by way of certification or section 336 application.)

15.4

The court may on the hearing date –

(1) give case management directions with a view to a hearing of the committal application on a future date; or

(2) if the committal application is ready to be heard, proceed to hear it.

15.5

In dealing with any committal application, the court will have regard to the need for the respondent to have details of the alleged acts of contempt and the opportunity to respond to the committal application.

15.6

The court will also have regard to the need for the respondent to be –

(1) allowed a reasonable time for responding to the committal application including, if necessary, preparing a defence;

(2) made aware of the availability of assistance from the Community Legal Service and how to contact the Service;

(3) given the opportunity, if unrepresented, to obtain legal advice; and

(4) if unable to understand English, allowed to make arrangements, seeking the assistance of the court if necessary, for an interpreter to attend the hearing.

Striking out, procedural defects and discontinuance

16.1

On application by the respondent or on its own initiative, the court may strike out a committal application if it appears to the court –

(1) that the application and the evidence served in support of it disclose no reasonable ground for alleging that the respondent is guilty of a contempt of court;

(2) that the application is an abuse of the court's process or, if made in existing proceedings, is otherwise likely to obstruct the just disposal of those proceedings; or

(3) that there has been a failure to comply with a rule, practice direction or court order.

16.2

The court may waive any procedural defect in the commencement or conduct of a committal application if satisfied that no injustice has been caused to the respondent by the defect.

16.3

A committal application may not be discontinued without the permission of the court.

Annex 1Rule 81.15(4)– Certifications of conduct, and applications under section 336 of the Charities Act 2011, to the High Court under Section 4 of Part 81

Form of certification, or section 336 application

Form of certification, or section 336 application (PDF - opens in new window)

Annex 2Rule 81.15(7)– Certifications of conduct, and applications under section 336 of the Charities Act 2011, to the High Court under Section 4 of Part 81

Form of acknowledgment of service (N210C)

Form of acknowledgment of service (N210C) (PDF - opens in new window)

Annex 3Paragraphs 12(4) and 13.2(4)

Form of penal notice to be included on committal applications

IMPORTANT NOTICE

The Court has power to send you to prison, to fine you or seize your assets if it finds that any of the allegations made against you are true and amount to a contempt of court. You must attend court on the date shown on the front of this form. It is in your own interest to do so. You should bring with you any witnesses and documents which you think will help you put your side of the case. If you consider the allegations are not true you must tell the court why. If it is established that they are true, you must tell the court of any good reason why they do not amount to a contempt of court, or, if they do, why you should not be punished. If you need advice, you should show this document at once to your solicitor or go to a Citizens’ Advice Bureau or similar organisation.